hey guys welcome back to the channel if
you're new here my name is ali i'm a
junior doctor working in cambridge and
in this video i want to share three
books that have really changed my life
over the last few years and i'll be
sharing some of the lessons that i got
from each of these along with some
quotes before we get started i just want
to say a big thank you to blinkist for
sponsoring this video they're a
fantastic app that lets you read
summaries of popular non-fiction books
so you can learn the lessons from them
and at the end of the video i'll talk
about the value that i derive from
blinkist and how it fits into my life as
a doctor youtuber but yeah let's just
get started by talking about book number
one
this is the four hour work week by tim
ferriss subtitle escape the nine to five
live anywhere and join the new rich
essentially this book is the author
talking about his story but also giving
some tips about how you can if you want
to you can quit your job and set up
businesses with automated streams of
income and essentially creating a system
whereby your businesses are generating
you money without you having to
physically do work for that and then
you're able to travel the world and live
this sort of lifestyle that everyone
thinks is just the exclusive domain of
rich people like for example when i was
growing up i just had in my head this
vague notion that a one day would be
cool to be rich and if i were to really
examine that i would have thought oh
well i guess because if you're rage then
you can like travel and stuff and then
you don't have to work and stuff and the
idea that he talks about here is that
actually a lot of this whole life of a
rich person ie you know just the idea of
being able to travel and live on a beach
in thailand all this sort of stuff is
available surprisingly cheaply like for
just a few thousand dollars per month
you can live like a really really really
rich person in places like thailand and
like argentina and other cool places
like that rather than you know do this
whole thing that we all get trained to
do ie work really hard go to a good
university get a fantastic job work
super super super hard and then make
loads of money so that when you retire
then you can be happy rather than doing
that instead it's more about you know
why are we why are we working to retire
when we're in our 60s and we've got
osteoarthritis in both our knees instead
why don't we take those 20 years of
retirement and spread them out
throughout our life so he he suggests
that we all try this thing of mini
retirements where each year you take a
few months off and you go traveling
while running your business remotely
from your laptop or whatever which
sounds all scammy and stuff but if you
have even a passing interest in
entrepreneurship or setting up your own
business or if the idea of being able to
travel the world while your businesses
generate money while you sleep if that
seems even remotely intriguing to you
then you should definitely read this
book to be honest you've probably read
it already but the impact it's already
had on me is that this has been the book
that has
pretty much single-handedly allowed me
to set up my business so i set up a
company while i was in medical school
six years ago
2013. six years ago now um and we run
courses for medical school applicants
then made like an online question bank
and some online courses and all this
stuff
and that company's been doing really
well it's done six figures in revenue
pretty much every year since it started
with five figure corporation tax bills
thank you her majesty's revenue and
customs and i was able to run that
company alongside studying medicine at
cambridge and doing reasonably well in
my exams because of the stuff that i
learned in this book so all the
productivity tips and tricks things like
outsourcing to remote workers that was a
big reason as to why some of our
question banks were really successful a
big reason as to why my own mental
health wasn't completely destroyed by
you know the challenge of running a
company alongside being a medical
student so this was all the stuff that i
learned from this book uh i'll stop
waffling all about it but yeah any
interest at all in entrepreneurship or
anything like that definitely give this
a read and check out his podcast the tim
ferriss show it's absolutely wonderful
so yeah let's move on to book number two
all right this is a tiny book called
show your work by austin cleon and this
has been another book that has been
really pivotal to my life it's really
small it took me about half an hour to
read it on kindle and actually i only
only bought these physical copies so
that i could show them off in this video
but yeah
i'm gonna have this around the house now
and gonna be re revisiting the lessons
in it whenever i pick it up anyway um
this has been a really pivotal book in
my life because
for a long time like ever since i
started medical school and started
running this company six med i'd been
sort of toying with the idea of setting
up a personal blog and kind of writing
about some of the lessons that i gained
and you know book reviews and things
like that and i'd never been able to get
over the fear of
personal like self-promotion that you
know it's
people are going to judge me people are
going to think i'm an arrogant
narcissistic [ __ ] for having the
audacity to have a blog you know with my
domain like aliabdal.com i mean who's
got their own name as a domain name
unless you're like super rich and super
famous blah blah i used to have all
these negative thoughts about this whole
stuff and then in january 2016 i read
show your work by austin cleon and that
completely changed the game for me it
made me realize that actually um
even if you're not an expert in anything
just the fact that you have done
anything at all means that you can then
write about that experience and there
will be people somewhere in the world
who will find that helpful so for
example setting up a company in med
school like you know it's it's not a
very common thing and it's the sort of
thing a lot of people would be
interested in therefore if i just write
about it and i can share the lessons
that i've learned and just kind of help
people and that's the main idea that
this book says is that by sharing your
work with the world you are working
towards helping people and that is going
to be an inherent good so after reading
this i started my own blog i started
writing a few posts that year and i
think if it hadn't been for this book i
wouldn't have even set up this youtube
channel because
starting that blog was the small step
that made me comfortable with the idea
of putting myself out there and you know
i've had so many messages from people
asking advice for starting a youtube
channel and oh how do you get over the
fear and there really isn't a way to get
over the fear but i think you know
taking small steps reading this book
lets you see that actually there isn't
really much to be afraid of and
sharing yourself and your work with the
world is only really going to be a good
thing if the message that you're sharing
is positive so yeah i've i've now had in
the realm of like over over 2 000
messages and comments from people all
around the world who have been inspired
or have been
you know have learned something from the
content that i've put out from the work
that i've shared i've shown and i think
if it weren't for this book that i read
three years ago none of this would have
happened so thank you austin cleon for
encouraging me to become more okay with
the idea of putting myself out there
if this is something that you ever
you've ever thought about if you have
something to say if you think you might
have something to say if you like the
idea of maybe writing stuff and sharing
it with the world even if you don't if
you're any kind like if you make any
kind of content at all if you're if
you're an artist if you're a painter if
you're a writer anything like that
you'll just really really benefit from
reading this book because
it's it takes like half an hour to read
there's no time at all you can buy on
amazon i'll stick a link in the
description below and
you'll love it it'll change your life
like it did mine i hope
and last but obviously not least is
anything you want this again really tiny
book by derek sivers that takes like
half an hour to read as well 40 lessons
for a new kind of entrepreneur and yeah
it's got the word entrepreneur in the
title but even if you're not an
entrepreneur i think you can still gain
a lot from this book um pretty much
anyone everyone everyone should read
this book because it's a lot of lessons
for life not just for entrepreneurship
anyway this had enormous impact on me as
well and i can honestly say that this
really changed my life uh derek sivers
is a guy he set up a company called
ctbaby many years ago um grew it to like
an 80-man operation with millions and
millions in revenue then sold it for
like 20 million dollars and you know
gave that money to like this charitable
trust for musical education stuff like
that anyway um in this book he talks
about his story of how he got started
with the company but also a very
counter-intuitive approach to business
and also to life i.e
not chasing growth all the time and
actually just
trying to make something that you enjoy
running and you enjoy the process off
and you're having fun and that you're
helping people that's such a novel thing
in the world you know where every
startup is just aiming to get that
billion dollar evaluation and aiming for
growth at all costs but this was like a
very nice very nice thing and for me
this is a book that i'll always hold
really dear because when i was in my
fourth year approaching the end of my
fourth year of medical school i'd been
running my company six med for that for
like three years at that point and we'd
been growing in terms of revenue every
year in terms of student numbers it was
taking up more and more of my time but
then around 2016 our growth started to
stagnate and even dip a little i'd never
really experienced anything like that
before where you know you've grown
something and it keeps on growing and
then suddenly it stops and then you're
like oh wow it's on the decline and this
made me really really sad during the
summer holidays in my fourth year and i
can remember kind of lying in bed awake
thinking you know whatever what have i
done where have i gone wrong have i
screwed up my life by throwing away this
fantastic opportunity i had and then i
came across this book there's one quote
in particular that i want to share from
here and it's on in this chapter yeah
okay so in this chapter he's talking
about how sometimes mba types you know
people with mbas masters and business
administrations would ask me what's your
growth rate what's your retained
earnings rate as a percentage of growth
what are your projections for your
company he's talking about his own
company i just say i have no idea i
don't even know what some of that means
i started this as a hobby to help my
friends and that's the only reason it
exists there's money in the bank and i'm
doing fine so no worries
and then he goes on to say and this is
probably my favorite quote of all time
and i a quote that i return to
many times a month whenever i'm feeling
down or whenever i'm feeling
like explain in a minute here's here's
the quote uh never forget why you're
really doing what you're doing are you
helping people are they happy are you
happy are you profitable isn't that
enough question mark
and this is just
like if there are if there are three
lines like you know
any time i read this it just makes me
feel infinitely better because
like
doing stuff like running a business
where you're aiming for growth and
revenues and profits and stuff and also
now this thing of having a youtube
channel having this like social media
following having an email list and
everything that i'm now doing in my life
with the exception of my you know
full-time job of being a doctor all
these other things are all geared
towards
making stuff and then trying to grow the
brand or the your subscriber count or
the revenue or whatever and
that can be quite uh
i don't want to say stressful i don't
like the word stressful it can be quite
uh
it's
it's it's something that that often
plays on my mind and i know from
speaking to other people doing this sort
of stuff that it plays in their minds as
well and the idea being that whenever
you're relaxing or spending time with
friends or family and stuff you're sort
of in the back of your mind you're
thinking
you know i could be making a video right
now and if i you know if i don't churn
out that that video this week then you
know the algorithm is not going to rank
my channel highly enough or you know i
could be writing a blog post for six men
about how to get to megas medical school
right now and then that'll rank us
highly for search engine optimization
then more people are going to find our
courses then we'll get more revenue and
you just kind of
go down this spiral where any time
you're not working you feel super super
super guilty for it and you can't really
enjoy life because you have this amazing
thing that
you've somehow you know by the grace of
god you've got this youtube channel or
this company and
you know you have to keep putting work
into them to make them grow but you also
want to live a life on the side and just
this this quote it's just it's just
amazing like never forget why you're
really doing what you're doing are you
helping people are they happy are you
happy are you profitable isn't that
enough
so whenever i find myself thinking oh
you know i should make another video so
i can you know something about ad
revenues or oh my ad revenues have
dropped this month because i haven't
made an ipad video in a while or any
anything like that i just you know open
this book on my kindle find my
highlighted quote and just read that
because
it just makes me appreciate that you
know
the revenue isn't important you know
i'm enjoying what i'm doing which is
fantastic i've got this amazing thing
going on the side and in addition to my
full-time job which i also quite enjoy
uh it's making a reasonable amount it's
it's making an incredible amount of
money actually and it's not an amount of
money that i'd ever dreamed i could have
been making especially at this age and
therefore you know it's helping people i
get messages from people who are all
happy because i've inspired them or you
know help them learn something or help
them out with their exams or getting
into med school and i'm happy doing it i
think people are happy watching these
videos i hope people are happy watching
these videos and that's that's enough
that that's all we really need and a lot
of burnout
within entrepreneurship within youtubers
within bloggers within any anything like
this comes from people
working too hard to grow the numbers to
grow the audience to grow everything and
i think if anyone is stuck in that
position or even if you're not this is
just like a really good book for general
life advice yeah anything you want derek
sivers
one of my favorite books had a big
impact on my life because it's helped me
become more happy and at peace with this
whole kind of running an online
entrepreneurship empire thing and by a
strong word i don't mean i'm fine just
like you know being an online online
person who tries to make money online
and stuff just really really really good
book
okay this whole video has been a lot
more waffley than i intended but i hope
you guys enjoyed it if you did can you
let me know in the comments or if you
didn't again i'd love to hear some
constructive advice as to what you would
do differently um if you know i do want
to do more book reviews and stuff and
i've read a lot of books over the years
thanks to having a kindle and thanks to
blinkist which i'll talk more about in a
second i've read so many books over the
years and i do want to talk more about
books on this channel and yeah so any
kind of feedback about about the format
would be great and before we finish i
just want to tell you about blinkist
which is a fantastic app uh and what
they do is that they take
all the important lessons from thousands
of non-fiction books and they summarize
them into these like 15-minute summaries
that you can either read or listen to so
the way i use blinkist is that if i ever
come across a recommendation for a
non-fiction book i search through
blinkist and see if i can find it and
add it to my library this is just a
quick scroll through some of the books
that i've read on blinkist oh four hour
work week um
and essentially they've summarized the
salient points of the book in this
series of like i don't know 15 13 13
blinks that you can read through in
about 15 minutes if you're like me and
you find yourself strapped for time and
you have all these book recommendations
being thrown at you and you just don't
really know where to begin this is a
great place to start where you can read
a summary of the book get the most
important lessons and if that's all you
need then that's fine you can just take
that away or if you want to find out
more then you can actually buy the book
and read it properly so yeah four hour
work week for our body seth godin's
marketing books seven habits of highly
effective people that was one that i
read on blinkist it's a massive book
i've never read it in real life but
because i've read it on blinkist i feel
like i've got the main lessons from it
so i haven't needed to read it in real
life which has saved me about 100 hours
of my life but yeah blinkish is pretty
great and if you want to try it then
there's a link in the video description
and it's going to appear over here and
the first 100 people to use that link
will get unlimited access to blinkist
the premium subscription where you've
got access to all of their library of
thousands of books completely free for
one week and you can decide if you like
it then if you do like it if you use my
code a link then you'll get 25 off a
paid subscription as well i'd recommend
it i think there are a lot of lessons
that you can gain from these non-fiction
books i think
the fact that they're all summarized in
blinkist means that it's very easy to
access them and you know it does cost a
bit of money for an annual subscription
but
if you're anything like me then you know
ideas from a single book can completely
change your life so you know why not why
why not go for it but yeah uh thank you
blinkers for sponsoring this video i
think you guys are great and i'll
continue to use blinkist whenever i get
a recommendation to decide if i then
want to read the book so yeah that
brings us to the end of this video thank
you so much for watching this has been
the first time i've tried doing like a
book thing on the channel um but as i
said let me know if you have any
comments i'd love to hear from you
thanks for watching if you liked the
video please give it a thumbs up if you
haven't subscribed to the channel then
please consider doing so have a lovely
day and i'll see you in the next video
goodbye