this book The Almanac of nval rakan is
one of the best books I have ever read
about Financial Freedom and in this
episode of book club which is the
ongoing Series where for the last 5
years I've been distilling And
discussing highlights and summaries from
some of my favorite books we are going
to be talking about the five key
components of the Financial Freedom
equation all right so the first key idea
from the book is to find and build
specific knowledge now this is probably
the thing that is most confusing about
the stuff that Nal writes in that like
what is specific knowledge well here is
what he says in the book about what
specific knowledge is he writes specific
knowledge is knowledge you cannot be
trained for if Society can train you it
can train someone else and replace you
secondly he says specific knowledge is
found by pursuing your genuine curiosity
and passion rather than whatever is hot
right now thirdly building specific
knowledge will feel like play to you but
will look like work to others fourth
when specific knowledge is taught it's
through apprenticeships not schools and
five specific knowledge is often highly
technical or creative it cannot be
outsourced or automated and the way that
I understand the concept of specific
knowledge is that it's this combination
Knowledge and Skills that is somewhat
unique to you so Nal writes that when I
talk about specific knowledge I mean
figure out what you were doing as a kid
or teenager almost effortlessly
something you didn't even consider a
skill but people around you noticed your
mother or your best friend growing up
would know an example that nval uses is
maybe you had an obsessive personality
you dive into things and remember them
quickly or maybe you have a love for
science fiction you are into reading
sci-fi which means you absorb a lot of
knowledge very quickly maybe you play a
lot of games so you understand Game
Theory pretty well and if I use myself
as an example there were broadly three
things that I was was kind of super into
when I was a kid and a teenager the
first one was reading a lot of books the
second one was trying to build stuff so
this was like Legos and like airplane
models when I was kid and then like
websites and like web development e type
like trying to Tinker away and build
things and the third thing is that I
always really really liked teaching I
would always be teaching students who
were younger than me or students in the
class who would ask me for help and
stuff like that and teaching is
something that came very naturally to me
and I found myself effortlessly drawn to
it now nval would probably call this
combination of factors some kind of
specific knowledge and in the
intersection of these things like
reading a lot of books and enjoying
teaching and enjoying building stuff
that is sort of morphed into this career
that I've stumbled into where I make
videos and I write books and I like do
reviews of books and and stuff like that
but I didn't get here by setting out 20
years ago to become a YouTuber doing
productivity stuff and writing self-help
books it was more a case of pursuing
what I was genuinely interested in and
curious about rather than by trying to
find the most efficient way to learn a
skill that can make money or whatever
that might be Nal writes specific
knowledge is found much more by pursuing
your innate talents your genuine
curiosity and your passion it's not by
going to school for whatever is the
hottest job it's not by going into
whatever field investors say is the
hottest all right so one of the things
we're going to talk about later in this
video is the concept of Leverage and the
concept of media based leverage and that
is where the sponsor of this video comes
in which is Riverside Riverside is your
all-in-one online studio for video and
podcasting both recording and editing
and it makes it incredibly easy to
create high quality content right from
your browser I absolutely love Riverside
I've been using it for years to record
podcasts and remote interviews super
easily it's super easy to use and it
integrates really nicely into a workflow
for video and podcast production and the
great thing about Riverside is that it's
built specifically for creators like us
not only does it let me record in up to
4K but the editing features are really
good and save a ton of time as well for
example with multitrack editing we can
adjust individual tracks mute certain
parts or even add scenes automatically
and the AI producer is incredibly
helpful when I do podcasts with me and
my brother we don't want to deal with
all the faf of having to manually edit
things and so you just click a button
and the AI automatically removes
silencers and switches camera angles and
everything and it's just absolutely
incredible oh and the AI producer also
adds perfectly animated captions to your
videos which is fantastic especially if
you're doing short form content content
that has like the captions baked in now
if you want to try a Riverside here is a
special offer just for you the first
1,000 people to click the link in the
video description and use my coupon code
will get 3 months of Riverside Pro
completely for free that is exclusive
access to all of their Pro features for
3 months for absolutely no cost at all
so if you ready to take your content
creation to the next level and get your
media based leverage which is one of the
things we're going to talk about then
definitely check out the Riverside using
the link below I absolutely love
Riverside been using it for years we'll
continue to use it for years and thank
you so much Riverside for sponsoring
this video and so if you're at this
point in the video the question you
could be asking yourself is what could
my own specific knowledge be and there's
a few different ways of thinking about
this so firstly you can think about
internal versus external motivation you
want to ask yourself what are the sorts
of things I am internally intrinsically
motivated to learn more and find out
more about this could for example be the
difference between someone who when they
were a kid or a teenager would take
apart computers for fun versus someone
who learns to code because they've heard
that Tech pays really well so when
you're internally motivated to do stuff
then it's probably stuff that you would
be reading about in your spare time or
maybe talking about that thing with
friends friends maybe a bit too much and
it's probably the thing that you would
find yourself drawn to even if you
weren't getting paid for it now if you
compare this to external motivation
that's when you're following market
trends like hey I hear AI agents are
really hot right now so let me build an
interest in AI agents and you'll have a
sense of constantly checking whether the
thing is profitable yet this is like the
difference between someone who starts a
YouTube channel because they love the
idea of personal self- expression versus
someone who starts a YouTube channel
because they think it'll make them money
and if you're in that category where
you're only starting a YouTube channel
because you think it'll make you money
then you're constantly going to be
checking to see have I made money yet
have I made money yet have made money
yeah and given that it takes ages to
make money and it's not even guaranteed
chances are if you are chasing starting
a YouTube channel or any kind of skill
because you see the money on the other
end of the thing chances are you won't
stick to it long enough for it to
actually work and you probably won't
enjoy it very much either which means
you will be out competed if it's a zero
some game by people who genuinely do
enjoy the thing secondly you can think
of building specific knowledge in the
sense of process versus outcome are you
focused on the process or are you
focused on the outcome and generally the
vibe is that if you're building specific
knowledge I.E things that you can't be
trained for things that are found by
pursuing your genuine curiosity and
passion if you're genuinely leaning into
your own natural inclinations then
chances are you'll get lost in the
process rather than being fixated on the
outcome and thirdly something that nval
often talks about in interviews is that
if you're looking for specific knowledge
you want to be looking at what are the
intersections or the unusual or unique
combinations that are specific to you
and true valuable specific knowledge
often comes from combining interests in
a way that might seem strange to other
people at first like if we take someone
like Joe Rogan for example he starts off
as a comedian and then he gets into
fighting and then he gets into like
commentating on like martial arts fights
and stuff and then he develops a skill
to just have a conversation with anyone
and then he starts a podcast which ends
up becoming like one of the biggest
podcasts in the world but this
combination of like comedian plus
fighter plus commentator plus
interviewer that's kind of an
interesting combination that not many
people in the world have or if you look
at Naval rabhan himself like there are
thousands and thousands of investors out
there but Naval is one of the most
wellknown not because he is a
particularly good investor but because
he combines the investing
entrepreneurial stuff with
philosophizing on Twitter and writing
essays and these tweet storms about
stuff like this like wealth and
happiness and health and how to how to
get rich without getting lucky and it's
this combination of the philosophizing
with the investing e thing that leads to
an interesting combination that makes
Naval much more wellknown than most
other investors who maybe specialize
just in the investing component again
what this is trying to get at is that if
you really want to become wealthy if you
want to be financially free don't just
follow the previously pre- trodden paths
because if there was genuinely a path
that you could literally just you know
stack the blocks and like follow the
path to a tea and then that would get
you rich everyone would already be doing
that and that would be priced into the
amount of money you can make from the
thing and so to round off this section
here are a couple of prompts that can
help you think about finding your own
specific knowledge firstly what do you
do on weekends that feels like play to
you but looks like work to other people
secondly what topics make you lose track
of time when you're learning about them
thirdly what unique combinations of
interests do you have that seem
unrelated and four what do your friends
constantly ask your advice about all of
these are different ways of getting at
what could your specific knowledge be to
find within yourself innately and then
to build upon that but having specific
knowledge alone isn't enough if you want
to build wealth or if you want to build
Financial Freedom without getting lucky
there's all sorts of people out there
like researchers and developers and
people with deep deep unique expertise
who haven't achieved Financial Freedom
because they're missing the other
components of this little Financial
Freedom equation and that brings us on
to component number two which is
[Music]
accountability now as it relates to
accountability what Nal says is Embrace
accountability and take business risks
under your own name
Society will reward you with
responsibility equity and leverage Nal
writes we are socially hardwired to not
fail in public under our own names the
people who have the ability to fail in
public under their own names actually
gain a lot of power so this is the first
aspect of accountability that he talks
about this ability to actually take
risks under your own personal name now
in most Industries the people who are
making the most money are most likely
the people whose names are out there and
whose names themselves are on the line
if we take the industry of medicine for
example like you could totally make a
reasonable living as a doctor where no
one really knows who your name is other
than your employer and like you know you
introduce yourself to your patients but
within medicine the doctors who tend to
make the most money tend to be the ones
who are taking risks under their own
personal name they are building a
personal brand for themselves they're
putting themselves out there maybe
they're getting really good at
orthopedic surgery and so they're known
as like the best orthopedic surgeon in
New York and so patients are actively
seeking out that individual rather than
saying hey I'm going to go to this
hospital cuz this hospital is really
good and I'll just be paired with
whatever surgeon happens to be working
on the day again that's that's totally
fine and for most doctors the goal of
becoming wealthy is not the primary goal
they're working towards but the doctors
who tend to be the wealthiest and that's
what we're talking about here Financial
Freedom how to build wealth they tend to
be the ones taking risks under their own
personal name building their own
personal brand taking accountability
without hiding behind a brand or an
institution why do companies sell
themselves to Berkshire hathway it's not
because they care intrinsically about
Berkshire hathway they care about Warren
Buffett because Warren Buffett has built
a strong personal brand professional
reputation credibility around his own
name and therefore people want to do
business with Warren Buffett because
he's built this credibility for being a
fair guy for like holding on to stuff
forever for like not really interfering
with the business that's one form of
accountability in that you are putting
your name to things but another form of
accountability that Nal talks about in
the book is being accountable for your
outputs rather than your inputs so what
does this mean well for the most part if
you are for example an employee you tend
to be accountable for your inputs in
that your job is to show up and put in
the hours fundamentally the employer is
buying your time and the employer is
hoping that as a result of that time
certain outputs will get produced and
those outputs will will drive certain
outcomes for the business or for the
customers or whatever but fundamentally
you're accountable for your inputs the
problem with being accountable for your
inputs is that your time and value and
work and how much you get paid is
generally quite annoyingly correlated
then you've got level two where you're
accountable for your outputs now in this
context you could imagine someone being
let's say a freelance writer now if
you're a freelance writer and you're
getting paid per article you produce
suddenly you're accountable for your
outputs rather than your inputs the
client does not really care how long it
takes you to write article as long as
you produce the article and therefore
you have decorrelated the amount of time
you're putting into the thing with the
amount of value you're creating and the
amount of money you can get paid for
doing the thing but then you've got
level three where you're accountable for
outcomes now again if we use the example
of a let's say a freelance writer being
accountable for inputs might be being
paid per hour for writing a sales page
being accountable for outputs might be
being able to charge I don't know $5,000
for a draft of a sales page but being
accountable for outcomes that would be
level three of accountability might be
saying to the client hey don't pay me to
actually do the work of creating the
sales page but anytime this sales page
makes more money than your previous one
did I want 20% of the upsite that is
where you are accountable for the
outcome now as you go up this
accountability Spectrum from input to
Output to outcome you as an individual
end up taking on more and more risk but
the rewards also get higher and higher
and as you go up this accountability
Spectrum as well you also end up
spending more time sweating at night if
things are not working out this is also
what nval means by taking accountability
in this capitalist world that we live in
the greatest rewards go to the people
who take the greatest RIS R now in a
world where you're being employed by a
business and being paid an hourly rate
you're unlikely to get very rich off of
that even if it's a very high hourly
rate because the business and by
extension the business owner are the
ones taking on the risk of being
accountable for outputs and for outcomes
You're simply being paid an hourly wage
to hopefully generate some outputs and
hopefully generate some outcomes but
you're not really going to capture the
value that you've created because you're
not taking on the risk he does write
that accountability is a double-edged
thing it allows you to take credit when
things go well and to Bear the brunt of
the failure when things go badly he
writes in the old days the captain was
expected to go down with the ship if the
ship was sinking then literally the last
person to get off was the captain
accountability does come with real risks
but we're talking about a business
context here the risk in a business
context would be that you'd probably be
the last one to get your Capital back
out you'd be the last one to get paid
for your time the time that you put in
the capital you put into the company
these are at risk but the point that he
makes is that in a modern society this
downside risk is actually quite small
even personal bankruptcy can wipe the
debts clean in good ecosystems he writes
I'm most familiar with Silicon Valley
but generally people will forgive
failures as long as you were honest and
made a high integrity effort so at this
point we have talked about specific
knowledge and we have talked about
accountability but even those things
aren't enough like for example you could
imagine a doctor who is employed by this
big hospital and that doctor or surgeon
is really really good they are taking
risks under their own personal name and
they have deep specific knowledge but
they are unlikely to get as rich as the
person who owns the hospital and that
brings us to point number three from
nal's book and point number three is
[Music]
equity nval writes if you don't own a
piece of a business you don't have a
path towards Financial Freedom why is
owning equity in a business important to
becoming rich well it's ownership versus
wage work if you are paid for renting at
your time even lawyers and doctors you
can make some money but you're not going
to make the money that gives you
Financial Freedom you're not going to
have passive income where a business is
earning for you while you are on
vacation without ownership your inputs
are very closely tied to your outputs in
almost any salary job even one paying a
lot per hour like lawyer or doctor
you're still putting in the hours and
every hour you get paid without
ownership when you're sleeping you're
not earning when you're retired you're
not earning when you're on vacation
you're not earning and you can't earn
nonlinearly if you look at even doctors
who get rich like really rich it's
because they open a business they open a
private practice the Private Practice
builds a brand and the brand attracts
people or they build some kind of
medical device a procedure or a process
with intellectual property essentially
you're working for somebody else and
that person is taking on the risk and
has the accountability the intellectual
property and the brand they're not going
to pay you enough they're going to pay
you the bare minimum they have to to get
you to do their job that can be a high
bare minimum but it's still not going to
be true wealth where you're retired but
still earning if you look at someone
like a Management Consultant or someone
like a lawyer or someone like a private
Equity partner the way they get really
rich is because they own equity in the
business it tends not to be from the
salary that they're getting paid and as
he talks about there's a couple of
different rots here so for example you
could work at a tech company that gives
you some amount of equity in the company
in return for you working there you know
there's a lot of people who join early
stage startups they're taking a big risk
because most startups don't work but if
the startup does work and then sells for
I don't know tens hundreds of millions
or billions or whatever the thing might
be then even as an early stage employee
you can get pretty rich in that process
secondly there is what MJ DeMarco calls
the slowlane path to wealth which is
basically where you have a job and you
spend less than you earn and then you
put the remainder of that into something
like the stock market and so you could
invest that in the S&P 500 you could
invest in the top 500 companies in the
US you could invest in just tech stocks
or whatever the problem with that
approach is that if you want to make
real wealth through that you have to be
putting in a ton of money like Millions
into the stock market to get enough
passive income for it to be you know
lead to meaningful wealth or meaningful
Financial Freedom but what MJ DeMark
calls the fast lane path to wealth is by
starting your own business because you
have 100% or like a massive chunk of
equity in your own business rather than
trying to buy
0.00001% of Apple every year based on
like the amount of money spare money you
saved up from from your salary for
example but even Equity ownership by
itself has limits like if you imagine
you starting a very small business like
the local restaurant or something you
are unlikely to get very rich off of
starting just simply the local
restaurant and that is where principal
number four comes in and that is
leverage now this whole leverage stuff
is something that Nal is very famous for
he writes that there are three broad
classes of Leverage one form of Leverage
is labor other humans working for you it
is the oldest form of Leverage and
actually not a great one in the modern
world I would argue this is the worst
form of Leverage that you could possibly
use managing other people is incredibly
messy it requires tremendous leadership
skills your one short hop from a mutiny
or getting eaten or torn apart by the
mob secondly money is good as a form of
Leverage it means every time you make a
decision you multiply it with money
capital is a trickier form of Leverage
to use it's more it's the one that
people have used to get fabulously
wealthy in the last century it's
probably been the dominant form of
Leverage in the last century but then
the final form of Leverage is brand new
the most democratic form it is products
with no marginal cost of replication
this includes books media movies and
code code is probably the most powerful
form of permissionless Leverage all you
need is a computer you don't need
anyone's permission and this whole idea
of Leverage is being able to multiply
your own efforts this book for example
is a form of Leverage long ago I would
have had to sit in a lecture hall and
lecture each of you personally I would
have maybe reached a few hundred people
and that would have been that so books
for example are a form of media leverage
where you do the work once and then you
could sell the thing potentially
infinite times code software for example
is a form of Leverage where you do the
work once to create the product and
maybe a little bit of work in
maintaining it and then in theory you
could sell it an infinite number of
times probably the most interesting
thing to keep in mind about new forms of
Leverage is that they are permissionless
they don't require somebody else's
permission for you to use them or
succeed for labor leverage someone has
to decide to follow you or be employed
by you for Capital leverage someone has
to give you money to invest or to turn
into a product coding writing books
recording podcasts tweeting youtubing
these kinds of things are permissionless
you don't need anyone's permission to do
them and that's why they are very
egalitarian they're great equalizers of
Leverage every great software developer
for example now has an army of robots
working for him at night time while he
or she sleeps after they've written the
code and it's cranking away so if you
combine these things if youve got
specific knowledge I.E this combination
of unique skills that are somewhat
unique to you that you have personal
interest in you combine that with
accountability like taking risks under
your own personal name putting your
personal name to something and being
accountable for outputs or outcomes you
combine that with starting a business
around the thing and having equity in
that particular business then you choose
a vehicle so rather than opening the
local restaurant that has very little
leverage around it unless you like hire
people to work in your restaurant which
is kind of annoying you find a way to
use Media or content and a code in
particular to like do the stuff that you
know as your vehicle for the business
all of that sets you up very nicely to
become wealthy to become financially
free and then we have key principle
number five which is time and there is a
subsection in the book in titled be
patient one thing I figured out later in
life is generally at least in the tech
business in Silicon Valley great people
have great outcomes you just have to be
patient every person I met at the
beginning of my career 20 years ago
where I looked at them and said wow that
guy or Gala super capable so smart and
dedicated all of them almost without
exception became extremely successful
you just had to give them a long enough
time scale it never happens in the time
scale you want or they want but it does
happen it takes time even once you have
all of these pieces in place there is an
indeterminant amount of time you have to
put in if you're counting you'll run run
out of patience before success actually
arrives oh that's good if you're
counting you'll run out of patience
before success actually arrives again
this speaks to this idea around
following your curiosity if you're doing
something that genuinely feels like play
to you you won't be counting the minutes
down and like the hours down and the
days and the years waiting waiting to
become successful waiting to become rich
you'd be doing the thing anyway and
weirdly it's the people who are not
seeking the money who tend to get the
money everybody wants to be rich
immediately but the world is an
efficient Place immediate doesn't work
you do have to put in the time you do
have to put in the hours and so I think
you have to put yourself in the position
with the specific knowledge with the
accountability with leverage with the
authentic skill set you have to be the
best in the world at what you do oh this
is good stuff this is good stuff you
have to enjoy it and keep doing it keep
doing it and keep doing it don't keep
track and don't keep count because if
you do you will run out of time man
that's good stuff now you know I was in
two minds about whe whether or not to
make this video because I like to make
videos that are a bit more actionable
that give you more of like a step by you
know follow the step-by-step process
here's how you build a YouTube channel
from the ground etc etc but this book
doesn't really give you a step-by-step
process instead it gives you more like
the philosophical like like the way of
thinking about it and what I was really
worried about before making this video
is that oh is there any is there really
any value in this video will people just
think that like oh they're not going to
read the book because it's not it's not
step by step or it's just it's it's too
high level and I thought you know what I
have benefited enormously from this book
by thinking in these different ways by
thinking like okay specific knowledge
what are the what are the different
factors that I'm personally interested
in where where I can to find the
intersection of those accountability
okay cool I need to take risks under my
own under my own personal name and
really I need to decorrelate my own time
from the value that I'm trying to add to
the world I need to be owning pieces of
businesses preferably my own business I
need to have leverage and so Media or
content which is the thing that I do and
code which is the thing that we're now
doing with software like voice pal and
progress pal and superfocus me and my
team are building various different apps
that is a form of code-based Leverage
and then the time thing it's like oh I
just need to do this over a long enough
time Horizon like following this advice
and thinking in these terms for myself
has had an enormous impact on my own
life and I think this is a really good
framework like if you're genuinely
interested in becoming financially free
and becoming wealthy you really can't
expect to get there by watching a
YouTube video that gives you a
step-by-step road map because like I
said if there was a step-by-step road
map other people would already be
following it and it would be priced into
the system and it wouldn't work anymore
but what I really love about this book
is that you we we've barely scratched
the surface there's a load of
interesting stuff in here about
happiness and about health and about
like what's even the point of money
anyway but like we've literally just
focused on the first I don't know 50 50
60 70 pages that specifically talk about
how to get wealthy I really would
recommend the book there's a lot of
really good wisdom in here but I'm
hoping that if you've gotten to this
point in the video you can see that this
was a little bit of a high Lev thing but
I'm hoping you found it useful anyway
and like I said you should definitely
check out the book if you are looking
for more specific advice on how to
become financially free this video over
here is a conversation I had with a
friend recently who is a corporate
lawyer who wanted to become financially
free uh by making passive income and
this is a recounting of the conversation
that we had that goes into a little bit
more practicalities around how to
actually do this stuff so thank you so
much for watching and I will see you
hopefully in the next video