this is a visualization of each country
in the world's most desired careers do
you see a theme and if you look at the
Google search data how to be a writer is
the second most popular career search in
the world after only how to be a pilot
but we're always told that writers can't
make money this article shows they only
make a couple of hundred a year but if
you think that that's all there is to
being a writer then this book might just
change your mind it's called the art and
business of online writing and it's by
multi-millionaire online writer Nicholas
Cole now Cole is one of the most read
writers on the entirety of the internet
he's wrapped up hundreds of millions of
views he's been the number one writer on
quora he's been paid tens of thousands
of dollars as a speech writer and ghost
writer and now he's built his online
writing business Shi 30 for 30 to
millions of dollars in Revenue anyone
can become a writer all of these skills
are easy to learn so in this episode of
book club the ongoing series will we
distill and discuss highlights and
summaries from some of my favorite books
we're going to use Nicholas Cole's
journey and model to talk about three
things firstly we're going to talk about
what online writing is and what online
writing isn't secondly we're going to
talk about the tools that you need to do
to do it effectively and thirdly we're
going to talk about how you can start to
make money from online writing and thank
you to Shopify for sponsoring this video
but more on them later so firstly what
is digital online writing and why have
most people never heard of it well the
easiest way to explain it is to explain
what online writing is not I don't know
what to write online writing isn't
grinding for years on your new book idea
and waiting for traditional Publishers
to come along and give you the approval
to be a professional writer online
writing is not slaving away for years on
your blog or website in the hope that a
few people might stumble across it on
Google why is life so hard online
writing is about publishing where the
readers already are I.E social media
platforms and that's why most people
haven't heard of it because we've all
grown up on the idea of Legacy writing
for example you probably know the story
of how JK Rowling got rejected by 12
different Publishers before one finally
took on Harry Potter now the Legacy
writing business relies on these
Gatekeepers these Publishers and these
editors that tell people when they are
allowed to be a professional writer
because back in the day you couldn't
make money unless you had a traditional
publishing deal I think Legacy writing
has this elitism to it where it's like
not everyone can do it and you have to
suffer and you have to stack rejection
letters and you know you're you only are
rewarded if you're brilliant and like
it's there's all this red tape and the
world of digital writing now is anyone
can become a writer all of these skills
are easy to learn now obviously Legacy
writing does have its place and in fact
my book Feelgood productivity is being
published by penguin in the UK and
worldwide and McMillan in the US which
are very traditional Publishers but for
most people if you're actually trying to
make money as a writer the answer is not
to try and land a traditional Legacy
publishing deal the answer is online
writing so unlike traditional forms of
writing you have the ability to generate
a hell of a lot more money by using the
leverage of the internet which I'll
break down in a minute and not only can
you get paid better than most other
writers out there but you can also build
a personal brand and an audience while
you're doing it along the journey which
also opens up your freedom to monetize
in different ways further down the line
if you really want to for example pachy
mccormik began online writing with his
newsletter not boring in 2019 and just 2
years later his thousands of subscribers
were helping him pull in a million
dollars of Revenue a year as a
ridiculously successful writer just
working from his home office and there's
a reason that only online writing is
able to do this so quickly and that's in
a word word feedback feedback is the key
to starting and sustaining and
monetizing your online writing Journey
so with Legacy writing you have
absolutely no idea how your work is
going to resonate with the audience
until the final product is released
which is pretty mental so Legacy world
of writing Hemingway sits down he spends
four years writing a novel sells it to a
publisher he has to wait another 18
months for it to get published then he
has to wait another 12 months for the
magazine reviews to come out and then he
has to go to a pub down the street and
then he overhears some person being like
anyways novel was terrible right that's
the feedback loop whereas with online
writing you can work smarter and faster
and you can constantly iterate on what
you put out there into these social
Gardens platforms like Twitter and
Linkedin and quora and places like that
by sharing smaller bite-sized pieces of
work that are judged by the masses you
can see what's working on the journey
and you don't run the risk of spending
years on your big projects only for them
to be released with no response you can
find out instantly if an idea is going
to hit or not the feedback loop is I
have an idea I write a tweet a thread an
AIC essay a LinkedIn post I publish it
and I get feedback 3 minutes later now
this very short feedback loop is
ultimately what helps build the online
personal brand and the online audience
as people watch you practice in public
are you're putting your writing out
there onto these social platforms the
ones that really Vibe with your stuff
will then join you on the journey and
then when you're ready to write the book
or do your magnum opus or ship that
fully-fledged work then what's amazing
is that you've already got this built-in
audience of people that already Vibe
with your stuff the little bits and Bobs
you've been releasing over time and
therefore those people are way more
likely to actually pay for your work and
then also read it whereas in the Legacy
publishing world if you're a first-time
author generally most people have no
idea who you are so how do you actually
go about online writing and then how do
you do it well well we can kind of break
this down into three parts and these are
represented by this little funnel so
imagine you're setting off on your
journey to become a successful online
writer and make your own pot of gold now
Cole explains that the first step is to
generate lots of ideas and publish
consistently personally I like to think
of this as the forest of ideas at this
point in the process we have absolutely
no idea what sort of content is going to
resonate with an audience we also have
no idea what sort of stuff we would
actually enjoy writing and so the point
of the forest of ideas is to generate
lots and lots of ideas and to write lots
and lots of things and put them out
there and see what happens now in terms
of where you're going to post this
writing there are a bunch of different
options but be careful you're not making
the big mistake that Cole says that
writers often make when starting out so
some examples of good places to write
are for example Twitter which is now
weirdly known as X where another Deep
dive guest CLE Bloom blew up his writing
career we've got LinkedIn for more busy
content we've got whatpad for fiction
this is where Anna Todd famously started
we've got quora we've got Reddit we've
got medium essentially any platform
where there is already an audience the
key thing is to make sure that you are
not starting your online writing Journey
on a blog or a website now there is
obviously a place for the kind of
writing that you would put on a blog or
a website but in the book Cole talks
about how this is often more suited to
businesses and Brands rather than to
individuals trying to build a personal
brand so if you want to be known as a
solar writer who's known for their
original creative insights or stories or
thoughts to ultimately build your own
personal brand then the key is to write
stuff on the social platforms where
there is already a built-in viewership
or readership so that was step one
creating the forest of ideas and then
step two is that wherever you decide to
post these step two is to get feedback
from the audience and I like like to
call this step the feedback cave now why
is there a troll that you have to get
past in this phase well Cole talks about
how facing feedback with online writing
is really hard and creates anxiety as
you might get comments from social media
trolls and also just normal people in
social media who might not Vibe with
your stuff and unlike with Legacy
writing methods you can't really just
camp out in your forest in the woods and
not have to face any feedback for your
writing until after your product is
released you're doomed now in the online
writing world this feedback is going to
be immediate and obviously this can be
daunting because now you have nowhere to
hide but it's also a very good thing
because this feedback loop this rapid
feedback loop is ultimately what makes
online writing way more effective than
Legacy writing in fact as Cole says in
the book there are two types of writers
today those who use data to inform and
improve their writing and those who fail
so now that you've posted your writing
and you started to get data in terms of
quantitative and qualitative performance
and comment metrics it's time to then
analyze the data and this is where we
get to the pool of analysis now this is
what people like Hemingway and people
like JK Rowling never had which is
genuine feedback on which ideas are
valuable and which ones are not and now
this point based on the fact that you've
been generating all these ideas and
writing about them consistently over
time in the forest of ideas you've gone
through the feedback cave to actually
look at the comments and the data that
you're getting and now you're analyzing
it it's now your job to try and spot
patterns within the data and this is
exactly what ridiculously rich and
bestselling author Mark Manson did when
it came to writing his first book Mark
Manson didn't sit down and go I'm going
to write this insanely amazing
best-selling book you know Sellar of not
giving right but what happened is the
publisher goes to him and goes well you
have a big blog you have a big audience
you should write a book he goes great
what should it be about they go we don't
know what's your biggest most viral blog
post he goes well it's a blog post
called the subtle art of not giving a
right and what did he do he just
expanded the blog post into a book this
example applies to Ryan holiday as well
so Ryan holiday initially began his
career as a marketing writer but after a
blog post he wrote about stoicism went
totally viral he decided to double down
on the topic which ultimately ended up
creating his Empire of books about
stoicism newsletters and even physical
products and now Ryan holiday makes
absolutely Millions every year selling
his writing he's one of the most
financially successful writers that
you're likely to come across now at some
point in your writing career you might
actually have a product that you want to
sell or start a business around your
writing and a great resource to use is
Shopify who are very kindly sponsoring
this video Shopify Powers businesses by
giving you all the tools that you need
to create your business wherever you are
in the world letting your sell online or
in person or across any social platform
it's a fantastic way of starting your
first business or your side hustle
without needing to learn how to code or
to make a website Shopify Powers more
entrepreneurs and businesses than anyone
else with millions of businesses using
Shopify in over 175 countries their
mission is to reduce the barriers to
business ownership to make Commerce
better for everyone which is a pretty
good goal if you ask me and we've
actually been using Shopify to sell our
own stationary brand and also our own
online courses and even if you're a
fairly small business like ours is or
you're an absolutely massive
multi-billion dollar Corporation Shopify
has you covered shopify's also got tools
for new business owners like the
business name generator and Shopify
learn which is their online learning
platform for all things related to
business and they also give new
entrepreneurs the really easy to use Stu
data plan where you can create an online
store in literally minutes if any of
this sounds up your street and you're
interested in trying out Shopify for
your business then head over to
shopify.com for/ Al abdal and that link
which is also in the video description
will let you sign up to a completely
free trial of Shopify so you can try it
out and see if it Vibes with you so
thank you so much Shopify for powering
our business and for sponsoring this
video now at this point you might be
wondering okay cool but how will all of
this ultimately make money and broadly
there are three specific ways of going
about making money from your online
writing so the first and least lucrative
of these is the advertising model also
known as the attention model now as we
all know on the internet attention is
the ultimate currency and it's exactly
the same for online writers as it is for
people like Mr Beast if you can generate
online writing that grabs attention you
can make money by earning from clicks
selling ad space within your own content
becoming an affiliate where you get a
commission each time you recommend a
product or Landing brand sponsorships
now the upside of the advertising model
is that it's very simple to understand
and apply so for example if you're
writing on medium the more people that
click and read your articles the more
money you're going to get paid as you
can see from this screenshot from James
Julian his article do these four
exercises and you'll you'll be in the
best shape of your life got 38,000 views
which has generated him
$1,741 from medium similarly jacked Rob
low revealed the one harsh truth about
staying fit at 60 got 25,000 views and
earned him
$1,114 that's not bad at all but to make
the advertising model work and to quote
Cole you need a ton of attention so
when Cole was writing articles for Inc
magazine for example those articles
might be getting hundreds of thousands
of views every single month but he would
only be making like $11,000 from it on
top of that people generally don't like
lots of ads being thrown at them and the
revenue can be volatile too sure you can
earn pretty well one month on medium but
the next month may be much less for a
bunch of reasons that are outside of
your control and that's why potentially
a better way to make money through
writing is the pay wall or the
exclusivity model now this is the
opposite of the ad model in the ad model
you put your content out there for free
and you monetize through advertising on
the platforms whereas in the pay wall
model instead of giving open access to
your content you charge for some of it
and this can come in many forms for
example you can write behind a pay wall
like newspapers like the New York Times
do or you can put writing behind a
premium newsletter mini pay wall for
example the popular business substack
account no opinion pulls in about a
million dollar per year via subscribers
who want to pay for access to his two
pay World posts per week and a good idea
to keep in mind here is Kevin Kelly's
famous 1,000 true fans Mantra now if you
haven't come across this before
basically the idea is that if you want
to earn a living you don't need millions
of people to follow your stuff you just
need 1,000 true fans 1,000 people out
there in the world who'd be willing to
pay let's say $100 per year to get
access to your stuff your writing your
merch your band albums all this stuff
and it's way more doable getting a
thousand true fans than it is to try and
go for an audence of millions of people
alternatively another example of a
payall method would be creating a course
like I did with my parttime YouTuber
Academy or you can create a product like
online writer Daniel Vaso did with his
Amazon FBA ebook So Daniel had been
writing online for a while and building
an audience such that when he released
his ebook he was able to make $40,000 in
just 16 days and this is the crazy power
of online writing and product creation
the beauty of productizing your service
is that you like we were talking about
earlier you're removing the constraint
of uh being paid for time that's the
whole that's like the biggest challenge
is as long as you're being paid for your
time and not the
outcome it's really hard to have some
sort of exponential jump in income now
generally with the pay model the content
that you would charge people for might
be the same sort of topics as the stuff
that you're writing online for free but
you're may be going into them in way
more depth in detail and then finally
we've got the services model also known
as the I'll do it for you model now in
this method you're not directly making
money by writing for an audience but
you're offering writing as a service to
businesses or to individuals who are
willing to pay for that service and this
is things like content writers and ghost
writers and speech writers these are
people who are making a living using
their writing but offering it as a
service now these can be ridiculously
well-paying like some ghost writers for
example who write autobiographies for
celebrities and CEOs and Executives and
stuff can be charging up to a million
dollars for a single book potential
ghost writing quote unquote clients are
everywhere they exist everywhere anyone
with a big YouTube channel probably
needs a ghost writer anyone with a big
podcast probably needs a ghost writer
anyone with a company probably needs a
ghost writer but there's also way
smaller ways of doing this if you think
of ghost writing or content writing for
businesses now Nicholas Cole actually
has a new book about this called the art
and business of ghost writing I've not
read it yet it's on my Tob read list but
I'll put a link down below if you want
to check it out if you're interested in
potentially making money from Ghost
writing his writing is fantastic so I'm
sure the book is going to be amazing
even though I've not yet read it and the
cool thing about ghost writing is that
it also helps you build your own network
while you're doing the thing but when it
comes to offering writing as a service
the real money is often made in a field
called copywriting and copywriting is
writing that is designed to sell
something kind of product and the reason
why copywriting can often be more
lucrative than any other form of writing
is because you can potentially earn a
percentage of the upsite for example
there are famous copywriters like Gary
Halbert who apparently can make millions
of dollars from just a single piece of
copywriting how you break into upper six
figures seven figure plus territory is
you have to not be compensated for the
effort but for the outcome that you
drive the way that a lot of uh really
successful sales copywriters structure
their deals is they go okay let's take a
product or let's take an ex existing
funnel here's the average amount of
Revenue that you're doing right now if I
can write things that lift the revenue
25% 50% I get a piece of that so now
you're being compensated on the outcome
you drive not on the I spent 20 hours
rewriting the landing page right so
that's a bit of an introduction to the
world of online writing you should
definitely check out the book it's
really good I've read it I think three
times and each time I've taken lots of
tips away that I can apply to my own
business and my own YouTube channel even
outside outside of the world of writing
and if you enjoyed this video you're
going to absolutely love the long form
podcast episode that I did where I
interviewed Nicholas Cole where we
talked about the five specific methods
that you can earn up to a million
dollars as an online writer that'll be
linked right over there and it's also
available on Spotify Apple app podcast
iTunes everywhere you get podcasts but
you should watch it over there because
that's a YouTube video version so you
can see what's going on in real life as
well thank you so much for watching and
I'll see you hopefully in the next video
bye-bye