all right so how do you start your first
business in a weekend that is what Noah
Haan purports to teach us in this book
million dooll weekend which is what
we're discussing in this episode of book
club the ongoing Series where I distill
and discuss highlights and summaries
from some of my favorite books and
genuinely this is a absolutely fantastic
book to read if you are an aspiring
entrepreneur if you've ever thought that
you want to start your own business and
you have not yet done it you need to
read this book because it's going to
give you a play-by-play road map on how
exactly to do that okay so the book has
broken down into three parts we've got
part one start it part two build it and
part part three grow it and in this
video I'm going to focus on part one and
two start it and build it let's go if
you're watching this and you haven't yet
started your business I suspect for a
lot of people I know you might have been
thinking about starting a business for
several years you have just not yet
taken action and there is this pervasive
myth that happens amongst everyone who's
an aspiring entrepreneur which is I need
the right idea I cannot get started
until I have the right idea but the
thing is and what Noah talks about
throughout the book is you don't start a
business by first having the right idea
and then starting the business you start
a business by deciding to start a
business and then you find a process to
come up with the right idea and really
the core message he's sharing this first
chapter which is why it's called a
chapter one just [ __ ] start is begin
before you are ready no one feels ready
to start a business just like I've heard
no one really feels ready to have kids
the timing is never quite right
similarly the timing to start a business
is never quite right you have to just
start you have to begin before you're
ready and just to label this point just
a little bit more there's a nice quote
here most people overthink First Act
later every successful entrepreneur ACT
first figure it out later any analysis
ahead of action is purely speculation
you really do not understand something
until you've done it rather than trying
to plan your way into the confidence to
act just start acting and there is a
motto that he talks about here and this
is a motto that that that has really
stuck with me since I read the book a
couple weeks ago and that motto is now
not how whenever we think of doing
something we're like okay well I've got
this idea for this thing but like how do
I do it and you know there's this
tyranny of how the how holds us back
from doing things instead think what is
the smallest action I can take right now
even if you don't know what to do about
anything there probably a small action
that you can figure out that you can
just take action on and then once you've
taken action on that you can then get
started with the thing so honestly the
whole first chapter is a lot of
emotional support genuinely like I've
been running my YouTuber Academy for a
few years now we've taught like 5,000
students in it 95% of students when it
comes to starting YouTube channels it's
not technical things they're struggling
with it's the emotional side of things
they're like I couldn't possibly make
YouTube videos unless I have the perfect
idea no one starts making YouTube videos
with the perfect idea just like no one
starts a business with the perfect idea
you decide to start and then you can
figure out the idea second now whatever
stage of the business process you're at
you're hopefully making some amount of
money and then you're going to need a
place to invest that money and that is
where the sponsor of this video comes in
and that is trading 212 trading 212 is a
fantastic app that lets you invest in
stocks and shares and funds in a
commission-free fashion they've got a
bunch of really good features which is
why I personally use them to manage a
portion of my portfolio so first they've
got a great practice mode if you're new
to Investing For example you can go on
the app and you can make an account for
free and you can invest with fake money
which actually sort of will track how
the Market's actually performing and so
you can see would you have made money or
would you have lost money over a certain
period of time had you invested actual
real cash and then once you're ready you
can always switch it from like the fake
play video game mode into the actual
money mode which is obviously what I do
cuz I invest my actual money through
trading 212 they also have a really good
highs and auto invest feature so
basically there's a bunch of like random
people who are super into like the stock
market analysis and they'll create these
pies where they might be like you know
this is a p of stocks like 30% Apple 20%
Tesla 10% like I don't know Microsoft
20% Google all that kind of stuff and
you can browse through these different
pies and you can see how they are
currently performing and how they've
historically performed and if you like
the idea of a pie and you kind of agree
with what's going on with it you can
actually just copy and paste that asset
allocation directly into your account
and you can invest however much money
you want in that particular pie
obviously for the record the thing that
I do not Financial advice but generally
what most people recommend is to just
invest in Broad stock market index funds
but if you're like me and you maybe want
to play around with some small
percentage of your portfolio then using
the pi feature is a great way of
dabbling with like individual stock
picking in that sense they've also
recently added support for multicurrency
accounts so if for example you're in the
UK and you want to invest in a US stock
market index fund like the S&P 500 like
I do then you won't get hit with your
annoying foreign exchange fees and if
you have an invest or an Isa account
then trading 212 also gives you daily
interest on your uninvested cash in USD
or GBP or Euros they've got more than
23,000 trust pilot reviews with an
average rating of over 4.6 Stars so they
are very reputable and like I said I've
been using them for years to manage a
portion of my own portfolio and so if
any of that signs up your straight then
do hit the link in the video description
and that will take you to this page
where you'll be guided on how to sign up
for an account and if you use that link
you will also get a free share up to the
value of £100 so it's free money you
might as well check out trading 212 and
thank you so much trading 212 for
sponsoring this video so now that we've
got the emotional support side out of
the way that begs the question what
happens next and that is where we now
come to the customer first approach to
building a business I have interviewed
hundreds of entrepreneurs on my podcast
spoken to hundreds more in real life and
all of them basically talk about this
idea this customer first approach which
is that you're not trying to find an
idea for a business instead first of all
you're starting with who are the people
you would like to serve because
fundamentally what a business is a
business solves a problem for someone
who is willing to pay for that problem
to be solved and the biggest thing that
holds back entrepreneurs and has done
forever is trying to build something
without first verifying that there's
actually someone out there will to pay
for the thing this is the problem that
students often have because students
come up with great ideas and it's
amazing they're like I have this idea
for this business and they'll just go
and try and build it without first
verifying that there are in fact people
to pay for it here we go that's why when
it comes to generating business ideas
customers come first before the product
or service even before the idea to build
a business you need someone to sell to I
can't tell you how many times someone
has emailed me saying what do you think
of this business idea I also get those
emails my auto reply have you asked what
the customer think basically when you're
trying to start a business the first
step is to figure out who are you going
to sell to and that's ideally within
your own zone of influence for example
in my position of being a medical
student at University the people I'm
serving are probably the people around
me or the parents of the people around
me or the people I interact within
hospitals or the people I interact with
at the University or the local
businesses I interact with that's like
within my zone of influence the other
good thing that this customer should
ideally have is money it is so much
easier to create a business where you
are targeting people who have money
rather than people who don't have money
again this is one of the issues with
students is that if you're a student
then everyone you know is your age and
probably does not have very much money
if it were me and I were student
starting a business I might be thinking
okay my friends don't have any money but
who does their parents do okay what are
the problems that my friends's parents
have who else has money like my college
or my University there's a pot of money
I can tap into there okay now that
you've brainstormed who are the sorts of
people ideally with money that you'd
potentially like to serve the next step
is to brainstorm what are all of the
problems that they have now the easiest
way to do this is to just go and ask
them what are the things in their life
that are really annoying what the things
that they already pay for one of the
things where they're paying for
something but the thing they're paying
for doesn't seem very good and if you do
this enough you will come up with an
infinite list of problems that people
have and the whole world progresses and
evolves based on people discovering a
problem and then trying to find the
solution to that problem Uber started
because someone complained was like oh
man it's really annoying trying to held
down a cab and trying to ring the taxi
company and so that's where the idea for
Uber comes along and there's a really
good example here so I love this there's
the founder first approach and then
there's the customer first approach so
here we go let's say you have an idea
for a dog walking app how would you go
about doing it here's the way most
people most entrepreneurs would do it
one spend hours at home thinking about
the app and coming up with Clem names
for it two spend $100 hiring their
cousin to draw a cool logo three set up
an LLC four watch YouTube videos about
apps and programming in business and
dogs five consider signing up for a
developer boot camp and quickly realize
that coding is hard six buy the domain
name for the snazzy website they're
going to build seven look into hiring a
developer on upwork and quickly realize
it's prohibitively expensive eight give
up again does that sound fam that is
founder first now let's take the same
idea for a dog walking app and let's put
it through the customer first
perspective one call or text three
people right now who have dogs and ask
them to pay you to walk their dog two
turns out none of these dog owners have
problems walking their dog you discover
their real problem is finding dog
sitters when they're traveling three ask
for their next travel dates and have
them pay you a deposit they pay jackpot
and the idea here is that quickly you
know based on this really simple example
which I think we can all relate to in
some ways in the founder first approach
you go down a rabbit hole where you
build this thing without verifying that
people actually have the problem and are
willing to pay for it in the second one
you come up with an idea cool and then
you talk to people and you see does the
idea have legs would they be willing to
pay you for it you realize no they don't
and now you do something else cuz you
realize they are willing to pay for this
other thing and crucially you ask for
that first sale you make that first
dollar the first dollar is always the
hardest the first three customers are
always the hardest if you just aim to
try and get your first three paying
customers as soon as is humanly possible
before you even try and build anything
then at least you have some kind of
validation that the idea has legs so
this for example is an email that one of
Noah's friends Boris sent subject
helping you help me with food hey
friends one thing I realized is that I'm
busy all the time and I don't have time
to cook a quality meal I wanted to
invite a few close friends to test a
business idea with me consider yourself
the lucky Chosen Few smiley face
convenient and home-cooked meals on
February 9th for $20 there will be a
personal chef making us food and
delivering it to you conveniently and
deliciously if this is something you're
seriously interested in please PayPal
$20 open to all and any feedback cheers
Boris PS please let me know if you have
any dietary requirements Etc I promise
the dinner will be delish exclamation
mark exclamation mark exclamation mark
this is how you validate the idea for a
business you know you might have a
business idea and you at a party you say
to someone oh I'm thinking of starting a
business around bloody blah would you be
interested social etica dictates they
basically have to say yes you're very
unlikely to meet someone who will
actually say no I won't I won't get
about that but here's the crucial bit if
you ask them for money be like okay cool
well you know I'm taking pre-orders now
would you be willing to pay me $20 for
it now you see how good your idea
actually is because no one is going to
part with their money unless they
actually believe in the idea words are
cheap money is not so if someone says
yeah I like your business idea that that
means jack all what matters is are they
actually paying for it have they
pre-ordered the thing would they be
willing to be your first customer for a
50% discount with a money back guarantee
anything like that now the other way to
get business ideas is to also look to
your own problems if you find something
is a problem for you chances are it'll
be a problem for other people as well
and there are four prompts that Noah
gives us that I fully agree with that
help us figure out what our own problems
are so firstly what is one thing this
morning that irritated me secondly what
is one thing on my to-do list that's
been there for over a week thirdly what
is one thing that I regularly fail to do
well and fourthly what is one thing I
wanted to buy recently only to find out
that no one made it and these sorts of
prts help you think about like the
problems in your own life you should
sort of become a magnet for problems
like as you go through life anytime you
find something annoying what an aspiring
entrepreneur or an actual entrepreneur
does is they recognize oh I'm finding
this thing annoying I have just
identified a problem and a problem with
a solution is a business assuming people
are willing to pay for that solution
whereas what most people do is like they
will just come across a problem and
they'll be like oh yeah it's just a
thing oh yeah it's really annoying that
we have to fill out these like feedback
forms in in our lectures and that's
where the idea will stop what I used to
do in med school was oh man it's really
annoying that we've got to fill out
those feedback forms and lectures I
wonder if there would be a more
efficient way of doing that if we found
the right person we could build a
solution to this and when I was in med
school I was unsophisticated with this I
was like oh how might I build this I
knew how to code I knew how to make
websites and apps and stuff so I default
to like just trying to build the thing
I've wasted years of my life chasing
business ideas where I was like I found
an idea I'm going to build the thing and
I didn't find any customers to pay for
the bloody thing and really if someone
had told me this when I was 13 I would
have literally saved seven years of my
life chasing down random rabbit holes
because I I was afraid or didn't realize
I could speak to people and actually
just ask them for money the main thing
is that honestly the way you start a
business these days is that you try and
get people to pay for the thing before
you make the thing people come to me and
they're like hey Ali I've got a bit of
an audience I want to make an online
course and I'm always like okay cool I
know that the Temptation is there to
build the course and then sell it in
that order but you should flip that
around you should sell the course and
then build it so if for example you're
thinking you know maybe your audience
wants a course on how to build the
perfect productive desk setup you could
go out and spend like a month or two or
three trying to create the course that
would be a terrible idea instead what
you should do is pre-sell it you can
whip up a landing page in like a Google
doc in maybe half a day you can send it
out to people in your audience and be
like hey potentially working on this
course about how to have a productive
desk setup if this sounds interesting
you can pre-order the course here it'll
be released in the next month and I'll
give you a money back if you don't like
it 50% off something to that effect
because based on how the pre-sale goes
if enough people want to buy it then it
gives you an idea it lets you validate
the market so it's about finding a
problem finding someone who's willing to
pay for the solution to that problem
talking to those people quite a lot
getting money from them and only once
you have done that do you know that okay
this is a business idea worth pursuing
and now you can start to build the thing
cuz you already have paying customers
this is the thing that I wish I had
known when I started my entrepreneurship
Journey this is the thing I wish is a
message that could be hammered into the
heads of every single aspiring
entrepreneur out there I give so many
talks these days around the world it's
super fun and there's always like half
the audience are aspiring entrepreneurs
and they're all stuck in this thing of
like ah I need to have a good business
idea or or oh I've just been building
this thing but like I haven't built it
yet and I need to make my MVP first and
then all of it is a total waste of time
if you speak to people who are second
time Founders people who have started
multiple companies you'll find this they
spend the majority of their time just
talking to customers the more you talk
to your customers the more you validate
the idea actually has a market the more
you understand what problems they have
the more you can start to see huh maybe
I thought this thing should be R but
actually this thing is blue the more you
try and ask them for money to pre-sell
the thing that you haven't even built
yet the more more likely you are to
succeed in the business honestly I think
you should totally read the book it's
absolutely amazing Noah has done a
smashing job of it and if you like this
video and you want to see a way deeper
dive into this I actually have an
interview with Noah keun on on the Deep
dive podcast that will be linked right
over here thank you so much for watching
and I'll see you in the next video
bye-bye