Hey friends, welcome back to the
channel. So, if you are looking to start
or grow a [music] YouTube channel
alongside working a full-time job, then
hopefully this video is going to help
you out. If you're new here, my name is
Ali and I started my YouTube channel way
back in 2017 when I was a medical
student at Cambridge University. And I
then spent 2 years working full-time as
a junior doctor in the UK's National
Health Service, including during the
pandemic. And while working full-time, I
grew this YouTube [music] channel over 3
years from zero to around 1.3 million
subscribers. And so, I definitely know
how hard it can be to balance working a
full-time job alongside starting a
YouTube channel, but it is definitely
possible. So, in this video, I'm going
to be sharing my best advice about how
you can successfully balance working
full-time with building a YouTube
channel. And we're going to talk about
things like how you can find the time
and energy to do both things, [music]
how much time you should spend on your
channel, and how to optimize the way
that you use your time and energy so
that you don't burn out and you [music]
can still keep making the videos. Now, I
recently asked my audience to send in
any questions you guys had about growing
your YouTube channels. And I'm going to
be using a question that Hanil sent in
to talk directly about this problem that
I'm sure a lot of you are facing. So
let's dive into Heneil's question. And
of course there will be timestamps down
below. So do feel free to skip around
the video if you feel like it.
Hey Ali. [music]
So I am a veterinarian working from 10
to 6 in a clinic and I also uh do some
private cases after I'm done with my 10
to 6 job. And basically the thing is
these both these things are like sort of
active jobs where they require my
presence and my energy and [music] I
really wanted to get into something that
will have more like a passive uh [music]
way of working and a passive way of
generating income. So I was thinking of
going into like getting into the YouTube
route uh or making content either that
would be for veterinarians like myself
or pet parents uh educating them about
the things that we as veterinarians want
them to know beforehand. So, I really
wanted to start this YouTube channel
since [music] the past 1 year and I feel
like I just don't get enough of time
during the day or even if I have the
time, I am kind of so drained out that I
just want to sleep and not do anything.
And um
so in order to combat this, I thought I
would start [music] at least doing live
streams of me studying so that I get the
hang of being on YouTube.
And I tried that out once or twice and
that kind of stopped there. But I think
it really worked out well because it
kind of kept me focused on the studying
part of it as well as I was kind of
putting out content on the channel. Um,
so what I have done so far is I have
made that setup and kept it. But I would
really like to know what would be your
opinion on me
getting this YouTube channel really up
and going even though I have all these
things lined up for the day already.
Thanks.
Okay, this is a [music] good question.
How do you do YouTube with a full-time
job? Now, I am going to take a little
bit of a different approach to answering
this because of Hanil's background. So,
he's a vet who works full-time from
10:00 a.m. to 6:00 p.m. [music] He does
private cases as well, but he would love
to have a passive form of income. We all
want to make money in our sleep without
doing any work. So, you know, this is
why I started this journey. I can
[music] understand why Hanil and
probably you watching this would like
some passive income. It sounds great,
doesn't it? Um, he's thinking maybe
YouTube or content, maybe content for
vets or people who are pet parents. That
is actually a very good thing to be
thinking about. He's leaning into his
unfair advantages, but he's been wanting
to start for a year, but I don't have
the time and I don't have the energy.
classic problem that we all face with
[music] anything that we're trying to
do. Either we don't have the time or we
do have the time, but we but we're so
drained by the thing that we do for our
day job that we just don't have the
energy to do it. [music] He's dabbled
with some live streams and stuff, but
really just wants to know how do I make
this YouTube channel successful with a
full-time job. So, [music] we need to
zoom out and we need to zoom out because
if Hanil were sitting in front of me
right now, the first thing I would say
to him, Hanil, is like, why do you
actually want to start a YouTube
channel? Do you want to start a YouTube
channel because you are intrinsically
motivated to start a YouTube channel
specifically? Or do you want to start a
YouTube channel because you think it is
your best route to passive income? And
the reason why really matters here
because if Hanil were to say to me that
look honestly the reason I want to start
a YouTube channel is like I don't really
care about YouTube itself. I don't
really care about making videos. I am
using the YouTube channel as an
instrumental strategy to get to my real
goal, which is some form of passive
income. In that sense, I would tell
Hanil, look, man, don't start a YouTube
channel. If your goal is passive income,
there are way more efficient ways to
make passive income than by starting a
YouTube channel. I would not recommend
YouTube channel if the goal from
starting a YouTube channel is to try and
make passive income. Why is that? Well,
it's just too much of a slo. You know,
if you really want to make passive
income, there just are just better paths
for it. One thing that I would that
would come to mind is generally if you
want to make want to make money, you
want to do some sort of B2B offer. You
want to sell to businesses rather than
to consumers. [music] You want to try
and sell some sort of product. In
Hanil's case, he's got expertise in the
veterinarian field. So like it's it's
just more efficient to find a client who
is a veterinary practice or going up the
supply chain of vet stuff, talking to a
pharmaceutical company that supplies
products to vets, trying to figure out
what is a service that I can offer them
which would solve a problem that they
have in their business. Because
businesses have large amounts of money,
whereas individuals do not have large
amounts of money. Usually, when someone
wants to start a YouTube channel,
they're they're trying to go the BTOC
approach. [music] Either they're hoping
to get loads and loads of views so that
they can get sponsorship and AdSense and
stuff and then make money. It's not
particularly passive because you still
have to keep on making the videos and
you're always going to run into the
problem of like kind of time and energy
and stuff. Or you're going to try and
sell some sort of product to consumers.
So maybe he would sell a course on how
to get into vet school, which would be
sold to consumers who want to get into
vet school. And then yeah, in that sense
it's passive because you make the course
once. Uh it might it might take 6 months
to make the course, but you make it once
and then in theory you sell it over
time. The problem is it's just a very
long game. There's no guarantee that
it's actually going to work. There's no
guarantee that Hanil has what it takes
to succeed on YouTube. Um it takes
having some sense of like having
expertise in the topic, but also a sense
of being able to explain things on
camera, a sense of other people
connecting with the sort of personality
that you have on the internet. I'm not
saying O'Neal doesn't. It's just that
these things are not guaranteed.
Whereas, if you were genuinely just
trying to make money and you were just
trying to sell a very useful service to
some sort of business, that is way more
guaranteed. The path to selling a
service to a business in the vet sphere
and making money from it that you can
then hire people out to become to make
roughly passive. That to me, I would say
has a 10 times more likelihood of
working than Hanal trying to start a
YouTube channel as an instrumental
technique to give to make passive
income. That's if Hanal were to tell me
that really the YouTube channel is just
a means to an end. If however, Hanil
were to tell me, you know what, the
YouTube channel is not a means to an
end. I really like the idea of starting
a YouTube channel. I'd say to him, okay,
you really like the idea of starting a
YouTube channel. Would you do it even if
you knew you'd never make money from it?
If Hanil's answer is still yes, I would
ask him why. Would you do it if you
didn't make money from it? Yes, I still
would. Why is that? Because I get a lot
of personal joy and satisfaction from
the thought that my content could be
useful to someone else. That to me is
gold standard. That's like great. We are
doing YouTube for the right reasons. The
people who end up making money on
YouTube usually are the ones who didn't
set out to make money on YouTube. It is
very hard to make money on YouTube if
you set out to make money on YouTube.
There are just way more efficient ways
to make money. But it becomes a lot more
doable if the reason you're doing it is
an intrinsically motivated reason for
starting a YouTube channel because
you're motivated by the purpose, the
service, the joy, the love of teaching
in Hanil's case. So if anyone is
watching this and thinking of starting a
YouTube channel as an instrumental
reason for making money, I would say
don't do it. It's not worth it. There
are more effective ways of making money.
What are those more effective ways of
making money? Well, I have a video over
there, my honest advice as someone who
wants to be financially free that has so
many recommendations of books and
articles and podcasts that you can check
out because that is the more efficient
way to make money. You should start a
business selling stuff to other
businesses. Please, for the love of God,
do not start a YouTube channel if your
only reason to start it is to make
money. There are more efficient ways of
doing it. Having said all of that, I'm
now going to assume that for the rest of
this video that Hanal actually does want
to start a YouTube channel for its own
sake because he's motivated by the
pleasure, the purpose, the joy of
service, all that kind of stuff, and is
simply running into the problem of time
and energy.
I'm going to assume that her goal is
something to the effect of I want to
make one YouTube video per week. This, I
think, is a good goal. Um, when we think
of goals, there's sort of a spectrum of
goals. There is [music] input goals,
there is output goals and there is
outcome goals. Generally these are
easier, input goals are easier and
outcome goals are harder. And also
broadly um these sort of input goals are
more in your control and outcome goals
are less in your control or under your
control or whatever the phrase is. Okay.
So what would an outcome goal be? An
outcome goal would be I want to get to
100K subs
by I don't know 20206 whatever the thing
might be. That is an outcome goal. That
is broadly that's very hard to do in
outside of Neil's control outside of
your control. What's an output goal? An
output goal is one video per week. I
would like to output i.e. publish one
video per week. And what is an input
goal? An input goal is I want to do I
don't know 8 hours per week
uh work on my YouTube channel or
whatever the thing might be. This is an
input. Anal is inputting 8 hours of time
here. This is an output. He's aiming to
output one video per week. This is an
outcome. He's aiming to get [music]
100,000 subscribers by 2026. I don't
like outcome goals. Outcome goals are
very hard. I think when you're very
experienced, you can go for outcome
goals. These days for my business, we
have outcome goals. I'm like, you know,
the goal is to grow the business to 10
million in revenue by the by the end of
next year. It's hard. It's outside of my
control, but I'm fairly experienced in
the world of business that it it's sort
of makes sense to have that as an
outcome goal. If I was a total noob and
I had outcome goals for my business,
things would be things would be a lot
harder and I'd be more likely to lose
motivation. What I would probably
recommend for Hanil is starting here,
starting with the output goal of one
video per week because that is an output
goal that is, you know, more or less
within our control [music]
and it's something that we can then
optimize for when we're figuring out
this main problem that Tal has, which is
I don't have any time and when I do have
the time, I don't have the energy. So,
knowing that the goal is one video per
week, we're now trying to figure out,
okay, how do we get more time? How do
how do we find the time and how do we
[music] create the energy to be able to
make one video per week? And knowing
that is actually quite useful because
one video per week is less of a vague
abstract thing than I want to grow on
YouTube or I want to do YouTube or
whatever the thing might be. So, we know
we want one video per week. Oh, by the
way, if you're enjoying this video so
far, you might likely check out my
completely free Arttime YouTuber crash
course. It is a 7-day email course where
every day I will email you some super
useful principles, strategies, tools,
templates, stuff that I found useful
over the last 7 years in growing my
YouTube channel. It's completely free.
You can unsubscribe anytime and there'll
be a link down below [music] if you want
to check it out. Now then what we have
to do and at least this is the way I
think about it is we just need to break
down what does it look like to make one
video per week. What is the process of
creating a video? Well, you start off
with the idea. Then if Hanil has seen
any of my content, he knows that you
should figure out the title and the
thumbnail of the video. Then Hanil will
probably want to write the video and
then probably film
and then probably edit
and then probably publish.
And so this needs to happen in order
[music] for anal to make one video per
week. So let's break this down. This is
genuinely the advice I give to someone
who's in the situation. And loads of
people are in this situation, right?
Well, if you're if you're watching the
video to this point, you're probably in
the situation where maybe you want to
make YouTube videos. You want to make
maybe one video per week, but like how
the hell do you find the time and the
energy to do it? especially with a
full-time [music] job. I was in this
position for 3 years. One year while I
was a medical student full-time at
Cambridge and then two years while I was
working full-time as a doctor and then
the pandemic happened and then I took a
break and stuff and then suddenly I
became a full-time YouTuber. Um or
rather a part-time YouTuber and a
full-time entrepreneur blah blah blah
blah blah. But like this is the stuff
that I'm very intimately familiar with.
Okay, so how do we do it? Well, first
thing we need to figure out how much
time do we actually have available per
week to be able to make this video.
[music] Anneil says he works 10il 6
during the weekdays and does private
cases after that. I'm going to bet that
Hanal can probably not film videos on
weekdays because he's working [music]
full-time. So now we only really have
weekends left. Hanneal might have a
life. [music] And so you might say that,
okay, I want to get all of this done
within 4 hours on a Saturday. So let's
say 4 hours is what we're trying to go
for. I think 4 hours may be a little bit
unrealistic, but we'll just go for that.
We'll just pretend that Anal has [music]
4 hours. The input is 4 hours per week
to give to the YouTube channel, and the
output we're going for is one video per
week. Now, it it actually is possible to
do that. Um, right now you could open up
the YouTube app and you could hit go
live and you could do a live stream and
you could just film a [music] video and
that would produce one video per week
because you don't need to edit it. It
just goes on your YouTube channel and it
shows up as a live stream. Easy enough.
The problem with that is that the less
time you put [music] into creating these
videos, the less high quality they're
going to be. So obviously a video that's
properly filmed and written and edited
with a proper title and proper thumbnail
is probably going to do better than a
random live stream that you just put
[music] online. You would then think
that okay well that's fine. So maybe
it's not the live stream. Maybe a live
stream would take half an hour but I
still got another 3 and a half hours. So
what do I do with that time? Or maybe
you just film a video just off the cuff
and then you spend 3 hours editing it.
That could be it. Maybe you spend 2
hours looking at the idea, 30 minutes
writing it, filming it and then not
doing any edit editing at all. Like
essentially we just have this allocation
of 4 hours [music] and we need to
allocate the time to these different
activities. So if I personally had to
start a YouTube channel and I was going
to make one video a week and I only had
4 hours to put into my YouTube channel,
this is what I would do. Firstly, I
would cut out editing because I would
outsource it. How do you outsource
editing? Well, you look at editors on
Upwork and Fiverr and People per Hour.
If you want to [music] find really good
editors, you go to heyfriend.studio,
which is a company that I'm running with
some friends. There's ways to find
editors. People are always like, "Oh,
but I can't outsource editing because
it's expensive." I have a whole course.
My part-time YouTuber Academy has like a
whole module on how to outsource your
editing. But in a nutshell, Hanil is a
veterinarian. Um, he probably makes more
money from his day job than it would
cost [music] to to hire a video editor
in his country. Um, I don't know where
Hanil is from, but I'm going to assume
[music]
it's somewhere like India where vets
definitely get paid more than video
editors. So, what Hanal can do is he can
outsource video editing and find someone
who's just making less money than he is.
He mentioned that [music] he does
private cases. That means he gets paid
private practice rates to do private
cases. So let's say Hanil makes $100 for
each private case that he does. And
let's say it costs him $30 or $40 to
find someone to edit a video. Hanal can
do some extra cases to buy back his time
and to use some of that money to buy
back time when it comes to outsourcing
video editing. The way the the way to
think about this is that 4 hours per
week is not that much time to put into a
YouTube channel. Everything takes two
[music] resources. Time plus money.
And you can argue energy and stuff, but
actually time and money are
interchangeable. [music] You can spend
time to save money or you can spend
money to save time. In this context, I'm
saying that if if it were me and I only
had 4 hours per week and I was making
money through my vet day job and my
private practice, I would be spending
money to save time. [music] I would be
outsourcing my editing. If I didn't want
to outsource my editing for whatever
reason, because I'm silly or [music]
because I'm broke or whatever the thing
might be, then we would have to factor
editing into this whole process. And I
would probably say editing would take
maybe 2 [music] hours. So, I'm going to
put 2 hours in brackets over here. And
yeah, you can always edit a video for
more than 2 hours. On average, it takes
our editors 5 days [music] to edit one
of these videos for my main channel. But
back in the day when I was editing my
own videos, it was taking me like 4 to 6
hours to edit a video. Sometimes I had
to get one out while, you know, because
I was aiming for one video a week and so
I'd [music] only spend two hours in the
editing. I was editing my own videos for
two whole years before I decided to
outsource the editing and that was just
dumb of me. I wish someone had told me
you need to figure out how to outsource
it. I'm going to assume Hanil is
following my advice and is actually
outsourcing his editing. Great. It still
probably takes half an hour per week to
like uh review the edit, go back and
forth with the editor, use Frame.io,
which is really good software for like
feed feeding back on the edits and
stuff. So, we're down to 3.5 hours. What
do we do with the rest of that time?
Well, I think filming the video, we
should aim for that to take 30 minutes.
If Hanal is doing content about things
that he's experienced in and knows what
he's talking about, you know, it
shouldn't take longer than 30 minutes to
film a video. And maybe maybe each video
is like 10 minutes long or like 6 to 10
minutes long. You can do that within a
30-minute filming session. So, that
leaves us with 3 hours left. What do we
do with that 3 hours? Honestly, I'd
probably spend two of those hours on the
idea, the title, and the thumbnail. And
I'd spend one of those hours on writing
the video. The two hours on the idea,
title, and the thumbnail. 1 hour on
writing the video. 30 minutes filming
the video. 30 minutes reviewing the
edits that my outsourced video editor
has done. And then publishing the video.
I'm not really going to count in the 4
hours cuz I can just sort of upload it
overnight if it depends depends on how
good my internet connection is. [music]
And once I've nailed the title and
thumbnail already, that's like the hard
part. Publishing it is like a 5minute
job. It's not it's not too hard. So, I'm
going to assume this takes 5 minutes.
[music] And now this just becomes a
maths a maths puzzle. Like, how do you
make the best quality videos given the
constraints of time and given the
constraints of money? So, how do we do
idea, title, and thumbnail in 2 hours?
[music] Actually, 2 hours is a very
reasonable amount of time to do idea,
title, and thumbnail. He comes up with
some ideas. Again, [music] this is like
a whole thing. Figure out target
audience, value proposition, competitor
analysis, unfair advantages, the whole
shebang. But if Anneil is just getting
started out, I would say don't overthink
it. Watch all of the videos I've ever
made about how to grow on YouTube. maybe
sign up to my course if you really want
to, but it's kind of expensive. Maybe
you can't afford it. That's fine.
Whatever the thing might be. In fact,
Haniel, if you're watching this, reach
out to us. We'll we'll give you free
access to the course. Um, whatever it
might be, it's not that hard coming up
with ideas. And then you spend maybe, I
don't know, [music] an hour on Canva
doing title and thumbnail for that
particular video. We want to streamline
this process to make it as efficient as
possible. When it comes to writing
videos, what I would recommend for
Heneal is don't script your videos. If
you script your videos word for word, it
will take way longer than 1 hour to
write a video. Um, a 10-minute video is
maybe like how many words? 1,500 words,
something like that. It usually takes
longer than 1 hour to write 1,500 words
or 1,000 words. Generally, what I would
recommend is just going with bullet
points. [music] What I do for my videos,
especially if it's a topic that I
actually have expertise in. So, if I was
talking about medical stuff or whatever,
um, if I was, I'd be talking about vet
stuff, I would just decide what are the
three to five things I want to say in
the video, and I just want to limit it
to three to five things. [music]
Potentially, even just three things.
Let's say I were doing a video called
How to Get into Vet School in the UK,
right? And I'd be thinking, what are the
three main points I want [music] to make
in this video? Well, it's going to have
an intro and it's going to have an
outro. Sure. Uh, point number one, point
number two, point number three. Um, this
is the triplet method of making videos,
which I talk about in my course as well.
Uh, point number one, um, how it works,
point number two, um, tips for getting
in, and point number three, um, mistakes
[music] people make. And then within
each of these points, I would limit
myself to just three points. So this is
the triplet method, the 3x3 method. 3x3.
[music]
I have three main points. One, two,
three. And I have three sub points
within my three main points. And this
would take me maybe 10, 15, 20 minutes
to put together. That is the time that
Hanil would use in writing the video.
And then coming back to our little
diagram over here. This is actually
pretty good. I've given Hanil a whole
hour to write the video. and it
shouldn't take more than 20 minutes if
he's following my method and talking
about stuff that he actually has genuine
expertise [music] in. Now, we've got way
more time to film the video. So, Hilal
can hit record on the camera, he can
film on his phone, he can film on a
camera, whatever the thing is. I'm
assuming it's easy enough to set up. He
mentioned he's got this live streaming
studying setup, so it already has the
camera. He hits record and he just
shares from the heart and tries to add
as much value to his audience as he
possibly can, sharing everything he
knows within the confines of this
triplet method of creating this video.
The [music] three main points and the
three sub points. Now, the video is
filmed. It then gets uploaded to Google
Drive or Dropbox or whatever. You hand
an SD card to an editor if you know them
in real life. The editing is outsourced.
A few days later, Anneil is going to get
a review from the editor and it might
take half an hour back and forth and
then you publish the video. This is
[music] the simple process to making a
video every week with 4 hours of time.
The way we then [music] make this
process more efficient, for example, is
by recognizing what can we batch. So,
this was a thing that I really realized
when I was working full-time as a
doctor. I realized that the only thing
that actually needed large amounts of
time was the filming. I didn't have a
setup in my house. So, I had to like set
up the camera, set up the light, set the
tripod, set up the microphone, film the
thing, and then take them all back down
again. So, it would take me like an hour
to set up for filming. So, what I
realized, well, if it takes an hour to
set up for filming, every time I set up
for filming, I should film more than one
video. I should ideally film two or
three or four videos in the same day
because if I can do that then I can be
very efficient and then I can do my
entire like upload calendar in one
[music] filming session. So if Hil was
being really pro, this is what I would
advise. I would say Hanil, you should
probably have instead of thinking about
about this as like 4 hours per week
where it's like it has to be consistent.
Instead, let's say this is I don't know
a monthly calendar
or something. You guys get the idea.
This is a Saturday. This is a Sunday.
Now, I'm going to assume because Neil
works full-time, [music] you can't
really do very much Monday to Friday.
I'm assuming you can't really do very
much. What I would do if I were Neil is
I would say, okay, the first Saturday of
every month is going to be my film day.
And the goal is to film four videos in
that day. The goal is to film four
videos on that Saturday. That means in
preparation for that first Saturday
where I'm going to take the whole day or
the whole like morning or whole
afternoon, whatever, to film four
videos, I need to make sure I've
prepared those four videos.
[music]
So, how do we find the time to to
prepare those four videos? Well,
conveniently, when it comes to idea
generation, titles, thumbnails, and
writing, [music] these are actually all
of these are things that can be done in
small amounts of time here and there.
When I was working as a doctor
full-time, for example, you know, a
full-time job is not really a full-time
job. There are very few days where it's
genuinely backtoback and you don't even
have a single minute to yourself. You've
got break times. You've got lunch
breaks. You've got those times when
you're seeing a patient and then they
have to be taken to radiology and it
takes 5 minutes to get there and back
and there's no other patient to see. So,
you've got 10 minutes of time. You've
got times when you're on the toilet.
You've got times when if you're
commuting to work, it looks like Hanil
is driving. But if you're commuting to
work, for example, on public transport,
you can use your phone. You can get an
iPad or a laptop or a notepad. Like,
there's all these little moments of time
here and there. And you can use those
moments of time to think, "Okay, cool.
My goal is on Saturday the 1st of
August, I'm going to film [music] four
videos. So, I need four ideas. I need
four titles and thumbnails. I need to
have four outlines created so that when
it gets to Saturday the 1st of August, I
now have enough content that I can just
bang out four videos on that one filming
session. And that means then Hanil can
give all four videos to his one or two
or three outsourced editors and they can
slowly work on it over time. Then Hanil
is not spending that much time reviewing
those back and forth because there's
lead times and it takes a while to get
back from the editors and stuff. And
this is really how you become a
part-time YouTuber. This was the exact
method that I used to grow my channel
from zero to like 1.5 million
subscribers while working entirely
full-time as a doctor. And even now, I
only spend one day a week on my YouTube
channel. This day, this day is a filming
day. And on filming days, I aim to film
at [music] least one video. Sometimes
two, sometimes three. This is actually
the third video I'm filming today. We
had a filming video last week where I
filmed four videos in one day. Some days
it's just been one, some days it's been
zero, depending on how I feel. But I
only spend 8 hours a week on my YouTube
channel. I've gotten to the point of
course now where I have a team to deal
with all this sort of stuff. But
fundamentally what I do now is no
different from this process which is
what I was doing 5 years ago when I was
still working full-time and in the same
position as Hanil where I'd be working 9
till 6 every single day. Sometimes I'd
have shifts in the evening. Sometimes I
would have night shifts. I [music] would
have not very much time to do my YouTube
channel. But because I found ways to
streamline the process and make it
efficient, I found ways to batch film my
content. After two freaking years, I
found a way to outsource my editing
because I was still doing my own
editing, which was really, really,
really dumb. So, you should outsource
your editing. Eventually, this process
comes becomes like clockwork. And when
you do it enough times, you start
realizing, oh, I can actually make one
video per week. I could even make two
videos per week because actually, I can
film two in a row, especially if I make
it an easy lift in terms [music] of
writing. And the more you do this, the
more you get better at the skill over
time. And provided the content is
valuable enough for your target audience
and you do some amount of research into
idea title and thumbnail, which is why
I'm spending two half my time looking
idea, title, and thumbnail. Provided you
spend enough time researching that,
things will probably work out well.
Again, there's no guarantee. YouTube is
not a guaranteed game. This is why I
said right at the start, if your goal is
to make money and YouTube is your
instrumental way that you're going to
make money with, it's just not worth it.
Like, I would not recommend doing that.
But if you like the idea of starting a
YouTube channel and growing a YouTube
channel for its own sake, you know, I
have enough money now. I don't need to
make YouTube videos, but I make YouTube
videos because it's the thing I would do
anyway. I enjoy the process of teaching.
[music] I like the idea of taking in a
question from the audience, and I like
the idea of just being able to spill
about it and draw some stuff, and it's
kind of cool. And maybe the video is not
going to go viral, but I don't really
care. Maybe the YouTube channel is not
going to make money. I don't really care
because I enjoy the craft of making
YouTube videos. So, you want to get to a
point, Anneil, where the reason you're
doing this is not because it's going to
get you to passive income, but it's
because you enjoy it and you think there
is a value in the service you're
offering to the world in some way. You
might think that hopefully your videos
are helpful to at least one person. And
the more you do that, [music] the more
the channel grows. Eventually, you get
monetized. You start making money
through AdSense. And then, if you want,
you can start doing products further
down the line. And you can get to the
point where you're making a decent a
[music] decent amount of money from it.
But again, it's not guaranteed. So,
please do not start a YouTube channel if
the reason you're doing it is for the
money. Okay? Hopefully, all that makes
sense. If you're still here, then you
might like to check out this video over
here where I break down my threepart
process for actually growing a YouTube
channel in terms of level one, get
going. Level two, get good. Level three,
get smart. It doesn't really overlap
with the stuff in this video, but it'll
give you another mental model for
thinking about how to grow a [music]
YouTube channel. Thank you so much for
watching, and I'll see you hopefully in
the next video.