so starting this youtube channel is
hands down the single best thing i've
ever done in my life
and so in this video i'm going to be
sharing my top 10 tips on how you can
get started
with setting up your own channel if
that's what you're into
coming in at number 10 we have don't
worry about what other people will say
i always ask this question i ask a
question on twitter and on instagram and
i ask people you know what are your
fears about starting on youtube and what
do you want to know
and the number one complaint is always
i'm worried about what my friends and
family will think
i've been running a course called the
part-time youtuber academy where we have
people
who are sort of aged from 18 up to like
and basically everyone in that age range
also worries about what their friends
and family will think
but you know what the thing that
everyone realizes is that once you've
uploaded your first video
all of that fear kind of goes away
because you realize that no one gives a
[ __ ] like no one actually cares
whether you're uploading videos to
youtube you might think it's like the
biggest deal in the world that oh my god
what is my mum gonna say what are my
cousins gonna say what are my friends in
university gonna say but no one actually
cares everyone is just so worried about
their own lives that the fact that i'm
doing youtube no one cares the fact that
you're gonna start a youtube channel
talking about whatever you want
no one cares and we just need to get
that into our heads and this is such a
such a common fear and we all have it
and
it's just the first thing you have to
get over basically no one cares stop
deluding yourself into thinking that
people are thinking about you
because everyone is just worried about
themselves they're worried about how
they are appearing to other people
there's this thing in psychology called
the spotlight effect which is that we
we all walk through life thinking that
there is a spotlight trained on us
and just not realizing that everyone
else is absorbed in their own life and
we are only the heroes of our own story
and we are supporting cast in everyone
else's story
if they're even thinking about us at all
so start your youtube channel do not
worry about what people will think 99
of the fear is in just before you
publish your first video but
i promise you as soon as you hit publish
on that video 99 of the fear will
disappear and you will stop worrying
what people think
then at point number nine we have gear
doesn't matter at the start
gear does matter in the long run but at
the start gear does not matter at all
when i started my youtube channel i
started filming on my iphone i did not
have any microphone attached to it i
literally just got the
camera lay in bed pointed at myself and
said hey guys i think i'm thinking i'm
gonna start some kind of vlog i knew
absolutely nothing about editing i just
followed free youtube tutorials about
how to edit videos and that's what you
have to do when you're getting started
it's like if you're starting learning
how to write it doesn't matter what pen
you're using as long as you're writing
something if you're getting started
learning how to draw it does not matter
what pencil
and what paper you're using that's all a
distraction what you need to do is just
pick up any old pencil you've got ryan
or pen that you've got lying around the
house
any old piece of paper or scrap paper
and just start learning
from day one it's the same thing with
youtube really if you're watching this
you have a device which is capable
of recording video you have your phone
if you want to get started on youtube
screw the gear don't think oh i need to
wait to upgrade to a fancy ass camera
before i'm allowed to get started on
youtube
start with whatever you have start with
your phone and you can always upgrade
later
and in fact over there is a video where
i talk about exactly how to start
filming videos with just your iphone
and it looks pretty reasonable if you do
want to upgrade something then upgrade
your audio quality firstly because
people will sit through a bad video
quality but no one will sit through bad
audio quality so that's the first thing
to upgrade and if you want to learn more
about exactly which gear to upgrade and
like a shopping list for gear at
different levels you should definitely
sign up to my part-time youtuber
free 7-day email course this is totally
free you just enter your email address
and then every day i will email you with
a long-ass article
which contains lots of tips about
getting started on youtube and one of
those in the seven day course
is about exactly what gear you need to
upgrade and in which order and i give
you different levels for gear at
different budget levels so again that'll
be linked in the video description if
you want to check it out again totally
free just seven days of emails from me
where i give you my top tips on getting
started on youtube as a beginner
point number eight we have don't worry
about the numbers once you've started on
youtube this is a mistake everyone makes
is that you
way too focused on the analytics but at
the start like it doesn't really matter
the only thing you have to do is just
keep on producing more and more and more
videos
and not really worry about the fact that
no one is watching them and that you're
not getting very many subscribers if you
look at the stats according to tubebuddy
the average channel with 1 000 to 10
000 subscribers has made 152 videos
so until you've made 152 videos you do
not have the right to complain that
you're not growing on youtube you have
to make 152 videos first
and then we can think about how to tweak
your growth prospects on youtube for me
it took me 52 videos and six months to
hit a thousand subscribers that was
making two videos a week
six months in a row while i was a
full-time medical student at cambridge
while preparing for my final year
medical student exams two videos a week
six months and then i hit a thousand
subscribers and so at the very least if
you've made anything less than 52 videos
then don't worry about your subscriber
count you can always email me for advice
or sign up to my youtube
part-time youtuber mailing list and
reply to emails on that you can always
email me for advice further down the
line
but i can't give you any advice until
you've made at least 52 videos
that's just how it works all right point
number seven is this idea of stacking
the deck in your favor so we've
established that you're gonna start your
channel and you're just gonna do it and
not care about what people think
but to succeed on youtube you wanna
think in terms of
stacking the deck how do you take the
deck and how do you stack it in your
favor now the extent to which you should
stack the deck depends on how you're
thinking about youtube
if you're thinking about youtube purely
as a hobby where you don't actually care
about the numbers and you're thinking oh
it would be nice to make money from this
further down the line but it's not my
primary aim right now
and that's great you don't need to worry
about stacking the deck in your favor
but if like a lot of students in our
course the part-time youtuber academy
you're thinking of youtube more as a
business opportunity so
the more business entrepreneurial people
minded end of the spectrum
you then want to think about how do i
stack the deck to try and grow on
youtube or to try and get
achieve my goals for youtube you know as
effectively as possible and there's
broadly two ways of stacking the deck
you can stack the deck in terms of time
or you can stack the deck in terms of
money how do you stack the deck in terms
of time well
it involves putting in the time to learn
how to get better on camera which
happens over time as you make more and
more videos
it involves putting in the time to get
better at editing videos again it
happens as you just produce more and
more videos i've got a friend called
james johnny who has grown from zero to
000 plus subscribers on youtube by
making like 10 or 12 videos or something
stupid like that because
he spends hundreds of hours editing each
one to make it craft it into a perfect
netflix documentary style video he is
stacking the deck
in his favor by spending large amounts
of time hundreds and hundreds of hours
writing scripting and editing his videos
the other way of stacking the deck in
your favor is by using money now we're
not going to talk about this because
this is a more advanced point but
for example you can invest in gear and
number two you can invest in hiring your
own team which is now what i've done
and actually a lot of people don't
realize that you can outsource video
editing for
quite cheaply very early on and so
especially if you have a job where your
time is worth
let's say more than ten dollars an hour
you can easily outsource video editing
to someone who you're paying less than
ten dollars an hour to if you want
as a way of stacking the deck in your
favor by using money again that's a bit
of an advanced point we'll talk about
that more in my part-time youtuber free
email course so sign up in the video
description if you want to check that
out but yeah that's kind of how i think
about it like there are no guaranteed
formulae to success on youtube
but really it's all about stacking the
deck in your favor in whatever way you
can
depending on what your goals for youtube
are are you a hobbyist or are you
a entrepreneur business person i'm
somewhere in the middle leaning kind of
towards the business side so i do
whatever i can to stack the deck in my
favor
point number six use your unfair
advantages now i've got a secret
three-part formula for success on
youtube and in fact
success in anything in life and that is
success equals work
multiplied by luck multiplied by unfair
advantages
now work you have to put in the work you
have to put in the time and the effort
to
do this otherwise you know it's not
going to go anywhere luck
you are kind of reliant you do have to
get a little bit lucky but the good
thing about luck is that the more videos
you put out
the higher the odds that any one of them
will get picked up by the algorithm and
will start to go viral
and in fact for my channel it's only
been like two or three videos in the
last three and a half years that have
gone really viral that have really
propelled channel growth
everything else has been fairly average
fairly mediocre so that was work and
luck but the third component of the
success equation is
unfair advantages what are the unfair
advantages that you have
that you can exploit in your youtube
channel or in whatever you're doing
for me my unfair advantage was that i
was a medical student and i was at
cambridge university
those are pretty big unfair advantages
because the niche that i was targeting
was people applying to study medicine at
cambridge university i was not trying to
be a
makeup influencer i was not trying to be
a fashion influencer or a lifestyle or
workout or fitness influencer
none of that would have used my unfair
advantage maybe the medical student
thing if i was actually
interested in fitness but you want to
think about what are the qualities i
have
what are the things that other people
can't necessarily compete with
compete with even though we don't really
want to think about this as a
competition
what are the unfair advantages that i
have that i can use to help propel my
channel and if at this point you're
thinking well i don't have any unfair
advantages you should check out a video
linked up there which will be my book
club episode of
a book called the unfair advantage which
is all about the formula to success
where i chat with one of the authors
hassan
about the five different types of unfair
advantages and we talk about
how to answer this question of like well
i don't feel like i have any advantages
because everyone has their unfair
advantages you just have to lean into
them you have to figure out what they
are
and then you want to try and weave that
into your youtube channel somehow
point number five focus on quantity
rather than quality
it is far more important when you're
starting out on youtube to make a
hundred
really bad videos than to try and make
ten really good videos caveat unless
you're going down the james johnny route
of like you know
putting in hundreds of hours of editing
into the videos that's like a different
style but like
i imagine for most people watching this
your aim is to become a youtuber that's
sort of like me whereby
you can sit in front of a camera and
talk about whatever you want and it's
kind of nice and you share your life and
you share your experiences and you do
some teaching
rather than to craft a netflix
documentary but whatever the case
quantity is more important than quality
at the start and there's a nice story
that i like which is the parable of the
pottery class
and the story goes that there is a
pottery class and the teacher divides
the group into two different groups one
of the groups has to make a pot
every day for 30 days so by the end of
the 30 days they make 30 pots
whereas the other group has to focus on
a single pot for the whole 30 days so
they only have one pot at the end of the
30 days
and then at the end of the 30 days the
teacher kind of brings all the pots
together
and judges the quality of the pots and
he gives out prizes about who's the best
pots were
and every single pot that won a prize
came from the quantity group
rather than the quality group especially
when you're getting started out in
something
there are so many learnings to be had
improving your own ability to
talk to the camera improving your
ability to edit videos improving your
storytelling
all of these happen through quantity
rather than through quality
you have to get in the reps and so my
theory on this is that you just have to
make a hundred videos
make at least 100 videos and then worry
about trying to improve the quality of
them because by virtue of making 100
videos
you're naturally going to improve the
quality of them without even really
thinking about it
but the main thing is you have to you've
got to get in the reps it's all about
quantity rather than quality at the
start number four
is don't really worry about what your
niche is like people get hung up on this
like i don't know what to make videos
about
it would be like a writer saying i don't
know what to write about therefore i'm
not going to write
or like an artist saying i don't know
what my masterpiece is going to be
therefore
i'm not going to hold a paintbrush it's
totally okay for your niche to emerge
over time
yes you can take a very calculating
route and plot it out in advance and be
like okay this is my path or you can do
what i recommend which is just start
making videos on youtube about whatever
you enjoy whatever you want if i were
starting on youtube
i wouldn't really worry about the niche
thing i just think you know what let me
make videos about the things that i
enjoy maybe some close-up magic because
i'm not a total loser
maybe like iphones maybe like you know
my favorite pen maybe like you know
tips of getting started on youtube maybe
life as a medical student maybe like
whatever experiences in my life that i
enjoy talking about and that i think i
could teach
on the internet that is the stuff i
would start making videos about and
over time as you start making videos
about things that you enjoy
the audience starts to resonate with
some of those things and so
your niche ends up emerging over time i
never thought i would be a productivity
youtuber but i seem to have become a
productivity youtuber because that niche
just sort of emerged over time it was
not
forward planned in advance and so if
you've got a lot of interest if you've
got a lot of things you're interested in
or even if you don't know what to talk
about on youtube
just start making stuff and you will
figure it out don't be one of those
writers who says i don't know what my
bestseller book is going to be about
therefore i'm not going to write a
single word
it's the same with youtube who cares if
you don't know what your niche is your
niche can
your niche will change over time i
started off making videos for medical
school applicants
i now no longer care about medical
school applicants in terms of making
videos
and therefore it's it just sort of
changes over time so don't worry about
it don't overthink it
just make the videos that you enjoy and
start
point number three be patient and be
consistent those are really the only two
things that you need for success on
youtube you need consistency
and you need patience consistency in
publishing at least one video a week
and patience in that not worrying about
the fact that you're not going to get
any traction for a large amount of time
success on youtube is absolutely
not an overnight thing and certainly
with my channel you know for my first
like 80 videos i made no money and then
i started making a few dollars here and
there
and with all of these things like with
every good thing in life
it's like a compounding returns curve
and you don't realize it when you're
right at the start of the curve because
you're not seeing any traction but three
years later if you can stick with
publishing two videos a week for three
and a half years like i've been doing
you look back and you think oh my god
you know my first 100 videos
they were just part of that getting that
flywheel to turn and really it's all
about that consistency
but also having the patience and having
the faith that this will pay off
in the long run just not in the short
term it's like one of my goals for the
new year is to get six-pack abs
but if i were to do some crunches right
now and not see any abs coming out
it would be a bit silly of me to say oh
you know why am i not growing on youtube
or why are my apps not coming out
because you have to do it every day for
several months before you see any
results and that is and that consistency
is what
gives you the result rather than a super
intense ab workout on day one
point number two is try and think about
it in terms of systems now this is a big
thing that we teach on our course the
part-time youtuber academy again if you
wanted the free seven-day email course
hit the link in the video description
but it's really all about building a
system because we've established that
the way to grow on youtube
is by being consistent for a very long
time you then want to start thinking
okay if i need to be consistent and put
out one or two videos a week for the
next five years
how can i build a system around that to
make it easier for me to do and at the
start of our youtube careers what
everyone doesn't and what i did is you
think one video at a time you think okay
what's this week's video
okay what's next week's video and then
another one but then very quickly you
realize that okay
this is quite hard to sustain and so you
want to think about building a system in
terms of
how can i generate as many ideas for
content as possible and then number two
how can i kind of refine these ideas and
turn them into titles and thumbnails and
hooks
number three how can i sort of create
these videos in parallel number four how
can i
find pockets of time throughout the day
where maybe you know i've got a
10-minute break at work or
in my lunch break where i can plan out a
video that's going to be pushed out
several months in advance
how can i plan out my content calendar
so that i actually only have to film
once and i can batch film maybe five
videos in a row
so that i don't have to go through all
the effort of setting up the lights and
camera and everything it's all of this
stuff around building a system and if
you want a book recommendation on that
you should check out the e-myth
revisited by michael gerber
this is a book i've been recommending to
all the students on our course and
everyone who's read it says that oh my
god this book is absolutely amazing
um it's just a great way of changing
your mindset to thinking in terms of
systems and that i would say that's one
of the books that's most changed my life
and that has made publishing on youtube
a lot easier because now instead of
thinking of it as one video at a time
i think of it as a holistic cohesive
coherent
system and finally point number one is
if you're thinking of getting started on
youtube then just do it you know you
could literally
pause this video right now you could get
your phone out you could switch on the
recording the
the camera uh turn on selfie mode on
your phone and be like
hey guys uh this is my first youtube
video you know i was watching ali's uh
tips on getting started on youtube video
and he was saying to be honest you
should just kind of do it and so this is
it i'm gonna start my youtube channel
and this is video number one that video
took me 11 seconds to film
and if you're starting on youtube you
could literally do that like pause this
video right now
turn on the selfie camera on your phone
and just upload it using the youtube app
on your phone
it is that simple like we all overthink
this so much like oh my god my first
video has to be good and has to be
perfect and
what are people going to think but what
we don't realize is that no one cares no
one's going to watch your first video
like who gives a who gives a toss like
if it takes the average channel 152
videos to go between 1 000 and 10 000
subscribers
why do you think that video number one
matters it's just completely
inconsequential video number two three
four five
six twenty thirty forty none of those
videos actually matter in the long run
what matters is that you actually just
get started and you realize that hitting
that publish button on youtube
is not as hard as it originally seems
and there's that quote that i like that
you know the
the best time to plant a tree was 10
years ago the second best time
is now and so if you're thinking oh damn
i wish i had started youtube 10 years i
wish i'd started youtube 10 years ago
but if i didn't have a channel and i was
watching and i'd watch to the end of
this video
i would just get my phone out and film
that video right now in fact if you're
doing that
link it in the comments down below and i
will i will subscribe to your channel
and i'll be like your first subscriber
for whatever that's worth but i just
need you to upload that very first video
and then commit to publishing at least
one video a week so those were 10 tips
on getting started on youtube you really
don't need anything else you just need
to get started
but if you're interested in joining me
on a live course where i teach
a few hundred people about how to do
this stuff with assignments and things
and everything and
we teach you about the systems based
approach to growing your channel then
check out the part-time youtuber academy
link in the video description
along with my free seven-day email
course again linked in the video
description do you need a course to
succeed on youtube no absolutely not it
really is just about publishing content
consistently and there is absolutely
nothing i teach on my course
that you can't find out on the internet
anyway check out the video creators
podcast check out the video creators
youtube channel check out think media
they've got a fantastic youtube channel
there are so many free resources online
so if you don't want to sign up to a
course that's fine you can do the work
yourself but
if you're the sort of person who
benefits from accountability and having
a community of people to go through the
process with
on top of the content that's all in one
place nicely packaged up for you then
you might like to check out the course
whatever happens once you start your
youtube channel you're gonna need some
tips for time management which is why
you should check out that video where i
talk through my eight top tips for
managing your time
so you can pump out that content
consistently thank you so much all the
best with your channel and i'll see you
in the next video bye