hey friends welcome back to the channel
if you new here my name is Ali I'm a
doctor working in Cambridge and in this
video I'm gonna show you how I use the
app notion to be more reflective about
the stuff that I read watch and listen
to
now before discovering this method I
used to spend absolutely ages listening
to podcasts reading books watching
videos about like business
entrepreneurship productivity
self-improvement all that stuff and it
was that classic trap of consuming too
much stuff but not really acting or
reflecting on any of it but all of that
changed when I discovered this amazing
method that I like to call my resonance
calendar so let's dive in and I'll show
you exactly what that looks like so this
is what my resonance calendar looks like
at the moment and the idea is that any
time I read watch or listen to anything
that resonates with me that's kind of my
bar anything that resonates with me I
will drop it into the resonance calendar
and I'll take some notes on it so for
example if we look at this episode of
the Farnam Street podcast called the
great game this was June oh three 2019
at 11 p.m.
clearly I was listening to it quite late
and I've got these various notes so at
timestamp 2305 I wrote happiness isn't
found by seeking it it's found by being
engaged in the world and sort of that's
me writing down the stuff that the the
guest on the podcast was saying because
I that particular thing resonated with
me equally at times time 27 how can I
have fun and delight to the person in
front of me that was the stuff they were
talking about and at the time I thought
oh this is some pretty legit stuff why
don't I make a few notes on it and shove
it into my residence calendar and as we
can see here I've tagged it with podcast
because it's a podcast episode and life
because I think this is pretty legit
life advice I'll talk more about the
tags in just a moment and let's take
another example this is an article that
I read in March about the Parra method
for organizing digital information by my
productivity guru to yoga Forte and what
happens when you share an article into
notion is that it just gives you the
whole article it automatically copies
and pastes the entire article into
notion so you can always come back to it
without having to go back to the website
and here I've added some notes on it
about the various ways in which I'm
gonna be applying this to my own life so
previously what would have otherwise
just been I've read an article and think
oh that's kind of cool and never do
anything about it now at least I'm
writing down my thoughts and ideas and
writing down what I plan to do with the
information so that was a quick overview
of what this resonance calendar actually
looks like I'll expand more on that in
just a sec but first let's talk about
how we actually get stuff into
residence calendar firstly we can use
the notion Web Clipper add-on thing for
Chrome so let's say if I go in my own
website and I find an article that save
resonates with me Oh
using notion as the president's calendar
where did I write this I wrote this in
March 2019 so if you sign up to my email
newsletter which I send weekly then you
can keep up to date with this sort of
stuff and you can find out about these
use cases six months before I actually
make a video about them anyway let's say
I discovered this article on Keystone
habits that I wrote in February again as
part of the email newsletter and I was
talking about something that James clear
wrote anatomic habits but whatever I can
put that straight into notion using the
notion Web Clipper so I click this
little notion icon here I can add some
notes to it so I've made my few notes
and then I hit enter and that goes
immediately into my residents calendar
and so if I open that in notion we see
immediately Keystone habits and here are
my notes about it that are formatted
weirdly so yeah here are some notes
about the article what I'm planning to
do with it
so it's copied and pasted of the entire
article in turn ocean and it's written
my notes above it so that one I'm
returning to it I can see exactly what I
wrote so that's what I use if I'm
reading stuff on Chrome and I want to
get it into notion more often than not I
tend to be reading or consuming stuff on
my iPhone or my or on my iPad and so
let's have a look here let's say I'm on
Castro which is my podcast app of choice
and I'm listening to the alternative cv
podcast which is run by one of my
friends and oh just coincidentally let's
take this episode episode one which is
how to overcome fear put yourself out
there and get started which is a
two-part interview with me or I talk
about all this sort of stuff let's say I
was listening to that again I'll put a
link in the video description if you
want to check it out I could hit this
little share button and then the share
dialog opens up and I could message it
to people though message stuff too or I
can share it directly into notion and
it's all it gets added to my resonance
calendar and if I want to I can sort of
change this to all the various databases
that I've got with a notion but because
resonance calendar is the one that I
always just add things to that's the
first one that comes up I can write the
title so I can say Ally interview on a
CV podcast
whatever it is the matter of this typos
and I can write a few notes about this
and then what I want I can hit save and
that's gone and if we look immediately
on notion which is synced across all my
devices here we go on these interview on
the AC V podcast let's fix the typo
let's hit enter to fix the formatting
and yeah here we go here are some notes
that I wrote about this incredible
interview and here are the show notes
which automatically get populated here
which is really handy because now when I
return to this I can immediately see all
the references and all the links from
this podcast and normally when I take
notes on podcasts I like to refer to the
timestamps so that lets say in six
months time I'm making a YouTube video
and referencing this podcast I know
exactly where the timestamp is and I can
get it clipped from the podcast and
shove it into my YouTube video so that
was method number two for getting stuff
into the residents calendar and then the
third and I think most interesting way
that I get stuff into the residents
calendar is actually by using my Apple
watch now often when I'm listening to
podcasts I'm listening to them a double
speed and I'm listening to them in the
car which means like yeah I could stop
by the side of the road and write down
notes on my phone if I really wanted to
and I do sometimes do that but recently
I've discovered this app and drafts for
the Apple watch here we go this is my
Apple watch this is the Apple draft so I
can tap on that and then I can hit this
record button and I can do this while
driving so that it's just two taps and
then while I'm on draft I can record
anything that I want to say about this
podcast and as you can see it is
automatically transcribing that into
text in quite a reasonable fashion if
I'm honest then I had done and then that
gets saved to my draft inbox and then I
can open up draft on my Mac and usually
it sings reasonably and here we go we've
got the draft that's synced to Mac and
so if I want to add something to the
road to the resonance calendar I just
hit the new button and then I have to do
I do have to manually input this
information so I would write the Abdal
interview with
or something like that I'd find the URL
and then I would just copy and paste the
notes from draft into notion and then I
would archive the draft using a keyboard
shortcut and this would be the way like
there is a bit of manual labor and I
would like it at some point on shore
notion is gonna open up the API and you
automatically be able to add stuff from
drafts into notion but for now I think
just copying and pasting it from one
window into another is a very reasonable
way of doing it and it also means that I
can then quick capture all the ideas
that I have while I'm driving without
having to you know stop the car on the
side of the road get my phone out and
then get late for work so that's how I
get stuff into notion and now when it's
in notion I can use various fancy
filtering features of notion to make it
more useful and more organized and often
what I'll do is because I tag stuff
there and then I can answer questions
like if a friend is asking me hey Ally
what what course would you recommend I
can be like ha funny you should ask why
don't I use this filter add a filter
let's see tags contains podcast and now
when I filtered it by that it's showing
me all of the podcasts that have
resonated with me over the last I don't
know since when was the first one since
March 23rd 2019 when I first discovered
notion and this president's calendar
thing or if we clear that filter let's
say I'm writing an article or working on
a YouTube video about productivity I
could just type in the word productivity
on the search thing and it would
automatically find all of my tags that
I've been tagged with productivity but
also all of my residents calendar items
that just have the word productivity in
them somewhere and that just makes it a
lot easier for me to create content
about productivity because now all of my
stuff about productivity everything that
I've ever read or listened to or watched
that's resonated with me about
productivity is now in this resonance
calendar and there's another pretty
high-tech feature of notion that I do
use quite often and that's the ability
to add related database items to the
residents calendar so I'll show you what
I mean by that so at the moment this
whole residence calendar thing is a
database and because notion is based on
the notion of databases it means you can
have different views depending on what
you want to see so this is the list view
where I'm just looking at the title of
the note and the tags I could also view
it in calendar mode if I really wanted
to that's how I started doing this
initially so here we go
June 2019 was when I put a load of stuff
into this because I some reason we're
just consuming lots of content
and we can see that across across the
calendar I can see the stuff that I
consumed which I guess would be quite a
nice way to look at things over time
I've also got my table and what the
table does is that it lets me add links
to ideas from the calendar so I've got
the second database called ideas and
these are ideas for either blog post or
email newsletters or articles or video
scripts that I might make at some point
further down the line and some of these
are my own ideas but actually the
majority of them are ideas that I've
picked up through reading listening and
watching to stuff and so I'd like to
link to the original source and there's
a very easy way of doing that so for
example let's take this one decision
making windows versus doors this was on
the Arianna Simpson episode of the my
first million podcast by the hustle and
I've got this property within this
database that I called resonance link
and that means I can link items in my
residents calendar to these idea items
so if I search for Simpson that should
come up here we go Oriana Simpson the
Bitcoin believer and I can add this as a
resonance link to this particular idea
and that's useful if I come across this
idea I can see where the source of it
was but it's also useful cuz if I go
back on the resonance calendar and look
in the table mode now at this point if I
go on a specific item I can see all of
the related notes the related ideas that
I did have been linked to that all in
one place and so this is really good
this means that if I'm writing my weekly
email newsletter and deciding you know I
usually pick 3 or 4 things that I
enjoyed that week that I want to share
with the audience this is gonna be quite
high up on the list because one two
three four five there are five different
ideas that are generated from this one
podcast and that these ideas can then
later be turned into blog posts and
articles and stuff so again if we go
back to my ideas database I just love
showing the stuff off because I think
it's really cool and I'd go into
refinery mode this is the Kanban view
that notion has so we've got no status
which is just where all the ideas go
we've got idea we've got draft we've got
email we've got published so actually
this windows versus doors one it starts
off on two no status and then I can drag
it over into idea when it's something
that I'm actively thinking about draft
when I'm actually writing something
about it and email when I've thought
about turning it into an email
newsletter and then
published when it becomes a blog post on
my website so I like to think of this as
the refinery I call it refinery because
I think I'm cool as sort of a refinery
for ideas I get the ideas either self
generated or from other sources that I
consume and then it goes through
different layers of the refinery
ultimately turning into a blog post and
I suppose I'll have one over here called
a video so if I turn a particular thing
into a video then that's one step
further along the the pipeline as well
and the nice thing about this is that
and I thought you recommend that anyone
does this who creates any kind of
content at all because every Sunday when
I sit down to write my weekly email
newsletter which again you can subscribe
to with a link down below back in the
day I used to start with a blank slate
and used to think ah crap I need to
write something today what should I
write and it would take me an hour or
two to think of something off the top of
my head turn it into a like a reasonably
coherent few paragraphs and and send it
out but now instead of starting with a
blank slate I can just think I need to
write email today and earlier today I
thought exactly that and I looked down
my list and earlier today I actually
wrote this windows versus doors 1 and
then this idea which I got from the
podcast became an issue of my weekly
email newsletter so that was you know
that whole process took me about 20
minutes whereas before it would have
taken like an hour or two because I'm
not starting from scratch because
thankfully I've got my resident calendar
where I've added notes and stuff to
everything that has resonated with me
over the past few months so yeah that
was quick run-through of how I use
notion as a resonance calendar I use
notion for a ton of other things as well
and I'm gonna be sort of making videos
over time about that but I think the
great thing about the residents calendar
is since I started doing this in March
2019 it's really encouraged me to be a
lot more reflective about the stuff that
I'm consuming and actively think about a
how can apply it to my own life and how
I can change my behavior based on it but
be also because I'm a content creator
integrator it lets me think about how to
take those ideas from other sources and
apply my own lens and know my own
perspective to them and then release
them out into the world as my own little
creations and stuff and obviously I link
back to the original sources and it's
quite nice doing this sort of thing
because now whenever I write an article
that's based on someone's blog or on
someone's podcast or a feature in a
video I can tweet them saying hey I
wrote this thing that features your work
and speaks in glowing terms about it you
should check it out and then these
people who I admire and want to connect
with and stuff see my tweet and like oh
this guy's giving me free publicity
this is also
so like overall a lot of good things
have happened in my life just because of
this residence calendar so if you want
to check out this residence calendar
I'll put a link to it down in the video
description and the great thing about
notion is that you can make any of your
pages public if you want to and you can
make your templates public so this is
now a public template you can now click
on it in the video description and then
you can duplicate it into your own
notion account which means you can just
get this template for free just to do
whatever you like with then you can
modify it to suit your own goals or
whatever you want to do with it and you
can just add stuff to it over time and
on the notional website you'll find a
ton of other templates this is really
cool personal wiki one that's used by
been one of the notion marketing team
and that's something that I'm gonna be
experimenting a lot with as well and I
really liked it browsing through the
templates and seeing all the various use
cases for notion but yeah that was my
residents calendar link in the video
description and yep that's pretty much
the end of the video thank you very much
for watching if you like this video you
should check out a playlist over there
somewhere of my other notion related
videos and productivity related videos
that you might like as well so thanks
for watching have a great day and I'll
see you in the next video bye bye
[Music]