hey friends welcome back to the channel
this is going to be a little bit of a
chatty video where i make some tea and
we're going to drink some tea and we're
going to talk about uh the goals new
life goals for the year fun times and
i'm going to review the life goals that
i said last year and we'll see whether
i've made any progress on them and then
we're gonna unveil or talk about my
goals for this year and along the way
i'll share what's on my bucket list and
some of my kind of some of the stuff
i've learned around the idea of goal
setting over the last 12 months or so
all right so let's start by reviewing
last year's goals the first one on the
list which is interesting was to write
an amazing bestseller book which did
absolutely not end up going to plan i
had this vague idea that you know in
january last year i was like you know
what a book is 80 000 words i'm a pretty
fast typist if i say so myself therefore
i should be able to write 2000 words a
day and so within 42 days i each six
weeks i should be able to get out the
first draft of the book and it should be
able to be good and so i was like great
by the middle of february 2021 i will
have a book first draft it is now
january 2022 a whole year later and i
still haven't got a book first draft uh
the writing a book has proven to be a
lot harder than i originally thought and
we spent a bunch of time thrashing back
and forth trying to figure out what the
key ideas are and doing the proposal and
getting book deals in various countries
now we've got all of that and now i need
to write the first draft of the book and
so i've given myself well my publisher
deadline is july so the middle of this
year but i've given myself the deadline
in march by march i'll have the first
draft and then we'll spend a few months
like hopefully tightening it up and
trying to actually make it good because
the vibe is that the first draft of a
book is always really really crap and
you just have to lean into that and make
a really crappy first draft the next
goal we had was
make progress towards finding a wife and
i put this into my anti-wasteman system
which is the notion template that i'll
link down below by the way thank you
notion for sponsoring this video more on
them later anyway make progress towards
finding a wife why well because
relationships are one of the most
important parts of life and it's good to
take this seriously moving forward plus
it would be fun and hopefully if i meet
the right person my life will be better
although tbh i can't imagine that a lot
at all that's what i wrote about a year
ago so how did that go well i feel like
i have actually made progress towards
finding a wife like setting that as a
sort of one of my active goals i was
working on for last year did genuinely
make me take dating more seriously it
was a bit of a shame about lockdown but
i managed to go on a few dates and i
actually actually met someone who i'm
feeling pretty good about so more on
that in a later video we'll we'll keep
this one fairly pg for now am i right
goal number three was six-pack abs why
because it's a fun challenge would
potentially help the wife quest never
had abs before so it's a novelty and
would encourage healthy behaviors ish
and i had reasoned that by december 2021
i'll have had a period of at least two
weeks where my abs are showing i need to
convert into into a body fat percentage
this did not end up working out i guess
i sort of tried to try i didn't really
try properly i was just like oh kind of
vaguely give it a go i did get a
personal trainer which really helped and
i did start kind of counting my macros
and doing that kind of stuff but i
realized pretty quickly into the year
that i don't really care massively about
the goal i think this is one of those
things where if you are working on a
goal that has that requires lots of time
effort and some level of sacrifice it's
actually quite hard to consistently
motivate yourself to work towards it if
you fundamentally don't actually care
about the goal at the end of it so the
reason i wanted six pack abs was sort of
just for the bands i didn't really have
a compelling reason other than this
vague idea that oh maybe it'll make me
more attractive so yeah that did not
happen maybe it's a thing that i might
actually go for this year but but we'll
see all right so goal number four was to
busk on the london underground would be
cool it's been on my bucket list for
ages now and i said that by december
i'll have had my busking license for the
london underground and i'll have filmed
myself busking at least once ended up
not happening i actually did reach out
to a friend mary spender who is a
musician and youtuber link in the video
description if you want to check her out
and uh someone emailed me who saw that
on my bucket list and said that
apparently the london underground
because of kovid was stopping renewing
licenses for buskers on it i haven't
really looked into it it's not a huge
priority anymore so what else well
number five or whatever we are was to
become a better storyteller and i did
actually have a private coaching with a
chap called matthew dix who is like one
of the world's best storytellers he's
won bunch of competitions and written a
really good book called story worthy so
i had some sessions with him and i did
kind of improve my storytelling ability
but initially what started off as like
coaching on how to be a better
storyteller ended up actually turning
into coaching on how to write my book
better and i realized that actually the
sessions i have with matthew i would
rather we work on the book rather than
we work on my verbal storytelling
abilities because i think they're fine
it's ended i decided after a while that
this wasn't a huge priority and finally
one of my goals for last year was to
learn to draw like a concept artist and
i really wanted to learn how to draw and
i did actually do this for about three
or four months i had an art teacher
called alessandro who and we had lessons
two or three times a week where i was
kind of practicing human anatomy and
like learning how to draw and shade and
all that kind of stuff and after a few
months i realized that i was waking up
in the morning and i was like ah crap i
have an art i said now and when i had
that feeling of uh oh crap i don't want
to do this like you know i stuck with it
for a while i was like okay well you
know not everything is fun all the time
but
my general philosophy for life is that i
don't really want to do stuff that feels
like a lot of hard work and effort to do
i'd rather work with my own natural
motivations and work with my energies
energy that sounds a bit woo um but i'd
rather do things that i genuinely enjoy
that leads to good outcomes rather than
kind of force myself to do these things
and the art lessons were fun but after a
few months i realized that actually
i don't have that much time in my life
with all the other stuff that's going on
with the book and the business and the
youtube channel and the art lessons
became not a priority so i guess if
we're thinking about lessons that i've
learned for goal setting there's a few
things that come to mind firstly i think
it's actually about setting fewer goals
rather than more goals i think probably
i had too many things last year that i
was like you know what i really want to
work on this thing and then after a
while of working on them i realized
actually hmm time is starting to run out
i kind of want to have a healthy
balanced life i don't quite have enough
drive or productivity to get absolutely
everything done therefore i'm going to
choose to abandon certain activities and
this is a thing that oliver berman talks
about in his really good book 4000 weeks
which is that in a dream world we would
have the time to do all the things our
to-do list would be up today we would be
replying to all our friends we'd be
hosting dinner parties we'd be crushing
it at work we'd be writing our book in
the real world we're actually never
gonna have time to do all the things we
want to do and so we have to
strategically decide what are the things
that we want to fail at and i
strategically decided last year to fail
at the art lessons to fail at the
busking thing to fail at the six-pack
abs thing because i realized that i just
don't care enough about those things
compared to the other stuff that i was
working on the other thing i realized is
that it's a lot easier to work on a goal
when that goal is
a side effect of something else that you
want to do so i'll use an example when i
first learned to code i never set out to
learn to code i set out to create my
personal website and then later to build
a game and learning to code was a thing
that kind of happened as a side effect
of this other wider project that i cared
about that i was working towards
similarly um i have friends who learned
to play the piano and they learned to
play properly by following the path and
doing things with the classical music
and all that jazz and they hated
learning learning to play the piano
because they weren't working towards
anything that they fundamentally cared
about whereas i've got other friends
including myself you know i learned to
play the piano because i wanted to be
able to play disney songs by ear that
was the project that i was aiming for
and learning the piano kind of happened
as a side effect for the guitar as well
i didn't want to learn the guitar i
wanted to be able to play chords to
accompany myself and my friends because
i had that as a goal learning the guitar
kind of happened as a side effect and i
think one of the mistakes i made last
year is that like you know i've i've
often had on my bucket list like get
more fit take my health more seriously
take stretching more seriously learn to
cook
and
i've realized recently that i'm never
going to learn something just for its
own sake in isolation like i don't know
anyone who's learned to code by actually
just saying i want to learn to code and
then learning the only people i know who
have ever learned to code have had
projects to work on and have learned to
code as a side effect so this year when
it comes to my goal setting what i'm
really thinking about is okay if i care
about taking cooking seriously how can i
make the learning to cook a side effect
of something else that i want to do and
finally one thing that i've learned and
or rather realized or appreciated more
recently is that it's actually
completely okay to change your mind i
think a lot of us set ourselves these
new year's resolutions and like i want
to work on these goals for the year and
then we get new data points we realize
you know we try it and we fail at some
of the stuff and we realize cool that's
okay like the more we try something the
more data points we get about the thing
and so there's very little point in
whole clinging to this vision that we
kind of vaguely decided a year ago just
just because we decided a year ago and
there's a really good quote that i
apparently came from einstein although
although it's probably a bit of a myth
where it's like plans are totally
pointless but planning is indispensable
and i think i i think i do fully agree
with that like even within our business
we spend a lot of time planning and
strategizing and the plans that we come
up with are ultimately not really that
useful because stuff changes so quickly
but the act of planning and the act of
actually intentionally figuring out what
are my goals for the year what are the
business goals for the year what are my
goals in health wealth love happiness
and impact even if the plan changes just
the fact that you spent the time
planning is actually helpful okay so
that was a bit of a review of the goals
and the lessons i now actually have a
call to go to and so i'm gonna see you
in about an hour let's go
alrighty we are back let's now talk
about the goals that i'm gonna be
setting for the new year and i have
converted my anti-wasteman system into a
notion template linked in the video
description thank you notion of
sponsoring this video but i had this
template anyway from last year as well
i've just turned it into templates
rather than tables just to make it a
little bit easier to read so for each of
my goals i'm going to go through how i'm
thinking about how to set the goals
using the anti-waste man system and
we'll see what happens so goal number
one is to write my book properly so the
dream here is to write my book
or rather the dream is to write a book
i'm proud of
now this is an interesting thing with
goal setting is because like before i
had like a smart smart goal type thing
you know specific measurable all that
kind of stuff but i realized i'm not
really a huge fan of the whole smart
goal vibe because like i like achievable
and realistic are kind of the same thing
timely and sort of specific are kind of
the same thing time but like it's it's
it's got a few issues with it but we're
gonna
everyone talks about smart goal settings
so we're gonna we're gonna humor that um
a little bit and crucially it's right a
book i'm proud of because that is a goal
that's 100 within my control this is
another thing i've realized over the
last year that generally for goals that
we want to set most of our goals should
be goals that are 100 within our control
so i don't want to write a book that
hits a new york times bestseller list
well although i do but i don't have that
as a goal and i don't want to write a
book that critics are proud of although
i do but that's i don't want that as a
goal because it relies on someone else
being the gatekeeper to whether i
actually accomplish this thing that i
want to do i want it to be write a book
i'm proud of because that is something
that's 100 within my control so why do i
want to write the book well firstly
because it's fun and it's going to be
fun and it's kind of fun doing the
process of writing a book also i now
have a bunch of book deals got a book
deal in america and in the uk and in a
bunch of different countries for
translation so i actually need to write
the book because publishers are have
paid money for it already and advance
and so i now need to deliver on that
promise that i've made which is a pretty
compelling reason to write the book it
could be an interesting way to reach a
new audience people who may not
necessarily watch youtube videos but
might read a book could be good and to
be honest i've always kind of wanted to
write a book and if the book is good it
could hopefully unlock interesting
opportunities further down the line so
that's why i want to write a book i'm
proud of smart goal wise i want to aim
to complete the first draft by the 31st
of march and send the final manuscript
to the publishers by the 31st of july
fingers crossed we'll see if that works
next the question is what habit do i
want to do that is going to make this
more likely to happen and i've already
started doing this which is that every
single day except mondays where we have
team meetings all day every day tuesday
through to sunday from 9 00 am to 12
noon i have that three hours blocked out
for writing time and we've also tried to
do is clear my calendar of all the kind
of business type stuff so i'm not in
meetings all week which was a problem
like earlier this year so that i have
more time to write the book next we have
an interesting question how surprised
would i be if i failed on a scale of a
one to ten so one being not surprised at
all and 10 being very surprised i would
give myself a seven for this i would be
reasonably surprised if i didn't manage
to hit these deadlines and to write a
book i'm proud of um i'm still maybe in
that sort of uh uninformed optimism
stage uh you know where to talk about
with the dip and stuff but honestly like
i would be pretty surprised if i didn't
manage to do this
next we ask what are the top three
reasons that i might fail at the goal
okay so reason number one might be that
um don't make enough time to write the
book
reason number two might be that it takes
longer than expected
to make it good
and reason number three might be that
um urgent things keep propping up
so that i never make time for it which
kind of relates to point number one now
this is the sort of thing that i find is
really useful to think about like what
are the top three reasons why i might
fail at this thing for whatever goal
that i set whether it's at the start of
the year or not and i think it's
something that more people should think
about and anytime i have a friend who
says hey i want to really do this thing
i asked them oh okay cool you know so
just out of curiosity how surprised
would you be if you failed and what are
the top three reasons you might fail and
these are genuinely things that people
tend not to ask themselves when it comes
to goal setting and so having it as part
of the template as part of the system i
found last year was very helpful and i'm
hoping it'll be helpful this year as
well the next question is who can help
who not how good book by ben hardy and
dan sullivan as well like who can we
enlist to help with the book writing
journey so firstly book coach
editors agent team
audience like there's a bunch of people
who can help on the book writing journey
and i've done a bunch of brainstorming
to help to figure out how these people
might help next we come to how can i
stack the deck to succeed so what are
the things i can do to help minimize the
um you know the risk of that these top
three reasons would happen so firstly i
can make sure the calendar is always
empty for book writing i can tell my
team the importance of me having time to
write the book so that they don't
randomly put stuff in my calendar that
interferes with book writing time i can
be super disciplined with my writing
habit and actually make sure that when
i'm sitting down i'm actually writing
the book rather than browsing twitter or
other things that i tend to do and to
avoid the procrastination thing that's
inevitably gonna happen i can make it
super easy to get started with a book
each morning like having the computer
out already knowing what i'm gonna write
the night before or while i'm in bed the
morning of so that when i get to the
computer i can just start writing
without having to first think ah what
did i actually have to do and then the
final question of the anti-waste man
system is what is the action that i can
take right now while i'm doing this
goal-setting thing to make sure i am
well i will be on my path to achieving
my goal and that is blocking out time in
the calendar which i have done already i
should actually did that a couple weeks
ago making sure that nine to 12 every
single morning other than mondays is
blocked out for book writing time all
right so that was goal number one let's
move on to goal number two so i'm going
to click this add a new goal button
which conveniently fills all this stuff
in i'm not going to bother with it right
now but i will fill this in afterwards
and it will all be in the template
that's linked down below so writing the
book is goal number one that i need to
do for the year and to be honest if
that's the only goal that i managed to
accomplish this year i think this year
will have been time well spent goal
number two for me is to build a
sustainable fitness habit i'm not
setting a goal this year that like i
want to get six-pack abs or anything
like that basically i just want to have
a habit whereby i will work out three or
four times a week and enjoy myself
recently i subscribed to apple fitness
plus and i did my first apple fitness
plus workout a couple of days ago and
i've also been working with an
accountability coach who checks in with
me every week and and says to me you
know are you making progress on this
stuff and i stick time in my calendar
where i'm gonna work out and then he
messages me as well to be like hey how
was the workout and that's just a useful
way of me to add in an extra layer of
accountability to do this thing that i
genuinely want to do but that i might
struggle to do otherwise ideally i would
have a project that i'm working towards
we haven't found one yet but you know
one thing i've always wanted to do well
not always for the last few years it's
been on my bucket list to become a gym
shark athlete another thing i'm toying
with the idea of is is like wouldn't it
be cool to try and get hench and then
get on like the front cover of maybe
men's health magazine or something like
that just just just for fun just for the
bands but to have a project to work
towards so that kind of me working out
is not an exercise in just lifting
weights up and down against gravity but
it's actually working towards something
so similar to the learn to code example
when you have a project it's easier to
learn the thing similarly i think if i
had a fitness project it would be easier
to actually keep up the sustainable
fitness journey goal number three was
actually to learn to cook but since the
stuff that i've learned this year about
goal setting i have changed the goal
away from learn to cook i've made the
goal to host regular dinner parties so
what i ideally want to do is every one
or two weeks i want to host a party an
intimate dinner at my flat in london
where i invite some friends
over and i want to try and mix up
friendship groups so that my friends
from different circles can get to know
one another and i'll make it a point
that instead of ordering take away for
those dinner parties i will have to cook
something for those dinner parties so
i'm hoping that this little project will
be a forcing function that encourages me
to learn how to cook and since i've said
this you know actually i think tomorrow
evening is my first kind of trial dinner
party i've messaged a few friends from
university inviting them over i don't
have any idea what i'm gonna cook yet
but i've been watching a lot of youtube
videos binging with babish and ethan and
like alex french guy and pro home cooks
and these are the cool cooking youtube
channels so hopefully tomorrow's meal
will go well goal number four is to take
stretching more seriously so i have
really bad posture i've got anterior
pelvic tilt and i'm not very flexible at
all and so for the last few years i've
had do stretching on my new year's
resolutions list but this year i now
have a project to work towards and that
is that i want to learn acro yoga akka
yoga is that really cool thing that
really cool people like sam kolder and
stuff do where it's like
i mean we'll put some b-roll here you've
got people on the floor you've got like
a a bass and you've got a flyer and like
with a partner you're doing this cool
yoga stuff together yes akka yoga is
something that i really want to do but
to get reasonable acro yoga you have to
actually be able to do a straight
straight straight leg raise at the base
because i'm likely to be the base
obviously and my hamstring flexibility
is just so so so bad so i've actually
been working on my hamstrings over the
last couple of weeks um the the way i do
it is when i'm brushing my teeth my
electric toothbrush tells me every 30
seconds it like buzzes so for each 30
seconds i do like one leg the other leg
one leg the other leg in terms of
hamstring stretches and i have actually
found that my hamstring flexibility has
noticeably improved in the last two or
three weeks of doing this with brushing
my teeth because i'm trying to get my
hamstrings more flexible to the point
that i can then successfully be a base
during acroyoga so again this is another
example of where having the project of
trying acroyoga requires me to be a
baseline level of flexibility and i'm
hoping that will a be fun because
acroyoga seems really cool but b that it
will help me kind of get to my
flexibility and stretching goal without
that being an explicit goal and goal
number five we have to get better at
singing honestly i don't really have a
project associated associated with this
i probably should maybe something around
busking maybe busking in london maybe
busking a lot of underground maybe in
common garden in these cool places in
london but to be honest i could just do
that anyway and i have busted in
cambridge before so i just really want
to get better at singing because
ultimately i do want to make music
videos on youtube maybe for my second
channel maybe with the team we've got a
few people in the team who are
absolutely sick of music absolutely sick
of singing and i really like the idea of
making like a team band where we film
voice avenue style videos here in studio
in fact that would be a pretty good
project for the year that would
encourage me to get better at singing
encouraged me to get better at piano and
guitar and music theory so that we can
form this band so that's going to be our
little project right so those are my
personal goals that's what i'm following
this anti-waste man system for the stuff
that i want to do myself then we have a
bunch of business goals as well we've
been we've been working with a business
coach and following this method on a
book called traction that's called the
entrepreneurial operating system and we
have six main goals for the year uh the
first one is that we want to run three
successful cohorts of our part-time
youtuber academy where hopefully we can
get 1500 students and make a revenue of
3 million pounds 3 million something
like that from our youtuber academy that
would be really cool as goal number one
goal number two is to launch a bunch of
other kind of evergreen courses so that
we can hopefully get to the point where
by the end of the year we're making a
hundred thousand pounds a month from our
extra courses other than the youtuber
academy goal number three is to have the
book written that is a personal goal but
it's also a business goal so other
people are hopefully going to be helping
along the way and giving me the
motivation to succeed at that goal
number four is that we want to have a
very classy and nice and non-sales money
sales and marketing funnel for our
courses i don't really like the way a
bunch of these like internet gurus do it
and i want to do it in a nice way that
doesn't shove things down people's
throats that would be ideal goal number
five is that we have like core processes
in the business which are documented and
followed by everyone at the moment we
have a reasonably large team of 17
people but we've really run into the
problem where the people who are here in
the early days so like me angus
christian elizabeth we have a bunch of
stuff in our head of stuff that we've
just done and like when new people come
into the business because that stuff's
not written down anywhere it's like
really hard for them to get up to speed
on what's going on so basically we want
to have a we want to get to a point
where all of the key processes of the
stuff that we do for our courses and
videos and podcasts and socials and blog
et cetera et cetera it's all written
down so that someone else could come in
and sort of follow the checklist as it
were and finally there's this new
youtube channel project that we're
launching which we're hoping to get to
at least 100 000 subscribers and i'm not
to be honest i'm not really a fan of
these goals like
the the thing is that like as i said
before like i'm a fan broadly of goals
that are within my control and having a
certain revenue can't count a certain
subscriber count a certain kind of
amount of followers that kind of thing
it's a goal that's not really within our
control but um it is there as just sort
of a thing for the business i don't like
having those goals personally and then
we break those down as a business into
goals that are within our control as
well now if you want to follow this
anti-waste man system for goal setting
you will find the notion template linked
down in the video description and
completely coincidentally notion are
also sponsoring this video if you
haven't heard by now notion is just like
the ultimate it's like a cross between
like a google docs and google sheets and
like web design software and like a
content management system and just like
it's basically an app that i have been
using to organize my life for the last
two years back in the day you know
people used to come up to me and be like
hey i bought an ipad because of your
recommendation these days most people
who recognize me on the streets in
london or whatever say i started using
notion because of your recommendations
because i made a couple of a few videos
about notion back in the day we still
use notion for basically everything in
the business we are living in notion all
day all of our videos have written a
notion and i even use notion to track
things like my anti-wasteman system my
annual reviews for my personal goals as
well if you want to check out notion
then hit the link in the video
description it's completely free you can
pay for the extra plans if you want but
you can easily get by with notion by
using the completely free plan and you
can check the link in the video
description for my anti-waste man
template as well which you can then
duplicate into your own workspace
completely for free you have to pay a
penny and you can do this goal setting
system if that's the sort of thing
that's up your stream so thank you
notion for sponsoring this video and
thank you for watching this far if you
enjoyed this video you might like to
check out this video over here which is
the 21 or so the life lessons that i
learned in 2021 that might be
interesting if you want to see the stuff
that i've learned throughout the year in
addition to my philosophies on goal
setting so thank you so much for
watching do hit the subscribe button if
you aren't already and i'll see you
hopefully in the next video bye