hey friends welcome back to the channel
if you new here my name is Ali I'm a
doctor working in Cambridge and in this
video I want to talk you through my
annual review process or I basically
think about and write down all of the
things that I'm grateful for that people
that I'm grateful for the stuff I've
discovered that year lessons I've
learned and stuff that I want to kind of
do more better the following year if you
haven't done an annual review before
then I would highly recommend that you
do it and I'll show you the process that
I go through so maybe you can get some
ideas and I'll be sharing my template
that I'm using for this on notion so
that if you want you can just kind of
duplicate that template and you can go
through this process yourself so this is
my life OS kind of notebook this is kind
of a kind of a nerdy joke on my pot
let's not worry joke it's kind of true
because I like to I like to use notion
as like the operating system for my life
so I've got like my daily highlights and
some of my weekly reviews here but I've
also got my annual reviews and I'm gonna
show you the non private one where I've
removed all the potentially sensitive
things now here are the general kind of
categories of stuff that I like to
mention in my annual review so firstly I
like to talk about stuff that I'm
grateful for then stuff I discovered
then life lessons then stuff to work on
for next year and then like a bucket
list of kind of just general things I'd
like to do at some point in my life and
that can be as unrealistic as we want
and previously I used to do this on
Evernote but the nice thing about notion
is that you can use these toggle
features which means that it doesn't
like turn into this whole last massive
page of stuff you can kind of put things
in these totals so let's start with
experiences this is just a few of them
stuff I'm grateful for recent trip to
Japan
recent trip to Seville in Spain trip to
Sudan in January was quite nice super
nice for any people healthy amount of
figuring finger cutting going on in the
clinics etc so like alongside each one
I've just written a few notes for myself
to jog my memory because kind of the
point of the annual review is not just
to reflect on the year and to plan the
following year but I think in maybe five
six seven ten years time it'll be really
nice to look back on the annual reviews
that I've been doing since 2017 and
seeing kind of the trajectory of where
my life is gone which is why I'd like to
add a few a few bits of explanation to
each one so that is experiences general
surgery placement really enjoy the
teamwork making friends with
me Joe and Antonia there was some
colleague that I was working with guys
if you're watching thanks you're great
next I've got like people now and this I
actually had like a list of about 100
and 100 people but I've got rid of most
of them because you don't need to know
and a few of them were sensitive all
that stuff but came as my brother said
that the podcast has been quite fun had
been having good chats and I think he's
a really good sounding board for ideas
so table if you're watching you're
probably not cuz you don't watch any of
my videos and you know thank you for
that
malee use my housemate a few notes about
Molly so socializing my default by this
I mean it's really nice to have someone
that I can just kind of talk to by
default when I get home from work and
that's been really nice
Molly's also kind of taught me a lot
about sort of feeling and expressing my
own emotions and getting better better
at communication and stuff like that and
has been offering some pretty good
advice about love life amongst other
things so thanks Molly for that Paul yes
he started a podcast recently so it's
really nice having a creator friend to
talk to about that sort of stuff and
just a few other notes about some of my
other friends and I've deleted loads so
if you're a friend of mine in real life
and you know on this list don't worry
you're probably in the private one I
didn't want to share all this stuff
publicly also I'm Thomas Franklin that
list he's great he's another
productivity youtuber he's not bigger
than I am but he I gave really gave me a
lot of really good advice a few months
ago and he introduced me to the agency
that I'm now part of which is called
standard we've got Dave who runs
standard and signed me on to this agency
and that's really changed the game in
terms of YouTube because it means that
now we can do sponsored videos pretty
much whatever and that means that
there's a lot more money coming in which
means that I can actually hire people
full-time and I can kind of scale the
YouTube channel in a way that I haven't
really been able to do before so thanks
guys for that Simon Clark I haven't
actually met Simon Clark in real life
but he was one of the two youtubers that
really inspired me to start this YouTube
channel I'll put a link to his channel
down below and Peter McKinnon everyone
knows Peter McKinnon famous photography
videography youtuber he was another big
inspiration starting this channel he
recently yeah I've I've written here
that he recently released a camera bag
on Kickstarter and as soon as I saw this
I was like immediately dropped five
hundred dollars on it and it was really
weird excited I don't usually get
emotional about things but like when I
when I was buying that camera bag I was
like oh my god this is amazing finally
have a chance of giving back to Peter
McKinnon who's inspired me to start this
YouTube channel anyway moving on
accomplishments I feel a bit uneasy
about the word accomplishments because
like you know I don't like the idea of
taking credit for stuff but you know
people say you should talk about your
accomplishments in your annual review
and this is normally a private thing so
I apologize but yeah you know you tube
growth revenue growth hiring a full-time
team member you launching an online uk
caucus we launched a podcast me and my
brother we've been doing it for the last
like 36 weeks with some semblance of
consistency which has been good email
newsletter has grown quite a lot I think
this time last year it was maybe 4,000
subscribers now we're on 18,000
subscribers which is awesome Instagram
recently hit 50k which is cool and
became a physiology supervisor at Girton
College came fruit which has been really
fun and a nice accomplishment I think
I've gotten a little bit more hinge like
you know I've been going to the gym
semi-regularly for the last few weeks
and so people have been commenting on on
the biceps whatever combating hair loss
with finasteride I've been taking
finasteride since like January and I
feel like my hair has has kind of grown
back a little bit and a little bit of
chat about dating there are a few more
things on the list but I got rid of some
and then like stuff that I'm grateful
for again this is gonna seem a bit
big-headed but this is normally supposed
to be a private thing but I thought I'd
I'd share some of it so I absolutely
love my desk setup I've got a video
about it I'll link down below but
anytime like it's clean it's not right
now there's loads of stuff behind the
camera that you can't see any time my
desk is clean I just feel like a real
inspiration to to create stuff my car is
really quite nice so this is something
I've been actively trying to tell myself
because I drove it like a 8 year old car
that I've been driving because I lost
like 5 years and you know it's broken
down a fair bit but I'm trying to kind
of I'm trying to talk myself out of
wanting to buy a Tesla so I'm having
having to reiterate to myself to
actually you know my car is really quite
nice it's all good the flat is great for
the few light bulbs are also there was
this notebook that I enjoyed my I
discovered the added s ultra boost shoes
which have been really comfortable and
you know just stuff like that and then
game changers so I put I put three
things on this list firstly a standard
that I said is the agency that I'm now
part of that has really helped generate
sponsored videos for this for this
channel number two is editors so I
started outsourcing the editing of these
videos about six months ago and as soon
as I kind of took that plunge I mean
perhaps
he was even four months ago as soon as I
took that plunge then suddenly like so
much of my own time was freed up every
week and I could kind of do more things
like go to the gym and trying to eat a
bit more healthily and stuff like that
and finally I think like notion that
this this app that I'm doing this on has
genuinely been a game-changer because
like I use notion for so many different
things I think it's one of the few apps
that by design and like just because of
the app it's sort of changed the way I
think about stuff a little bit and I'm
not just saying that because they're
sponsoring the video this was on this
list before I knew this was going to be
a sponsored video so yeah anyway that's
we're talking about stuff I discovered
this year again I've just cut it down
for clarity the Wheel of Time series by
Robert Jordan really good series of
books I've been listening to an audible
burning a second brain I see a workshop
online course series of blog posts by a
guy called tiago Forte that's sort of
changed the way I think about content
creation and about note-taking notion
talked about that already the julienne
method for building muscle this is guy
called Julian Oh Julian calm and he's
written this like really in-depth guide
that's very follow able about how to
build muscle effectively and I've been
literally following that sort of and I
found that working out and going to the
gym and stuff while listening to audible
is much more fun now that I've got this
method to follow and I've tried loads of
things over the years strong lift and
5:31 and a few others but Julia but the
Julian method is the one that I think
I've stopped to for the longest so yeah
the e-myth is a book I'm blanking on who
it's by
but it talks a lot about how to grow a
small business and I've run a small
business called six med and I think I
made a lot of mistakes in the early
stages of six med by not delegating
enough and by thinking that I had to do
everything and now in my my second
business this YouTube channel I'm
starting to I feel like I'm
incorporating a lot of these lessons a
bit more and the e-myth was a really
good book that helped me out with that
discovered that you can use an oven to
cook food discover the power of light
lunches that if you eat a heavy lunch
then you feel like really full for the
rest of the day and feel tired if you
eat a light lunch then at least for me I
feel more energized Lori she termed
19:17 some somewhere in my bag it's like
a physical notebook that I like writing
stuff by hand in bulletproof radio stuff
about bio hacking that's a podcast that
I listen to as a few other things on the
list but let's move on next we're
talking about life lessons so all 15 of
these are actually editions of my email
newsletter so anytime I come across a
good life lesson that I find it that I
think is valuable
I share it in my weekly email newsletter
so every Sunday I send this email out to
now eight
thousand one hundred people as of the
time of this recording put link in the
description below if you want to sign up
you can check out all the previous
issues but just going through life
lessons quickly you know if this if this
isn't nice I don't know what is this is
a quote from Kurt Vonnegut who wrote
here he wrote in one of his books or
something and he says that you know as
you're going through life take take a
bit of time every now and then to ask
yourself if this isn't nice I don't know
what is and that just reminds us to be
grateful of things the daily highlights
are gonna be working on a video on that
but essentially the idea is that every
day you pick a single thing that you're
gonna focus on and that's going to be a
highlight of the day window openers vs.
door knockers an analogy that came to
mind that I discovered in a podcast
obvious to you amazing to others this is
reference to a blog post by Derek
Siver's the flywheel concept that I
first came across in a want to say Jim
Collison interview on the Tim Ferriss
show something like that master boring
fundamentals a life life advice
productivity thing that I learned from a
guy called James Stuber basically
there's a long list of stuff I'll put
links to all of these different email
newsletters all 15 of them in the video
description so you can kind of click on
them and find out more but essentially
the idea of the life lessons thing is
that when you're doing your annual
review then you can no doubt that
lessons that you learnt that here and I
think that's quite a nice thing to look
back on like I look back on my 2017 ones
and I think in 2017 I wrote about the
power of consistency and that's
something that has really helped it like
grow everything that I've ever tried to
do like my business YouTube channel
podcast and stuff just really about the
power of just being consistent with
things anyway next we've got stuff to
work on for next year so yeah of the
three things that I've kind of put this
into his life medicine and side hustles
for now I'm gonna add more to this list
this is sort of a work in progress but I
thought I'd share it as you know we're
approaching the end of the year and you
know you might want to do your own
annual review anyway so I want to get
more consistently going to the gym I
think it's much more possible now that I
don't have to edit a lot of these videos
by myself which is fantastic I want to
get a lot better at cooking I don't
really cook a lot make poached eggs
occasionally make some pasta
occasionally but more often than not I
either eat at work get a McDonald's
drive-through on the way home or order
takeaway from delivery which is quite
bad so I want to get into cooking a
storytelling I want to get better at
telling stories this is kind of good in
real life just as a general social skill
that I've discovered in a book by Tainan
called superhuman social skills which is
actually really good but also telling
stories is really important when you're
making videos and writing
on the Internet yeah stuff like that
yeah dating I think I'm starting writing
more about this normally when I'm doing
an annual review I would flesh this out
but I'm filming it I'm filming this on
the 20th of December so over the next
like ten eleven days I'm gonna flesh
these things out more I just wanted to
share it but yeah I think I want to want
to make more of an effort with dating
internet trying to meet more people you
know stuff like that I'm gonna be 26
next year so I feel like you know might
as well get on that sooner rather than
later anyway
medicine figure out what specialty to
apply for take some exams get pro
teaching communication skills I'm
currently training as a facilitator for
communication skills get pro teaching
physiology maybe make some videos and
then side hustles these are some like
ideas of things that I want to do for
the YouTube channel for the blog for the
podcast that sort of stuff and finally I
think it's important to have in our
annual reviews a bucket list yeah a
bucket list king can be as unrealistic
as you like and I've started making mine
I normally have at least like 50 things
on the bucket list just cuz I find it
this is generally quite useful to just
think about everything in life that I
could possibly want to be doing and then
just chuck it onto the bucket list
and you know maybe some of them will
happen maybe some of them won't but like
it just sort of gives us that level of
kind of background processing like if
I've got you know let's see
learn archery on my bucket list just the
fact that I've written that down means
that if the opportunity comes up to
learn archery or I have some time one
afternoon and the thought comes to me
that all you know I wonder what's on my
bucket list then I might seek out
archery lessons or find some kind of
week-long holiday camp or you learn
archery and stuff like that and just
kind of sayings to the video now makes
me want to Google how to do archery and
like I'm sure there's some kind of
retreat that you can go on where you
can't rub it and eat them and you know
it's stuff like that but I think just
the act of writing things down is really
helpful in that in that regard so am i
less become a gym sock athlete that is
you know that's never gonna happen but
just to find that it on my bucket list
means that it encourages me to go to the
gym more consistently eat more
consistently and get better at social
media so you know I think it's good to
have on the bucket list a few collabs
that I really like to do archery sword
fighting is really cool
I've recently been reading loads of
fantasy book series for the last like
two three years now and you know
obviously sword fighting is a big part
of fantasy busk on the London
Underground and film it and then
definitely the bucket list write a book
host a revision retreat my brother and I
had this idea right so we like this idea
of getting a group of people together
and maybe getting an air B&B cottage in
a random place like you know in
Lake District in the UK or in you know
the South of France or something where
we get sort of 1015 people together and
the idea is that we would study for our
exams kind of during the day and then in
the evenings would just kind of chill
out and have food and play board games
and stuff sort of like a revision
retreat so that's something that I maybe
want to do next year or maybe the year
after at some point
film is study with me video in a
ridiculous location I thought would be
cool to film like a study with me video
like you know in front of the pyramids
in Egypt or you know something like
weird exotic location like that
not seeing Egypt is weird but you you
know you probably get the message get
married have a kid perform a magic show
teaching medicine revision lecture
series past the MRC PMRC SFM or cos year
FRC a these are all various and
postgraduate medical exams I kind of
like the idea of doing all of them just
for bands because I love studying and I
love exams but you know it's on the
bucket list it doesn't have to be
realistic that's fine
convert a room into a YouTube studio
we'll see buy-to-let a house I want to
buy a house and then rent it out it's
like you know a real estate investment
buy a Tesla Model 3 it's on the bucket
list it's gonna happen at some point but
you know I want to convince myself that
my current car is legit for as long as I
can stream on Twitch join a world of
warcraft a raiding guild and yeah I'm
just gonna flesh this more out as we go
along so this is sort of the stuff that
I like to put on my annual reviews there
are loads of other ways of doing an
annual review and again in the video
description I'm going to link to a few
others are the formats for annual review
for example Tiago Forte who runs this
building a second brain thing his annual
reviews like 50 different questions but
a lot of them are quite like goal
orientated and list your top three wins
for the year what are your top goals for
next year I just don't really like the
idea of having goals I much prefer the
idea of just kind of enjoying the
process having systems that you know I
want to release a video a week rather
than I want to get to a million
subscribers by the end of 2020 because I
think like numerical goals like that are
and it's like they don't really sit very
well with me because I sort of feel that
it's kind of flies in the face of all
this stuff about gratitude and about
what we have being enough and kind of
explicitly defining goals in that sense
you know SMART goals specific measurable
achievable realistic timely blah blah
blah
it doesn't quite sit well with me but
you know I could be wrong maybe I'll
change my mind about goal-setting next
year who knows but yeah there's loads of
ways of doing an annual review this is
just the way I like to do mine and as I
said
linked my notion template in the video
description so if you want to do an
annual review like this then you can
just duplicate that template into your
own notion account by the way if you
don't yet have a notion account you can
sign up for a free one if you're a
student just use your AC or edu email
address and you'll get a personal
account completely free you can get a
free trial of notion that has a thousand
block limit and a block is like sort of
a piece of content or notion so you can
definitely try it out for free if you
really want to and actually I think you
should be able to do an annual review
with far less than a thousand blocks or
if you want to subscribe like I pay for
four dollars a month five dollars a
month for the premium subscription it's
good it's good like you know notion is
one of the apps that's actually change
that came for me and I use it to
organize most things in my life now so
easily worth the money that I pay for it
so yeah thank you for watching I hope
you enjoyed this video have you gained
some ideas about what you can do with an
annual review you know if you're doing
an annual review and you feel like
making it public so the rest of us can
see then leave a link to your notion
workspace in the comments down below and
I will definitely take a look and you
know we can share some ideas about what
makes a good annual review and also if
you have any ideas that I haven't put in
mine of things that like questions to
ask ourselves or things that might work
nicely in an annual review sort of
annual reflection thing then again leave
a comment down below and I'll you know
look and reply to all of them or at
least I'll try so yeah thank you for
watching if you like this video you
might like some of the other videos I've
done on notion links will be over there
thanks for watching and see you later
bye bye
[Music]