friends welcome back to the channel
happy new year all of that good stuff
if you new here my name is Ali I'm a
junior doctor working in Cambridge and
in this video I want to talk about 15
life lessons that I learned in 2019 all
of these are things that I've mentioned
in some capacity or other in my weekly
email newsletter so pretty much anytime
I come across any interesting life
lessons that I find useful I share them
in my email newsletter every Sunday so
you can sign up with a link down below
but yeah here is a roundup of 15 of my
favorite ones from 2019 let's go
firstly I learnt about the importance of
setting a daily highlight and I came
across this in a book called make time
by John Zaretsky and Jake Knapp and they
suggest that every day like the way to
be productive is to have a single daily
highlight that you're going to be
working on for that day so that's either
something that's gonna bring you the
most joy something that's the most
urgent or something that will bring you
the most kind of satisfaction when you
do it and I've started actively tracking
this in the app notion for the last few
months and I find that on the days where
I remember to set myself a daily
highlight I inevitably get more done
that day just because I then have this
default activity that I know I'm gonna
be doing so that was a really important
lesson that I learned secondly we have a
quote from Kurt Vonnegut who's a famous
writer and he says and I urge you to
please notice when you are happy and
exclaim or murmur or think at some point
if this isn't nice I don't know what is
and I first came across this kind of
towards the end of 2019 and kind of on
reflection I realized that I'm I'm very
quick at moving from one thing to
another thing to another thing and I
very rarely take the time to appreciate
and kind of like enjoy the moment and
since I came across this quote I've
really started to actively do that more
like you know let's say I'm driving in
the car and I've got like a latte in my
hand I'm listening to something on
audible or whatever then you know I just
occasionally have the thought that if
this isn't nice I don't know what is or
let's say I'm on my desk and making a
video filming something we'll try to
learn something or running a super
vision for my students you know I just
like to think if this isn't nice I don't
know what is and I just assist it's that
subtle encouragement for me to be more
grateful for the things in my life so
yeah thank you could want to go for that
quote thirdly I came across this idea of
window openers versus door knockers it's
not quite the terminology they used in
an episode of the my first million
podcast that I first heard this on but I
kind of synthesized what they were
talking about and turned it into window
openers and door knockers and the idea
is that in life there are two sorts of
people there are the window
and the door knockers the window openers
need to look through a window and when
they see their expected outcome on the
other side then they opened that window
and they walk through whereas the door
knockers are the sorts of people that
will knock on lots of doors and open
those doors and see what's on the other
side so like the key difference between
those is for the door knockers you don't
know what's what the outcome of your
action is going to be you have to knock
on the door and see where as for the
window openers you see the outcome on
the other side you just kind of work
through it to get it and the point that
they were making in this podcast that
really resonated with me was that in
most things in life these days a lot of
the success disproportionately comes
from from the door knocker attitude
rather than the window opener attitude
there are still some traditional careers
like medicine and stuff whereby you know
you have your path charted out in front
of you and any action predictably leads
to a certain outcome but in all the rest
of bits of life and you know a lot of
business a lot of creation or like you
know starting a YouTube channel you
don't know where the outcome is gonna be
you just knock on the door you apply
consistency and hard work and dedication
and all that good stuff and you then
gain the opportunity for serendipity
that you never would have known what's
possible like you know if he'd ask me
two and a half years ago what's the
point of starting a YouTube channel I
won't have been able to articulate I
would have been like oh you know I don't
know I'm just gonna do it consistently
and I hope someday it'll go well and now
it's completely changed my life
and I wouldn't have been able to do that
if I'd been a window opener if I just
been thinking oh you know let me just
focus on my medical career because
that's the thing that I can see in front
of me point number four is this idea by
Derek Siver's which is that what is
obvious to you might be amazing to
others now whenever we're in any sort of
like sharing of ideas kind of filled
content creation this sort of stuff
making videos of writing blog post
writing books recording podcasts and
stuff we have this thing like we all
have this thing that oh you know I'm not
gonna share this idea because it's just
kind of obvious surely everyone would
know about it
you know that this first lesson that I
shared about the daily highlight at this
point because I've I've incorporated
into my life it's pretty obvious to me
that you know if you want to be more
productive you should set yourself a
task to do each day and if you don't
then you know what's the point but that
idea when someone comes across it who
hasn't heard it before
it's pretty revolutionary and it's like
oh my god that's incredible equally for
some of you watching this video when I
talked about you know if this is a nice
what is he might have been thinking of
come on mate that's obvious everyone
knows that but when I first read it I
was like oh my god this is this idea has
actually changed to change the game for
me because in it it's now made me more
happier it's encouraged me to feel more
gratitude so the point that Derek
Siver's makes in this blog post again
link in the video description is that
don't worry that what's obvious to you
is going to be obvious to others because
it probably won't be and so as a lesson
to all of us we can and should share the
things that we've discovered the things
that we've learned the 15 life lessons
that we learned in 2019 because what's
obvious to us might not be obvious to
others it might even be amazing to
others point number five in 2019 I
really began to appreciate the the value
of lifelong learning so I recently
became a physiology supervisor and
Girton College Cambridge University
where I teach 10 medical students every
week about human physiology and that's
meant that I've actually had to learn
all this stuff all over again and kind
of explore it in more detail and that
should be really fun it's been one of
the most kind of joyful activities in my
life kind of sitting with with the books
and with the PDFs and papers and stuff
and trying to figure out what the best
way to teach this sort of topic is and
actually the UK government I found
commissioned this like study which was
an analysis of all of the benefits of
lifelong adult learning so you know
people who learn stuff actively in their
in their adult life and there are all
sorts of benefits so they've said adult
learning can indirectly improve
well-being and lead to positive outcomes
in health and socially positive
attitudes and behaviors amongst like
loads of other stuff so yeah I've really
began to appreciate the benefit of
lifelong learning and one other way that
I've been trying to do this lifelong
learning thing is by doing online
courses on brilliant org and brilliant
is an amazing learning platform targeted
and maths science and computer science
and they've got online classes from all
sorts of things within those categories
like probability number theory
algorithms data structures AI in neural
networks all this sort of stuff I've
personally enjoyed taking that computer
science courses now I actually
considered applying for computer science
rather than medicine but I've sort of
reasoned at the time when I was 16 that
it would kind of be cool to be a doctor
who knows how to code rather than to
just be a coder but that meant that all
of the coding that I've done has been
sort of very hodgepodge and I've never
quite taken the time to understand the
fundamentals of algorithms the
fundamentals of how computer science
work and that's what I've been doing on
brilliant which has been really helping
on that front they've also got this
really cool new like daily challenges
feature on brilliant whereby every day
there is a new day
challenged and that introduces some
concepts to you whether it's math
science or computer science and then it
gives you a problem in which you have to
kind of take that concept a little bit
further and try and apply your new
learning to it and then they give you
the solution and kind of explain it and
it's a a really good way of just general
generally exercising the mind and I find
that it's also a good model for me to
build my own teaching sessions around
because the idea of tutorials and
supervisions at universities like Oxford
and Cambridge is that you would give the
student a small amount of information
you'd kind of give them the basic
building block and then you would ask
them a question about it that kind of
tests that a little bit more and so it
kind of takes a little bit further and
then we'll see and then you see how far
they can go and then add some more
knowledge and it becomes this iterative
process whereby hopefully kind of learn
together and build on someone's
understanding rather than by just kind
of regurgitating something at them like
I'm currently taking in this video so
that's one of the great things about the
daily challenge is featuring brilliant
so if any of this sounds up your street
and you want to join this journey of
lifelong learning to improve your
physical mental social and economic
well-being then please do sign up for
free at brilliant org forward slash
alley and the first 200 people to use
that link will get 20% off an annual
premium subscription and it's totally
worth the price so thank you very much
brilliant for sponsoring this video
right so point number six is this idea
of a flywheel now I first came across
this in a Jim Collison interview on the
Tim Ferriss show I think in engineering
terms of flywheel is like a device that
stores mechanical rotational energy but
in terms of like business and creation
and YouTube and entrepreneurship and all
the stuff that I'm I'm interested in
outside of medicine the the idea of a
flywheel is that it's it's something
that takes ages to get going but when it
gets going then it kind of builds on
itself and it's unstoppable and people
often use the flywheel analogy to
describe how Amazon works so for exact
like they get really low prices and that
leads to people wanting to buy stuff
from Amazon which leads to sellers
wanting to go on Amazon which means that
Amazon then has this supply and demand
thing which means they can drive prices
lower and over all this like one thing
leads to another leads to another leads
to another on this flywheel that you
know it takes a lot of effort to get
going amazon's been going for years now
but then it becomes completely
unstoppable because each thing kind of
builds on itself and the way that I've
applied this flywheel concept to my life
and I've started thinking about it is in
terms of things like YouTube and podcast
and
making a blog in that I got to start
when you're starting a YouTube channel
like you know you get basically no one
viewing your videos and you might get
one extra subscriber a day and you feel
like super proud oh my god I've gone
from 47 to 48 subscribers in two days
that's incredible and no one's watching
your videos but the more you can kind of
produce hopefully valuable content
consistently over a long period of time
the more the flywheel gathers momentum
and the weird thing about YouTube and
cool thing about YouTube is that the
algorithm is very flywheel II in that
the more videos a youtuber creates the
more opportunities there are for other
people to discover their content the
more they're likely to subscribe the
more watch time they're gonna give the
more the algorithm benefits you and
starts recommending your stuff in
suggested videos and it kind of drives
this wheel that keeps them going and
going and going but the point is that it
takes so much effort to get started
initially and any time I'm sort of in
that murder where I'm thinking oh this
is too much effort I think no it's a
flywheel if I'm starting something new
then I know it's gonna take that effort
to get started to begin with point
number seven is I discovered this idea
of mastering boring fundamentals and I
got this from a blog post by a guy
called James Stuber which was entitled
master boring fundamentals boring is fun
I just want to read a few things from it
so firstly he says for any endeavor
there are a set of basic skills needed
to build a strong foundation these are
the boring fundamentals sleeping 8 hours
a night exercise it consistently eating
your vegetables meditating reading books
writing for yourself in free appears and
then there are domain-specific
fundamentals like drilling guitar chords
or calculus if you're into maths he says
that even when we know they're good for
us even when we know that they'll
advance our goals we avoid taking the
steps needed we don't do the boring
fundamentals because well boring
repetitive actions done day after day
are not a recipe for excitement there's
a disconnect between the future positive
result and the presents log progress
often plateaus and only arrives in
unpredictable bursts and this sort of
goes back to this idea of a flywheel in
that we have to do these boring
fundamentals and he's kind of making a
broader point about life you know
sleeping at hours a day exercising
eating vegetables I don't even do these
boring fundamentals I don't sleep eight
hours a day even though I want to I
don't really eat vegetables because you
know I'm terrible at cooking and my diet
is awful and I don't really exercise
consistently because I always feel like
there's something better I could be
doing and the reason for that is because
it's boring it's a fundamental and the
rewards don't come immediately whereas
if I think oh I could go home and film a
video that
in a video and that's like immediate
gratification or as if I think or do I
want to go to the gym for two hours or
do I want to actively go to the shops
and cook some vegetables to just improve
my life in general
that that's got less of a an obvious an
obvious benefit and so reading this kind
of stuff reminds me that I need to
master the boring fundamentals and this
is you know something that I've tried to
actively think about more that sort of
sort of encouraged me to go to the gym a
bit more and to eat a little bit more
healthily and to really take care of my
sleep point number a is another idea
that I found from James tubers blog and
that's the idea of type one versus type
two fun you know when we think of fun we
often think that there's just the the
head anism though that the pure
unadulterated joy type of fun that all
playing video games is fun or playing
sports is fun but for something like you
know running a marathon or climbing a
mountain or doing cross-country skiing
we probably wouldn't consider that fun
because it's not the same sort of fun
but in his blog post he talks about this
kind of long long distance skier called
Tim Peck who defines a type 2 fun which
is where it's suffering in the present
but then it is sort of fun in hindsight
and that's a different sort of fun and
that is sort of this sort of fun that
that I notice that being a doctor when
it's really really busy is like like it
feels very grueling when you were there
but then at the end of the day you look
back and you think oh you know that was
actually a really good day it's
definitely not pure hedonism when you
were trying to kind of trick someone and
those emergencies going on and you're
struggling to keep up with the workload
but it is definitely fun and it's a type
two kind of fun and so just
understanding it like recognizing this
distinction between type 1 and type 2
fun it's been really helpful for me
because now I have the vocabulary in my
head to think about the sort of fun that
is you know takes some suffering like I
now appreciate why some people say that
running is fun because previously I used
to think how on earth can running be fun
because it's not as fun as playing
squash but actually is just a different
sort of fun so yeah point number nine is
something I came across on the Tim
Ferriss show he interviewed a guy called
Safi buckle I think can't remember its
credentials I think he broke but oh
maybe he wrote a book called loom maybe
that's it well link it over there if
that's a case and down below this guy
Safi is a writer and he talks about how
there are a few different modes of
writing and the first one is FBR which
stands for fast bad rock and he says
that when you're doing your first draft
just think to yourself this is gonna be
fast it's gonna be bad and it's gonna be
wrong just having that mindset
encouraged
a lot more to actually just put stuff
down on paper and so for me every time
I'm writing my weekly email newsletter I
initially have that kind of writer's
block where I'm like ah I don't know
what to write because I don't know if
this is gonna be good but then you know
for the last few months since I first
came across this I've been actively you
know writing down FBR on top of the page
just to remind myself okay this this is
just a first draft it's gonna be fast
it's gonna be bad it's going to be wrong
and that means that I can just kind of
write without worrying without judging
myself without without worrying about
the quality inevitably at the end of it
I've written something and then I come
back to editing it and I think oh
actually this is this is kind of
reasonable or if it's not then I edit it
but it's a lot easier to edit once
you've got a fast bad wrong thing then
that thing that we as writers or as
creators always try and do and try and
get it right on the first draft so just
appreciating this and having this kind
of vocabulary to define fast bad wrong
has been really helpful for me in my
writing career and again you know plug
to my weekly email newsletter you can
sign up with a link down below port
number 10 is something that I came up
with just completely made-up one day for
my weekly email newsletter but I've
started as I've started to apply it a
lot more and that is the write-off
principle for productivity for me I kind
of struggle with it's it's not a bad
struggle to have but I kind of struggle
with the art with switching off like
want to get home from work let's head to
9 p.m. I would think ah you know I
should I've got two hours before bed I
should probably film a video even if I'm
really not feeling up to it even if I'm
feeling really tired and I know I'm not
gonna do great work I just think you
know why I should film a video and
that's fine like you know consistency is
important and all that stuff but there
are a lot of days whereby I kind of
procrastinate from filming the video
like at 9:00 p.m. after work and I just
kind of lie on my sofa just scrolling
through Instagram and I don't do
anything like I wouldn't get out of book
and read it or recently I wouldn't stop
playing on my Nintendo switch because I
would be feeling guilty about not making
the YouTube video and not doing the work
and so the idea behind the write-off
principle is that sometimes it's okay to
just write the whole day off and once
you've written the whole day off you've
decided that you know what I'm gonna
give myself a break today which means
that at least to me I find this helpful
because then I don't have to feel guilty
about not doing anything and there was
like there was a day a few weeks ago
where I was doing this I was sort of
sitting on the sofa behind there and my
housemate Molly was sitting next to me
and I was just like Oh Molly I need to
film a video but I can't be asked and
she was like hey haven't you written
something about the right of principal
why don't you just make it a write off
day and I was like oh my god Molly
you're right there's gonna be a right of
day and then
just like brought so much joy to my life
that I didn't have to film a video that
evening that I just kind of dropped my
phone got at mine my Nintendo switch and
played with The Witcher 3 for like 2
hours but it was two glorious hours and
I wouldn't have had that enjoy had i not
kind of written the day off so yeah the
write-off principle you can read more
about it I'll put a link to my email
newsletter where I talked about it first
but yeah that's point number 10 what
number 11 god this videos getting really
long if you're still here I apologize
for being so rambling or trans beat up
point number 11 is the mundane OT of
accidents and this comes from a paper
that I've read which is from like the
1970s or 80s of you know like old
old-school like boomer level territory
where the author talks about what
defines excellence and he studies the
field of swimmers so he looks at
competitive swimmers in like local club
national and Olympic levels and tries to
figure out what's the difference between
them and he realizes that the difference
between them it's not a quantitative
difference it's not it's not really that
Michael Phelps practices that much more
than someone who's a club or county
level player it's that the people who
are at the really pro end of the
excellence packet spectrum they do
things qualitatively differently and the
point he makes is that it's all just
very mundane like they actively put a
bit of effort into figuring out the
technique they wake up on time every day
and do a they look after their diet
there's nothing really sexy about the
way that these people get really good at
stuff it's just that they didn't do the
mundane repeatedly and just kind of do
it consistently I kind of reading this
like it's a really long paper but I read
the whole things it was a riveting read
made me realize that we're always on the
lookout for some kind of shortcut you
know I fall into this myself I'm guilty
of this you know spreading the good news
about the latest productivity app but
like really the latest productivity app
probably isn't going to make much
difference to your life
what will make a difference to your life
is just doing the boring fundamentals
repeatedly and the point that this guy
makes in this paper is that excellence
is ultimately a mundane phenomenon like
there's nothing sexy or exciting about
it it's all just very mundane like it's
all just you know doing the right things
consistently and trying to get a little
bit better each time but I thought it
was very interesting read and a good
lesson that I took away from it point
number 12 is the go first
and I first came across that I don't
know where I came across this several
years ago but I've sort of ingrained it
into my my life but it really stood out
to me when I was in Sudan this time last
year when you go to a new place like you
probably know there's always that kind
of little bit of sort of meeting new
people and needing to break the ice and
what I read in this book that I already
can't remember where it's from is that
everyone is friendly but you have to be
willing to go first because if you go
first if you take the initiative to say
hello and you know introduce yourself
and stop strike up a conversation you
will find that people are just generally
nice and everyone's really friendly and
so in Sudan you know for a few minutes I
was like oh everyone's kind of shy
everyone's kind of quiet I don't really
know what to do but then I started
actively going up to people and kind of
saying alone just kind of generally
having a chat this going first that I
did on my part if I can say so like I
certainly appreciated how for a friend
everyone was and people like so happy to
talk to me and it was just like really
nice a really really good experience and
I think my experience in Sudan would
have been a lot less fun had I not gone
first
with those sorts of things and I think
this just applies generally across the
board as well like you know when I'm at
work I try and go first in introducing
myself to new colleagues in kind of
initiating banter a bit when I can and
inviting people to things just having
like being able to take that fear of
embarrassment and internalize it within
ourselves and forget about it and just
go first means that we see just how
amazing humanity is this sounds really
corny how amazing humanity is how
friendly people are and how willing
people are to connect as long as we go
first point number 13 high leverage
housekeeping this is an idea that my
brother came up with and which is that
every Saturday what he does is that
instead of doing active work on his his
thing he does where he calls
high-leverage housekeeping which is that
kind of sorting out the email INBOX
sorting out the to-do list you know
cleaning the desk sorting out like you
know the project management software I
think he uses notion to manage a track
his own startup and figuring out what
needs to be done we're spending a few
hours on a Saturday to just get get your
life in order
sort of like what Amazon used to do in
like that apparently there was one year
just before they had a billion in
revenue where the the mantra for the
whole year was go high o geo HIO
getting our house in order and the point
of the whole year was to kind of focus
on the systems and make everything work
really well not try and create new
things and so while I try and do now is
that every now and then I try do this
weekly but I ends up not being
I think about you know having a whole
day dedicated to high-leverage
housekeeping where I can do things like
like make decisions about where or like
what I want to be doing for the next
weeks or the next month or sort of
actively planning new video ideas
whereas otherwise I'm just in kind of
technician mode I'm just kind of doing
the thing I never really take the time
to step back and figure out where I can
apply and average where I can do some
housekeeping to make things scale better
grow better be more fun that sort of
stuff so high-leverage housekeeping
again link to all of these in my email
newsletter if you want to have a read in
more detail point number 14 is this idea
of having an inbox for your brain and
this is from David Allen's book getting
things done the art of stress-free
productivity which is just kind of like
the Bible for productivity about how to
get stuff done but the main thing I take
away from this is that it's really
important to have an inbox for your
brain basically a place where you can
capture ideas and things like as soon as
they hit your brain so that you can then
offload them from your brain into this
inbox so these days I use the app drafts
for that so anytime I have an idea for a
video or a quote or literally anything
I'm thinking of either on my Apple watch
or on my phone or on my Mac I will open
up the drafts app and just write write a
quick note for that and that means that
when I'm doing my high-leverage
housekeeping in my weekly reviews or
whatever then I can convert the draft
items either into notion projects or
into duyst items if they need to be done
urgently or I can just kind of file them
away in my archives and it's nice having
this in books of my brain because it
means that my brain is then for having
ideas not for storing them and that's
the idea that David Allen talks about in
his book getting things done again link
in the video description and finally
point number 15 is the power of project
lists so again I always only really
started doing this after reading getting
things done like for the third time and
the idea is that you should have a list
of all of the projects that you are
currently working on and that you want
to be working on so like after reading
this in in the app notion I made like a
project list of all the videos that I'm
all the video ideas that I might have
and all the videos that I was currently
working on and just the fact that I had
all of that stuff written down meant
that my brain was doing this like
background processing of these various
projects as I was going about my day and
just like not even realizing it or even
maybe when I was asleep so like
sometimes I genuinely like wake up in
the morning and I'd be like oh that idea
for a video that I had ages ago that I
wrote down in this project list I've
just thought about something to make
that happen
or if I'm driving to work in the car and
listening to an audiobook or listening
to a podcast occasionally I just have an
idea that reference is some of the pros
some of the projects that I've got on my
list and I didn't really have that
before I started writing the sort of
stuff down and so I'm a real big
believer of having a list of projects
that we're working on and that's not
even in the video front is just kind of
in life in general and the way that
David Allen defines that is as is that a
project is anything that has more than
one step required to do it so now I've
got like a whole list of projects that
I'm working on and I find that that's
really helpful and that's been the final
lesson that I learned in 2019
so that was a roundup of all the things
that I learned in 2019 and in fact it
wasn't all of them it was like 15 pretty
much all of them I write in my weekly
newsletter so for all 52 of them check
out emailed audible.com linked in the
video description you can have a look at
my weekly email newsletter you can
subscribe if you like but that is where
I share all of the things in real time
as I discovered them but I thought I'd
do this annual roundup just cause a few
weeks ago I was making my annual review
video and I thought oh you know this is
a list of 15 things that I've liked life
lessons I've learned this year why don't
I just make it into video so that was
kind of where the idea came from yeah
thanks for watching if you like this
video I'll put another links to hear of
another playlist that has similar sort
of life lessons life advice he sort of
stuff if you like this whole lifelong
learning thing like I do then please do
some - brilliant - org forward slash
oddly that also really helps support the
channel so if you like this video
consider signing up for a free trial of
that thanks for watching and I'll see
you in the next video bye bye
[Music]