every day we make choices that have the
potential to change the course of Our
Lives whether it's choosing what
subjects to study in school or starting
a YouTube channel or asking that girl
out on a date the choices we make each
day can massively affect our happiness
and how our lives play out but we almost
never stop and think about how to
actually get better at making these
choices so firstly what does it mean to
make better choices in life like there's
no objective criteria of what is a good
decision broadly and so I wanted to find
better as essentially more intentional
or more conscious or more in line with
my core values and so the way I see it
is that the key to making Better Life
Choices is to find different ways to
look within and figure out how can we
tease out what we actually want from a
given situation over the last few years
of making various Life Choices I found a
series of questions that I found really
helpful to ask myself so that whenever
I'm struggling with a life choice or
struggling with a difficult decision I
run myself through some of these
questions and generally I get at an
interesting answer and that helps me
nudge my decision towards something
that's a bit more intentional and a
little bit conscious so question number
10 is in one year's time what would I
regret not having started today there's
that classic quote that you know the
best time to plant a tree was 20 years
ago the second best time is now and I
think that often some of the most
difficult choices in life are the
decision to start something new for
example should I start working out I
could just always do it later but in one
year's time well I regret not having
started it today and this was actually
the core decision that made me start my
YouTube channel five years ago when I
started it a bit of a backstory
initially before starting this YouTube
channel I was actually thinking it was
going to start it a whole year later I
was imagining I was in med school at the
time and I was imagining I should start
a YouTube channel once I become a doctor
because then I can Vlog Life as a doctor
but then I asked myself hang on in a
year's time when I'm a doctor will I
regret not having started this earlier
and the answer was hell yes and I
realized that I should start the YouTube
channel right now this was 2017 when I
was still in med school because in one
year's time I would have just gotten
better at making videos your first 50
videos are going to be terrible so I'm
kind of hoping that over the next year
I'll make my 50 terrible
and then when we hit August the 1st 2018
when life as a junior doctor starts and
then I'd be able to kind of hit the
ground running and be able to actually
film decent Vlogs and so I wasn't really
expecting any growth or any kind of like
traction or anything on the channel it
was literally just I'm gonna be glad
I've had a year of practice before I
actually do this properly and so if
you're struggling with any kind of
decision right now that involves
starting something new or maybe even
quitting something ask yourself will you
a year from now wish that you had
started a year ago all right coming in
at Point number nine it's what would my
mental Board of advisors say now this is
a really good strategy essentially the
idea is that you want to formulate a
mental Board of advisors what this is is
a handful of people that can be living
or dead whose work or who's thinking you
admire and appreciate and you have them
as your mental Board of advisors in my
mental Board of advisors I have a
handful of people I have Derek sivers
and Tim Ferriss and Ryan holiday and Cal
Newport they don't even know they're in
my mental Board of advisors but I'm
familiar with all four of their work
enough and I appreciate their philosophy
and the way they think about life so
that if I'm ever struggling with a
decision I'll just run that through my
okay what would Cal say what would Derek
say and that results in interesting
things I'm not saying your mental Board
of advisors has to be these for white
American dudes it can be whoever you
want it to be but usually it's like it's
like this thing like it's really hard to
kind of take advice for ourselves but
it's very easy for us to give advice to
other people and so zooming out a little
bit and thinking what would these like
fictional or real or whatever characters
in my mind say in response to the
situation actually helps you figure out
what you personally want to do in
response to that situation for example
one dilemma I was struggling with a few
months ago was trying to figure out to
what extent I actually want to grow this
business like you know we're gonna do a
couple million dollars in profit this
year do we want to do more than that
next year or like way more than that
like what's what's the point is it worth
putting in loads of extra work to make
loads of extra money and so I ran it
through the mental Board of advisors and
basically all four of them the answer
was nope optimize for lifestyle optimize
for the things that you're interested in
and energized by don't worry about
making more money because making more
money does not actually correlate to
more happiness Beyond a certain point so
that was useful that was useful like
clearly the fact that that was the
conclusion that I reached from my MBA my
mental Board of advisors meant that I
knew deep down that that was the right
decision but just that framing allowed
me to get there a little bit quicker all
right in at question number eight we
have the question what is the risk of
doing nothing now again this comes into
play when we're making choices in life
about generally like trying something
new or taking a bit of a risk it might
be quitting your job or it might be
asking that girl out or it might be
starting a new venture or a new business
or whatever and in action are you doing
nothing often feels like the safe path
but actually it's worth asking ourselves
like what are the risks of doing nothing
like what what is actually going to
happen usually inaction does not
actually have zero consequences doing
nothing is also a decision just like
doing something is a decision by the way
if you're enjoying this video so far I
would love it if you could hit the like
button for the YouTube algorithm I was
at this uh YouTube conference a few
weeks ago and apparently the like button
still actually makes a difference so if
you can hit the like button that'll be
lovely all right and at number seven we
have the question of what core value am
I optimizing for now this involves the
whole thing of actually figuring out
what are your own personal values what
what do you personally value and
generally one of the ways you can figure
this out is think about a difficult
decision you've had to make in the past
where the choice wasn't entirely clear
and think about okay the choice that I
made in that context assuming I'm happy
with that choice like if I had to pick
like the thing that I valued above all
else to make that choice what would that
thing be okay coming in at number seven
we have the deathbed question which is
that when I'm on my deathbed what will I
regret having done or not having done
now this is obviously really helpful
because it generally nudges us towards
doing the thing that feels a little bit
more interesting generally the sorts of
things that people regret are the things
that they didn't do rather than the
things that they did do and so if you've
got a choice for example to take a gap
Year from University and travel around
the world for a year that's probably
something you're not going to regret
having done but you'll probably regret
not having done it if that makes sense
interestingly there's a book about the
top five regrets of the dying here is
what they are number one I wish I'd had
the courage to live a life true to
myself not the life others expected of
me number two I wish I hadn't worked so
hard brackets on stuff I didn't care
about number three I wish I'd had the
courage to express my feelings number
four I wish I'd stayed in touch with my
friends and number five I wish I'd let
myself be happier this is interesting I
often think about this list at one point
I even had this list of like things that
literally the top of my kind of daily
notes page when I was doing journaling I
gotta stopped doing that but it was it
was a really helpful reminder and
honestly I find that this list really
helps guide my own decision making
because again if for example I'm doing a
thing where it's like I could work
really extra hard to do this thing and
then I look at the regrets of the dying
where it's like I wish I hadn't worked
so hard I wish I'd stay in touch with
friends then I think you know what will
I actually regret not having done this
work related thing probably not but
instead could I use that time to maybe
reach out to a friend that I haven't
spoken to in a while and so hopefully
you know a little bit trying to make
better choices in life trying to
mitigate against the risk that I might
regret these things when I'm on my
deathbed but generally the deathbed test
is also a good way to say are you just
scared or are you doing something that
you actually are unlikely to regret and
you'll be glad that you did further down
the line all right in at number six we
have the question of how certain am I
about this decision and how certain do I
need to be to make this decision a lot
of us like even when it comes to these
sorts of questions we can end up over
analyzing everything and overthinking
things for example the decision to start
a YouTube channel or not a lot of people
get hung up on Wow will I will I be able
to make a full-time living from this I
was like the answer is who knows there's
no there's no certainty in life but how
certain do you need to be to try it out
probably not that certain maybe you have
30 certainty that or 30 likelihood that
maybe you'd be able to make something of
this provided you put in the work is it
worth trying with 30 kind of certainty I
would say it probably because it also
gives you skills along the way and it's
fun and also helps you meet people along
the way so you don't need to have 100
certainty because if you wait for 100
certainty you're just going to end up
wasting your life away broadly not
making any decisions because you're
never going to have 100 certainty the
timing is never going to be quite right
all right question number five is how
might I treat this like an experiment
there's another great thing like
generally you'll find a lot of these
questions like at least the way that I
think about decisions is that they nudge
me towards doing the thing that is a
little bit scarier a little bit riskier
because we as humans and I think me
definitely we have a bias towards risk
aversion we have a bias towards trying
to avoid a sense of loss and so the
question of like how can I treat this as
an experiment I find really nice because
when something is an experiment you're
not trying for it to be successful
you're not putting so much pressure on
it it's just an experiment the decision
to launch that business is just an
experiment if you're having to sync 300
000 into into starting that business
it's not an experiment anymore it's like
a big deal but is there some things more
you can do to run the test to treat it a
little bit more like an experiment could
you maybe run a school card or run an
event or try doing it for free or do a
minimum viable product could you do
something a little bit experimental to
test the idea and see whether it even is
the right decision to make for example
last year I was still thinking that I
wanted to work in medicine part-time and
there was a part of me that was thinking
you know what I'm just gonna to apply
for a medical training specialty but
I'll then have a chat with them once I
get in once I've done the interviews and
exams and stuff and I'll be like hey I
want to go part-time two days a week but
I thought no hang on hang on this is a
very big decision like to apply for a
whole like residency like specialty
pathway and then like all the work
that's gone into it could I treat this
as an experiment how could I treat this
like an experiment and so I ran this
hypothesis I said I reckon I'm going to
enjoy life where I work one or two days
a week as a doctor and spend the rest of
the time doing my YouTube and internet
and businessy type stuff how do I run
that as an experiment well I just picked
up a few extra ships in the emergency
department and tried to recreate that
life for myself where I was working one
day a week as a doctor and I realized oh
within a few weeks I actually don't
really enjoy this I'd rather work zero
days a week as a doctor rather than one
or two days a week as a doctor and I'm
glad I figured that out because I just
ran the experiment in a fairly easy
fashion rather than applying for a whole
program and kind of hoping that at the
point where I'd gotten into the program
then I was going to go part-time and
then I was going to enjoy it and so it's
kind of the same with a lot of decisions
people make around subjects to study at
University day or careers to go into or
jobs to apply for like there are often
ways of running smaller experiments to
reduce the uncertainty in your
calculation bearing in mind the previous
point that you can never fully reduce
the uncertainty to zero percent all
right question number four is do I want
to be the sort of person who does X now
this speaks to an idea that's common
throughout the research around like
habit formation and goal setting which
is broadly that if you have a particular
identity that you're trying to go for
like having identity based goals and
habits and decisions generally leads to
leads you to better outcomes than having
like specific task baits based habits or
goals or decisions and so if it comes to
let's say a trivial decision of how
often do I want to work out it's like do
I want to be the sort of person that
does exercise every day actually yeah I
do I would like to be that sort of
person and so that's a decision about
identity it's a decision about what sort
of person I want to be which nudges me
more towards kind of doing some exercise
every day do I want to be the sort of
person that makes healthy choices about
what they eat yeah I do because that's
important to me and I've realized that's
important to me because I've asked
myself that particular question and so
it becomes less about you know right now
do I want to go for that McDonald's
drive-through even though I often do and
more about like in general who is the
sort of person I want to be and that
generally I find at least help to nudge
me towards a more kind of intentional
and conscious way of making Life Choices
oh and by the way I'd love to hear from
you if you have any kind of Frameworks
for decision making or making better
choices in life or questions or
journaling prompts that you ask yourself
I'd love for you to leave a comment down
below I read all the comments I can't
respond to all of them I often heart
them when I'm on the toilet but like I
would love to see if there's any other
questions that I can start applying to
my life and it would just be generally
nice for us to see kind of what other
people are coming up with in terms of
making better decisions in life alright
and at number three we have the question
of will this energize me or will this
drain me I think this is great this is
one of one of the core more kind of
questions that I use to decide whether
or not to say yes to an event or
something that I get invited to I ask
myself if this was happening like right
now would it energize me or would it
drain me things that energize me are
broadly doing work related stuff and
hanging out with the team and having
dinner with friends things that drain me
are normally having meetings about stuff
that I'm not particularly interested in
or even doing like work related stuff
where it's not particularly interesting
or energizing to me but I'm doing it for
the money that generally is going to be
like a draining situation and actually
these days a lot of the decisions that
we make as a business around like what
direction we're going to go is by
running the choice through the filter of
will this energize or drain me I'm in a
very privileged position because I run
the business and so I can actually just
do the things that energize me we were
thinking at one point of running like a
service for businesses where we would go
into these like big companies and help
them out with their YouTube channels and
stuff and then I asked myself would this
energize me or would it drain me it
would make a lot of money because people
kept saying to us hey these big
corporations have so much money you
could make you can make millions by
doing this I was like so that's pretty
draining I don't really like the idea of
going to a big Corporation and being
like hey guys I'm going to teach you how
to do YouTube I much prefer the idea of
like reading cool stuff learning cool
stuff and making videos about it for the
audience on the internet then I do going
to like I don't know KPM GHQ and
teaching them how to do video all right
in at number two we have a quitting
framework that Stephen Bartlett's book
happy sexy millionaire which is actually
a really good read talks about and so
the framework is basically this like
firstly you ask yourself the question of
why am I thinking about quitting and
generally the two options there is it
sucks or it's hard if the thing is hard
you ask yourself is the challenge worth
the potential reward and if the answer
is yes then you keep going but if the
answer is no then you quit if the thing
sucks then you ask yourself do I believe
I could make it not suck if the answer
to that is no or I've tried my best and
I haven't been able to make this thing
not suck then wait you can quit but if
the answer is yes then you ask yourself
the final question which is is it worth
the effort to try and make it not suck
and if the answer is yes then don't quit
but if the answer is no then you can
quit honestly this is pretty good like I
came across this when I read his book
like last year and I found that this was
how I defaulted to making decisions
about things to quit but now that I've
got this framework I literally just run
stuff through the things like do I want
to do
probably not and this usually leads to
me quitting things that I actually
realized that I fundamentally don't want
to do which again this you know speaking
to this idea of making Better Life
Choices a better life choice is the one
that feels more intentional and more
conscious based on what we actually want
and then the final question that I find
really helpful to reflect on is Tim
ferriss's Fear setting exercise where
kind of question it's it's a series of
questions but question one is
essentially what am I not doing because
I'm scared and then there's a few
follow-ups to that so what am I missing
out on by not doing the thing that I'm
scared of number two why am I not doing
this thing it's like what are the other
reasons why it could be not doing the
thing number three what's the absolute
worst case scenario if I did the thing
number four what can I do to mitigate
against the risk of that worst case
scenario happening or to deal with the
worst case scenario when it does happen
and number five if I had to reverse this
decision how would I go about it and I
find that generally if I'm struggling
with something or struggling with a
decision generally when it comes to work
or even my personal life running it
through this filter of what am I scared
of what's the worst case scenario and
how do I mitigate against risk of that
generally makes me realize that I have
overblown the fears of all of this stuff
in my mind and I see this a lot with
students in my part-time YouTuber
Academy where people are scared to put
themselves out there on camera because
they're like scared of what their
friends and family and colleagues and
co-workers and bosses kind of think and
then if you ask them they're like hey
what's what's the actual worst case
scenario how do you mitigate against
this if the worst case scenario happened
would you would you be able to survive
what do you think is the actual
probability of the worst case scenario
just like laying the things out helps
people realize that oh I was actually
scared and I was like because fear is
like a powerful emotion it's easy to
kind of overblow fears of particular
things in our own minds now earlier on
the video we talked about the question
of what's something that I would regret
not having started today and actually
one of my answers to that question was
Heights who are very kindly sponsoring
this video if you haven't heard by now
Heights is a brain care smart supplement
I've literally been taking it since
November 2021 and it's two capsules that
I take every single day that have over
20 different micronutrients vitamins
minerals blueberry extract omega-3 like
these micronutrients that have a strong
evidence base why they're useful for the
brain now obviously in an Ideal World we
would all be getting all the nutrients
that we need from our diet but looking
at the stats especially here in the UK
99 of people are not on the gold
standard Mediterranean diet and so we're
all deficient in various different
things and so the thing I like about
Heights is that it's just two capsules
every morning I take it with water just
after brushing my teeth and it means
that I've got my bases covered in terms
of micronutrients if for whatever reason
I didn't manage to eat perfectly healthy
that day which is unfortunately most
days if you want to check it out it's
super easy to sign up you just go to
yourheits.com which is also linked in
the video description and you just put
in your address and you can sign up to a
monthly or quarterly subscription I have
the quarterly subscription because it's
cheaper and there's fewer deliveries and
just every three months it'll just send
you like three boxes and you just get
through one box a month and it's great
100 would recommend it and if you use
the coupon code Ali 15 and check out
then that will give you an extra 15 off
the already discounted price of the
quarterly subscription so thank you so
much Heights for sponsoring this video
and helping me improve my own brain care
which ultimately allows me to make
better choices in life and thank you so
much for watching if you enjoyed this
video you might like to check out this
video over here which is a book summary
that I've done about Atomic habits which
is a fantastic book by James Clear which
is all about building better habits and
breaking bad ones which kind of relates
to this stuff around making better
decisions in life because to be honest a
lot of our life choices are associated
with the habits that we have so you can
check out my video about Atomic habits
right here thank you so much for
watching and I'll see you in the next
video bye