okay so here's the problem that i've
recently solved with these five magical
apps like you i read a lot of books i
browse a lot of articles on the internet
i listen to a hell of a lot of podcasts
and i'm always scrolling through twitter
when i'm on the toilet and across these
dozens of hours of content consumption
every day i will occasionally come
across
highlights or interesting bits that
resonate with me or things that are
surprising or things like insights that
i want to capture for later but until
very recently i didn't have a way of
logging these insights and so i would
spend all of this time over the last
like 10 years plus of my life
listening and reading and browsing and
watching all of this stuff and only
really taking away a fraction of it and
remembering even less of it and applying
even less of it to my life which kind of
begs the question that why was i wasting
all this time consuming all this stuff
if i wasn't going to then you know do
something with it further down the line
but now we've got these five apps that
work together seamlessly to form what i
like to call the magical insight logging
framework and automatic method for
capturing and logging all of the
insights that we get from books articles
podcasts and even tweets all right so
let's start with the first three apps
that make up the consumption layer which
is the first part of the magical insight
logging framework the first on this list
and the least interesting is kindle so
if you're reading books on kindle which
i've been doing since like 2008 when the
kindle first came out i think as you're
reading stuff you can highlight stuff
which is pretty fantastic this works
really nicely on a desktop or laptop as
well you can just select a passage you
can highlight it you can highlight in
different colors
and you can do that on the ios and the
ipad and android basically on the kindle
app across any of your devices you can
highlight passages the second app in a
five part stack is a read it later app
like insta paper or pocket and instant
paper is the one that i use and the idea
is that any time i come across an
article or a blog post on the internet
that i want to read but i don't want to
read it there and then then i will share
it to insta paper and there's all sorts
of ways of sharing it you can use the
ios share extension you can email it to
instapaper you can use the chrome or
safari extension there are hundreds of
ways of getting stuff into instapaper
and actually this is one of my biggest
productivity hacks in general it's that
i will always come across interesting
emails with interesting articles but
i'll almost never read them there and
then i will always save them to
instapaper so that then when i'm next in
the mood to read stuff i open up the
instapaper app on my iphone or ipad or
on the web and they've got apps for
android and stuff as well i open it up
and i've just got this long list of
articles that i've saved that i can then
start reading through one by one for
however long i like and the really cool
thing about instapaper and pocket is
that while you're reading these articles
on whatever device you want you can
highlight them and that is how we are
going to be inputting our insights in
our insight logging framework so here's
an article from common cog let's say
don't forget about the world outside the
book let's say i you know for some
reason that passage like really
resonates with me and i think oh this is
an incredible insight i want to
highlight this i can just highlight it
and hit the highlight button and it will
be highlighted or even if i want i can
highlight something and i can add a note
to it this is a test note that i'm
adding to this highlight
so i can take notes on the highlights
that i'm reading as i'm going through
them and app number three is a magical
app that is unfortunately only available
for ios they're working on an android
version and this is now how i consume
all the podcasts that i listen to and
this is a truly magical app called air
dot io highlight and share the best
moments from podcasts so let me show you
what this looks like so air is now my
podcast app of choice on ios and i can
go on air and i can go through all of
the podcasts that i want to listen to um
so it's a pretty standard podcast player
so far but the truly magical thing about
aaron white's now my favorite podcast
app is while you're listening to a
podcast you can hit this big quote
button in the middle and that lets you
take an air quote which is a fantastic
name and essentially what that does is
while you're listening to a podcast if
you hear something that's particularly
insightful or that resonates with you
you hit the air quote button and it will
automatically create an air quote from
the last 30 seconds to 60 seconds of the
stuff that you've listened to and you
can change that amount of time if you
want so while i'm listening to this
episode of the portal with eric
weinstein and ryan holliday we still
want to play the same games they won't
let us tell our stories i mean like
i've come across something that
resonates with me and i'm going to hit
you know the whole meet the air quote
button and what that's going to do is
it's going to automatically turn it into
an air quote and then it gives me the
option of titling it something so ryan
holiday comment about meaning in life or
something like that and now it saved it
as an air quote and what's really cool
is that air automatically generates
transcripts for a lot of the most
popular podcasts and so when you create
an air quote if the transcription is
available it will basically just create
a highlight for you and this is
completely game changing because before
this app it was not possible to take
notes from podcasts and so with this
episode while i was listening to it over
the weekend i took one two three four
five six seven seven air quotes from it
because those were the bits that
particularly resonated with me so we've
got those three apps that make up the
consumption layer of the magical insight
logging framework let's now talk about
the integration layer and this is a very
special app that i've been loving for
the last like two years since i first
discovered it and that is called read
wise and you can find that at
readwise.io and there is a special link
in the video description if you use my
code you will get an extended free trial
for 60 days rather than 30 days if you
want to try it out and so what read wise
is is amongst other things it is the
integration layer for my system so what
it's doing it's bringing together all of
the highlights that i've created from
the three consumption apps and so if i
sign into my read-wise what we'll see is
that it brings together books articles
tweets and podcasts so when it comes to
books it automatically connects to my
amazon account because i've given it
permissions and so i've got these 107
books that i've been highlighting on
kindle for the last several years and
what it's doing is that it's just
bringing together all of my highlights
from these books all into one place but
it's not just books it's also
automatically connecting to instapaper
and so any article that i've highlighted
and we can see i've got highlights all
the way back from 2019 when i first
started using instapaper when i
discovered this
it basically takes all of the highlights
and puts them all in one place so this
is an article i've read in buffer and
these were seven of the passages that i
highlighted from that that particularly
resonated with me recently as well
they've added tweet and podcast
functionality so for tweets for example
if i come across a tweet that i'm
browsing
and i find that it particularly
resonates with me all i have to do is
send that tweet to the read-wise twitter
account and it will automatically save
the tweet or save the thread into
read-wise so again bringing all in one
place and finally more recently they've
added podcast support so it
automatically connects to error because
i've linked up my air to i o account
with read-wise and now all of the
air quotes that i'm capturing from
podcasts are automatically being synced
into read-wise so here are some
highlights that i took from the hugh
jackman episode of the tim ferriss show
and because air had a transcript
available for it like all of the quotes
that i've got from this episode are now
all in one place in read wise so that's
all well and good we've got this app
that integrates all of these different
highlights from these different sources
but what's the point of it well there's
two main benefits of this firstly the
traditional read-wise service and what
i've been kind of talking on my channel
for the last two years since i first
discovered it is that if you want every
day readwise can send you an email that
has five of your highlights that's
randomly surfaced but very recently
they've added another feature and that
makes this absolutely game changing and
part of the magical insight logging
framework and that feature is that
read-wise can now automatically export
all of its highlights to notion which is
the app that i'm using for my second
brain so as you'll know if you've been
following this channel for a while
notion is the app that i use for my
second brain it's my central external
note-taking system that basically
organizes my entire life for the record
notion are very kindly sponsoring this
video but they don't have any creative
control over what's being said and it's
one of those things where i've been
using notion for such a long time since
like i don't know february march 2019
and it is a perfect stroke of luck that
they also want to sponsor my videos
because and don't tell anyone i would
make these videos anyway even if they
didn't sponsor them but we'll keep quiet
about that anyway i use notion for
everything it organizes my life it
tracks my workouts i use it when
studying for my exams so when preparing
for the usmle the us medical exam that
i've been live streaming on twitch every
morning check out my twitch profile link
in the video description i also use
notion to manage every aspect of my
businesses and this youtube channel and
writing scripts and editing and working
with my team it just does so many things
and the best bit is notion is now
completely free of charge you only pay
for notion if you're working with a team
so if you're an individual if you're a
student you can use notion for free for
however long you want for whatever you
want it's absolutely fantastic hit the
link in the video description if you
want to check it out but yeah thanks
notion for sponsoring this video and so
the best thing ever is that read wise
now automatically exports into notion
and so what that means is that when you
link your notion account to read-wise
what it does is that it creates this
special read-wise page which just brings
together all of the highlights all of
the insights that you've gathered from
books articles podcasts and tweets and
this is really freaking cool right so
for example this is the library for
everything but if i want to look at
books here are all the books that i've
read that i've highlighted um and i can
go into one of them let's go tribe of
mentors and i can automatically see
every single one of the highlights that
i've gotten here and if i click on one
of these locations it will open up the
kindle app
to that location where i've made the
highlight if i want to find the context
behind what i was thinking at the time
here we go in the last five years what
do you believe behavioral habits improve
your life happiness is a choice you make
and a skill you develop the mind is just
as malleable as the body blah blah blah
from tribe of mentors by tim ferriss and
this works with everything looks like if
i click on articles i can filter it by
all the articles that i've read let's
see mark manson's post how to 80 20 your
life and in this post i highlighted
these two things in 1906 there was
economies blah blah economic output on a
larger scale like that clearly resonated
with me at the time which was in uh
november 2019 and because i highlighted
this on instapaper which is connected to
readwise is the integration layer which
then spits out its output to notion as
my second brain it's now here all in one
place and i can do that with a recent
podcast i've listened to that i've
highlighted for example here's the hugh
jackman one and it's got all of the
highlights for me in notion with nice
cover art and stuff so it just looks
pretty and it even does that with tweets
which i've only started doing recently
because i actually didn't realize you
could do this so for example this is a
thread that i bookmarked that i've now
shared into read wise which has now gone
into notion get a cup of coffee in this
thread i'll help you work out how much
money you need to retire so when i read
this thread of
39 things i was like oh this is cool
i'll save it but then it was it's been
sitting in my twitter bookmarks for i
don't know absolutely ages but now i've
got it all in notion all in one place so
those were the five apps in the magical
insight logging framework if you also
have this problem where you're consuming
too much stuff books articles podcasts
tweets whatever and you don't have like
a system for mining the insides from
that idea and actually applying them to
your own life and remembering them then
i'd really recommend you set up your own
magical insight logging framework you
don't have to use all of these apps uh
kindle i would 100 recommend to everyone
insta paper versus pocket you can use
both air is the only way of doing this
with podcasts at the moment read-wise is
fantastic and for your second brain
read-wise also outputs to notion rome
and evernote so you're not tied into any
one app for this sort of thing but as i
said the one that i use for my second
brain is notion and i swear by it and i
love it and i just basically organized
my entire life around notion and i
remember that back in the day like two
years ago anytime people would recognize
me on the streets or something hashtag
flex they would come up to me and say
hey ali you know i watched your ipad
videos and i bought an ipad or an ipad
pro because of your recommendation but
in the last like 18 months or so not one
person has said to me i've bought an
ipad because of recommendation instead
now the thing that people say to me when
they meet me in real life is i started
using notion because of you and it's
changed my life so thank you so if you
want to find out more about how i use
notion to organize my life and
supercharge my productivity hit the
little playlist over here that'll be
some of my top performing videos about
how i use notion the behind the scenes
of my magical system so thank you for
watching and i'll see you in the next
video
you