Hey friends, welcome back to the
channel. So what does it mean to make a
given year the best year of your life?
And I think it's kind of three things.
Firstly, it's that we are making
progress towards the things that truly
matter to us. Secondly, that our life is
broadly in balance. So we're not [music]
screwing up one area of our life for the
sake of another. And thirdly, that we
are while working towards the things
that matter to us, we are managing to
enjoy ourselves and kind of enjoying
every day on its own merit rather than
purely seeing it as a [music] means to
an end. And so in this video, I want to
go over three of my favorite methods.
These are really simple methods. You can
apply them whenever, whether it's at the
start of the year or the middle of the
year or the end of the year, like
literally whenever. And it will help you
move more towards making sure that this
coming year is the actual best year of
your life in terms of meaningfulness and
balance and enjoyability as well. All
right, so method number one is a really
simple reflection exercise called the
wheel of life. And the idea here is that
we want to split up life into a bunch of
different components and then we rate
our satisfaction with those different
[music] areas of life. And so if you
want to do this exercise, you can do it
on a piece of paper or you can do it on
your phone. I think a piece of paper is
nice. Start by drawing a little circle.
That is your wheel. And then you want to
split it up into three segments. And
those three segments are for your work,
for your health, and for your
relationships. So now you have a wheel
with three/3s. Now you want to split up
each of the thirds into three segments
each. So at this point, you've got a
wheel with nine segments. If you don't
want to do it on paper, you don't have
to on paper. You can just literally
write down these different categories
that I'm about to give you. And so those
categories are within health. We have
three things. And that is [music] body,
mind, and soul. or you can call it
physical health, mental health,
spiritual health, but I kind of like
body, mind, and [music] soul because it
sounds more cute. Under relationships,
we've got romance, family, and friends.
And then under work, we have mission,
money, and growth. And you can call
mission your career or job or whatever
you want to call it, but that's kind of
the main thing that you were doing for
work. Okay. So, at this point, we've
split up life into these nine different
components. And the job now is that we
want to rate on a scale from 0 to 10 how
aligned we feel in each of these
different areas of our life. And by
aligned, I mean my actions in the here
and now are consistent with where I
think I would like to be. You can sort
of think of this as how satisfied am I
with this area of life. I prefer to
think of it as alignment rather than
satisfaction because like I don't know,
you might be a 3 out of 10 in terms of
satisfaction with money because you're
not yet a I don't know millionaire in
passive income or whatever the thing
might be, but you might be a 10 out of
10 in alignment because you are taking
the actions necessary to get to [music]
where you want to be. And so with this
little diagram on screen, I would
encourage you to pause the video now.
Genuinely, please pause the video and
just think about what would your rating
out of 10 be for each of these different
areas of life. And I guarantee that if
you just pause this video and think
about it, you will come up with some
interesting insights into your life. And
this is genuinely a good use of your
time while you're watching YouTube right
now. You just pause the video and really
think about this. Now, these are the
ratings that I gave myself when I did
this exercise a few days ago. And the
cool thing is is that if you are doing
this on pen and paper, then you can
shade in the little wheel of life based
on what your numbers are. So, if you got
a 10 out of 10, you would fully shade in
that particular segment of the wheel. If
you got a five, you would half shade it
in. You get the idea. And you end up
with this sort of FIFA radar chart of
like these different aspects of your
life, which I think is pretty cool. Now,
once you've done that, we are going to
add one final category, which I don't
put as part of the wheel. I sort of put
it off to the side or underneath the
wheel if I'm doing it on pen and paper.
And that is the category for joy. How
aligned do you feel with your actions in
the here and now compared to where you
want to be in terms of the amount of joy
you are experiencing in your life? And
for me right now, that is probably a 6
out of 10. Now, this is great because
the whole point is to help make this
next year the best year of our life. And
so, in theory, if we were able to get to
a point where we were, let's say, 10 out
of 10 across all these different areas,
that would mean that we are doing the
things that are [music] most meaningful
to us and actually making progress
towards them. And we're also in balance
with all the different areas of our life
because broadly these 10 roughly cover
pretty much every area of life. And
hopefully, we are also enjoying the
journey along the way, especially if we
have a 10 out of 10 on the joy front,
too. So, this is pretty cool, right? It
means we have now created a clear sense
of where we are right now. And then we
can get a sense of where we would like
to be in terms of where we would like
these numbers to go. And whenever you
have a sense of where you are now and
where you want to be, that is what
creates what we call goals. And part of
making this year the best year of your
life is to be able to then make progress
towards those goals. And this is already
a really good start because a lot of
people want to be more productive, but
they don't even take an inventory of
their life because they just think of
productivity as being just about work or
just about hustle or grind or whatever.
But actually, at least the way I think
about it, productivity is using our time
in a way that's intentional and
effective and enjoyable. And that is
kind of the [music] message of my book,
Field of Productivity. At this point, it
is worth highlighting or underlining or
circling or whatever in each of these
different areas in work in health and
relationships. What is the one that
really stands out to you as needing some
amount of work? So, for example, for me,
in the relationships column, I've given
my friends category a 4 out of 10
because I just don't see my friends very
often. And so, that's one that clearly
for me needs some work. And so, I'd be
circling that. Within health, I've given
my soul category a four out of 10. But I
mean, I'm not overly concerned about
that. I am concerned about the
body/physical health being just a five
out of 10. So, I'm going to circle that
because that's something I want to
actively work on. And then on the work
front, I'm pretty blessed to be a 9 out
of 10 on mission and money, but I'm only
a 7 out of 10 for growth. And so, I want
to circle that one because I feel like I
could do with some more growth in my
life. But once you know how to do the
wheel of life, you can actually just do
this whenever you feel like your life is
somewhat misaligned or you're not really
sure where you're going or you feel a
bit burnt out or you feel a bit
stressed, it it literally takes 30
seconds to just bring up these different
9 to 10 categories and to just rate
yourself out of 10 on each one. And
that's not to beat yourself up. You're
not like, "Oh my god, I'm flagagillating
myself because I only gave myself a 3
out of 10. This is a pure solid
inventory of where you are in these
different areas of life." And then the
great news is you can then start taking
actions towards remedying certain of
these areas. Now, if you've been
wondering why my money component on this
wheel of life is a 9 out of 10, that is
because A, I've been running my business
over for over 7 years now. And B, I have
been investing my money throughout that
time. And if you're interested in
investing your money, then you might
like to check out Trading 212, who are
very kindly sponsoring this video.
Trading 212 is a fantastic app that lets
you invest in stocks and shares and
funds in a very easy and commission-free
fashion. And they've got a bunch of
features which are super helpful, which
is why I personally use Trading 212 to
manage a portion of my portfolio. So,
firstly, they've got a really nice pies
[music] feature. Pies are really cool
because what you can do is there's
people all around the world who are
professionals or super into investments
and stuff and what they do is that they
create a PI which is basically a basket
of stocks and shares and funds and then
you can browse all the different pies
and you can see how they've performed
over time. Now obviously the thing that
most people recommend when it comes to
investing is to invest in diversified in
index funds like the S&P 500 which you
can also do with trading 212 but if
you're using a portion of your portfolio
to be a bit more experimental like I
like to do with like 5% of my
portfolios. So let's say you were
investing £100 into someone's pie and
that pie had 50% allocation for Tesla
and 50% for Apple. It would mean £50
gets invested in Tesla, £50 gets
invested in Apple. And you can also
create your own pie with your own asset
allocation and share it on the app if
you want. They've also recently added
support for multicurrency accounts,
which is super helpful if you're
investing like I do in the US stock
market. You don't then get hit with
foreign exchange fees. And if you have
an invest or an ISA account, then
trading 212 also gives you daily
interest on your uninvested cash in
pounds, euros, or US dollars. They are
also highly highly reputable. They've
got over 23,000 Trust Pilot reviews with
an average rating of 4.6 stars, which is
pretty insane. Now, if any of that signs
up your street and you would like to
sign up, then you can hit the link in
the video description. And if you use
that link, you will even get up to 100
in a totally free share. So, it's free
money. You might as well sign up. So,
thank you so [music] much Trading 212
for sponsoring this video. So, that now
brings us on to method number two, and
that is what I call the 12 month
celebration. And this is basically my
preferred method for goal setting. So,
setting goals is an important part of
life. There's a bunch of studies that
show that people who set goals uh
perform better and are more productive
and feel happier with life than people
who don't. There are also a bunch of
studies that show that people who write
their goals down are more likely to
achieve them than people who either have
the goals and don't write them down or
don't have the goals at all. And so the
12 month celebration is just a very
simple way of approaching goal setting.
And the exercise is simple. In each of
the salient areas of your life, ask
yourself, what would I like to be
celebrating 12 months from now? And
really imagine this, like imagine you're
sitting down having dinner with a friend
of yours. You guys are mutually kind of
holding each other accountable and
helping each other out and you're
celebrating together. You're really
celebrating how much progress you've
made in each of these different areas of
your life. Now, you can start with the
three areas that you circled as being
the most salient. Or you can do it as I
would recommend for all 10 different
areas of your life, especially if you're
doing this like at the start of the year
as part of an annual planning thing.
You're asking yourself 12 months from
now in each of these different areas,
what what would I like to be
celebrating? So, for example, for me in
the physical health category, cuz I've
realized I've only rated it a five out
of 10. I'm imagining I'm having dinner
with, let's say, my friend Godwin, who's
pretty pretty jacked, and we're
celebrating how much progress I've made
in the last 12 months in my physical
health. What is like genuinely what is
the thing that I would love to be
celebrating 12 months from now? And then
I'll come up with a few different
candidate celebration options, like, you
know, a few a few different options for
goals. So, I'd love to be celebrating
having packed on loads of muscle. I'd
love to be celebrating getting more
lean. I'd love to be celebrating having
consistently worked out, let's say,
three times a week for the last 12
months. I'd love to be celebrating
becoming more flexible in mobile. I'd
love to be celebrating having played
sports once or twice a week every week
for the last 12 months. So, these are
all different options, but celebrating
all of these is probably a bit much. And
so, for each of these different
categories, once you've thought about
like what would I love to be
celebrating, what I'd encourage you to
do is to really boil it down to, okay,
cool. I would like to be celebrating all
these five 10 different things. But if I
had to boil it down to just one thing
and I could only celebrate one thing,
what would that one thing be? Because
generally having a single goal to work
towards helps the brain focus. It helps
the entire kind of physiology and our
habits and everything just move in
[music] that one direction. Whereas if I
was trying to build more muscle and also
get lean and also play sports and also
be more flexible, it's like there's a
lot of it it becomes very overwhelming
and very complicated very quickly. And
I'm all about simplicity here. So
starting with what is the one goal? What
is the one thing you would like to be
celebrating? And so for me in the
physical health front, I realized that
the one thing I would love to be
celebrating is to reduce my reduce the
amount of my visceral abdominal fat that
I have. Done a couple of DEXA scans
recently. I found that I've got quite a
lot of fat around the belly thanks to my
poor genetics and poor diet. And
visceral adipost issue is the thing that
correlates with all these negative
health [music] outcomes like
cardiovascular disease and stroke and
all that stuff. And so if I can get that
number down, if I can reduce the amount
of fat in my belly thanks to my poor
diet and my poor genetics, then that
would be a great thing worth
celebrating. And then all the other
stuff like getting more muscle and
becoming more mobile and like playing
sports. All of that kind of stuff is the
cherry on top. It's the bonus. And so
you can do this 12 month celebration
thing with the different areas of your
life and that then creates [music]
goals. Now a couple of extra points when
it comes to the 12 month celebration.
one line that I really like adding to
the end of any goal that I set. It's
actually a trick I got from my friend
Dicky Bush who is a fellow internet
entrepreneur and that is whenever you
set a goal just add a few words to the
end of that goal which is while enjoying
every step along the way. So if we use
this health example again you know my 12
month celebration is to reduce my
visceral adipost issues to i.e become
more lean. But I would add the phrase
while enjoying every step along the way.
And that means that instead of just
thinking of it as this goal that I'm
fixated on that I'm going to kind of
grind to get towards, it just helps my
mind think in a little bit more of a
light feelood productivity kind of way,
a little bit more of an adventurous way
of like how do I get lean but while also
enjoying every step along the way. And
then tip number two for the 12 month
celebration is please write this down
somewhere. [music] So, I have a Google
doc that I use with my CEO coach, his
name is Eric, and we look at the Google
doc every quarter and we've written down
what are my goals for each of the
different areas of my life. And then
every quarter, every 3 months, we'll
figure out, okay, cool. For each of
these different areas, what can what can
we make tangible progress on in the next
90 days? And this is super helpful
because if you think about these goals
and you make them in your mind, but you
don't write them down and then you don't
look at that document ever again, then
it just means you're going to forget
what goals you set at the start of the
year. And this is a big part of why
people struggle with New Year's
resolutions is they set all these goals,
they have all these like great
intentions, but then they don't have any
sort of system for reviewing the goals,
reflecting on it, measuring their action
and measuring their traction towards
that particular goal. And so if you're
doing this exercise, and I'd really
recommend you do if you do care about
making this year the best year of your
life, write the goal down somewhere, put
it in a Google doc, bookmark it, put it
on your Chrome bookmark bar, whatever
the thing might be. Just make it super
easy to remind yourself about what your
goals are. And this is why things like
weekly reviews and monthly reviews and
quarterly reviews and all this sort of
stuff like reviewing our life is such a
big part of anyone's productivity system
at least [music] if they know anything
about productivity. And then the final
tip I would recommend for the 12 month
celebration is a bit of an optional
extra but this is quite helpful. When
you've decided what you'd like to be
celebrating 12 months from now with each
of these different areas, ask yourself
why. Why is that particular [music]
thing important to you? And it's useful
to have the why also in that document
where you have written down your goals
because again you can just remind
yourself about why this thing was
important to you. And so for me, the why
behind this visceral adapost thing is,
and this is what I've written down in my
document, because visceral atapost
tissue is the major thing that's going
to lead to me dying early of
cardiovascular and cerebrovascular
disease. It's a significant priority to
get that number down and to keep it
down. Building more muscle is mostly a
vanity thing, but reducing [music] my
abdominal fat is genuinely a health
thing. So, I've written down for myself
exactly why that particular goal is
important to me. And that's not [music]
to say you can't change these goals
later in the year, but at least if you
have it written down and you have a
clear why behind it, it [music] means
that you're more likely to stay on that
path that you decided for yourself was
was going to be important to you. We
come to method number three and this is
where the rubber meets the road. Like
you know with the reflection and goal
setting and stuff, we have kind of
charted a course for where we want to
go. And now we need a system to ensure
that we actually make the time and the
space to get there. And now there's
loads of different productivity systems
for this. I have a whole course that's
coming out soon that's going to be about
my feelood productivity system. You can
read about strategies in the book as
well. But one really needlemoving
strategy I want to share in this video
is something that's called the ideal
week method. And this has been one of
the most game-changing time management
techniques I've ever used. And basically
the idea is that you open up a blank
Google calendar and you call it your
ideal week [music] calendar. And you
start off by blocking off the absolute
essentials in your life in terms of like
when do you want to wake up. So for
example, let's say every day I want to
wake up at 7:00 a.m. I would put that
into a block in the calendar. Let's say
I want to sleep at 10 p.m. I'd put that
into a block in the calendar. I'd be
putting all these different blocks into
my calendar. And then that shows me how
much time do I have left to play with.
So now you know those goals that we've
just set in terms of the 12 month
celebration in terms of these different
areas of our life. Our job when doing
the ideal week is we want to try and
find time or not try, we want to find
time in our calendar every week to
actually make time and to to take action
on these specific things. So let's say
in the friends category, I wanted to see
my friends more often. My 12-month
celebration might be that I'm
celebrating the fact that I saw my
friends for a group dinner at least once
a week. In my ideal week calendar, I
therefore need to have a block at least
once a week for a group dinner with
friends. And that's the point of the
ideal week. It's like your ideal
ordinary week. It's, you know, if things
are going according to plan, roughly
where are you spending your time and
what are you blocking out time to do?
Similarly, on the health front, my 12
month celebration is losing is becoming
more lean and that means I need to have
half an hour of day blocked into my
ideal week for exercise every morning or
every evening or whatever the thing
might be. And if you realize that you
don't actually have time for a
particular thing because you're busy
with other areas of your life, that's
totally okay. But that means you can
change your goal. You can change the
12-mon celebration to reflect the time
that you actually have. One of the other
big things that derails people is trying
to be too perfectionistic and trying to
do too much. Trying to say, "Hey, you
know, I want to set this goal and this
goal and this goal and this goal." And
then you look at your calendar and you
realize you actually just physically
don't have the time because you have a
job or two or you have kids to look
after or you have to commute to school
or whatever the thing might be. The
thing I love about the ideal week method
is that it forces us to get clarity on
what is actually important to us. What
is the time that we have for the things
that we have to do and then what's the
time that we can use on the things that
we actually want to do. And mostly
you'll probably realize that this is
less time than you thought you had.
Which is great because it means you can
start doing fewer things and you can
cross some things off your 12 month
celebration list. Maybe it's not a goal
you want to work on for this year.
That's totally okay. Maybe you can work
on it next year instead or when you have
a little bit more time freed up in your
life. Now, if you enjoyed this video and
you want to take a deeper dive into this
stuff, then you're going to absolutely
love my live free online workshop which
is being hosted on January the 6th,
2024. And that's going to be a few hours
where I take you through these exercise
live over a Zoom call. We'll actually do
the exercises and I'll elaborate on them
a little bit more so that we can set you
up for 2024 to be the best year of your
life. And that is exclusively available
for the very nice people who have
pre-ordered my book. So, you can
pre-order my book with the link down
below and then you send us send us your
receipt and we'll make sure you get a
ticket to the event. And if you enjoyed
this video and you want to know more
about my specific methods for time
management, you're going to love this
video, which is the Trident method for
time management. It includes a few more
details about the ideal week along with
my time management process for the whole
year and also dayto-day. So, you're
going to find that super helpful. Thank
you so much for watching and I'll see
you in the next video. Bye-bye.