hey friends welcome back to the channel
if you're new here my name is Ali I'm a
doctor turned entrepreneur and the
author of Feelgood productivity which is
a book about how to be more productive
in a way that feels good but in this
video I want to talk about four books
other than my own that can genuinely
change your life now before we go into
that this idea of books being
lifechanging or whatever is a bit of a
clickbait thing that we often see on
YouTube and I've made videos in the past
where I say this book has changed my
life and there are always people in the
comments that are a bit cynical or
skeptical about that like how could a
book possibly change your life so before
we dive into these four books which I
suspect most of these books you've
probably not heard of and you probably
not read I want to share a little bit of
my thoughts and philosophy around what
it means for a book to completely change
your life and this video is sponsored by
HubSpot but more on them later so the
way in which a book changes your life is
that a book exposes you to a particular
idea now that idea then leads to a
decision and that decision then leads to
action and then that action then leads
to result and that result is the thing
that changes your life so for example I
would say that the book The 4-Hour Work
Week by Tim Ferris completely changed my
life why did it change my life because
it exposed me to the idea that I could
make passive income and that I could
build a business that generates money
while I'm sleeping so that I can then
live life on my own terms broadly that
was the key idea that the 4our work week
exposed me to it's got a couple hundred
Pages it's got a bunch of other ideas
but that was the key thing that I took
away from it now it wouldn't have been a
life-changing book if I didn't then make
a decision based on that idea and the
decision I made after reading that book
was I am therefore going to spend my
years in medical school building a
business on the side that can generate
passive income so that when I work as a
doctor I can do it for fun rather than
because I have to and that decision led
to action it meant that while I was
going through medical school I was
looking for ways that I could possibly
make money on the side I learned how to
code I improved my skills with
programming and I ended up building a
business while I was going through
medical school that was making me around
$40 $50,000 a year which is what I would
have been earning had I been working
full-time as a doctor so that was pretty
sick and that business then morphed into
this YouTube channel which has
completely changed my life and so when I
say that the book the 4our work week
changed my life it's because it gave me
that particular idea and so if you watch
these sorts of videos about you know
this book changed my life please don't
think that I'm just trying to clickbait
you here with this freaking title is
like oh every other day 's life has
changed Changed by a godamn book it kind
of is it's probably not every other day
but anytime I read a book what I'm on
the lookout for is an idea that could
potentially change the course of my life
and so the four books that I want to
talk about in this video are books that
I think if you were to read them and
genuinely apply them and they hit you at
the right time these books can give you
an idea that causes you to make a
decision which causes you to take action
that leads to results and then you will
look back on this video and say wow this
video changed my life because it gave me
the idea to read these books that I
might not have read otherwise now this
is quite a wide assortment of books and
so I'd recommend you skip around in the
timestamps because realistically you
probably don't want to read all four of
these right now because like chances are
one of these will resonate more with you
than the other three and that's totally
okay I would recommend reading that one
and applying the insides from it and
seeing if you can potentially make a
decision which leads to action which
leads to results based on just that one
recommendation but because lots of
people follow this channel thankfully
thank you for that um I want to kind of
share a bit of a variety and these are
all books that I discovered this year
number one is a book called The Practice
by Seth Goden and this book is aimed at
anyone who does creative work basically
if the thing that you do or the thing
that you'd like to to do involves
shipping creative work than this book is
for you so what does shipping creative
work mean and here's a quote from the
book that explains it shipping because
it doesn't count if you don't share it
creative because you're not a cog in the
system you're a Creator a problem solver
a generous leader who's making things
better by producing a new way forward
and work because it's not a hobby you
might not get paid for it not today but
you approach it as a professional The
Muse is not the point excuses are
avoided and the work is why you are here
and the core idea that I've taken away
from this book that I think can change
your life if you take this idea and
really apply it on board is the idea
that it's going to sound cliche but the
process and the practice is what counts
not the output Seth Goden writes the
practice is not the means to the output
the practice is the output because the
practice is all we can control the
practice demands that we approach our
process with commitment it acknowledges
that creativity is not an event it's
simply what we do whether or not we're
in the mood sculptor Elizabeth King said
it beautifully process saves us from the
poverty of our intentions and BAS
basically this whole book is just Seth
Goden saying again and again and again
in a bunch of different ways that when
you are in the business of shipping
creative work you've got to focus on the
process you've got to not be attached to
the outcome and you've got to focus on
just showing up for the process showing
up like a professional and getting
better at that thing over time and that
itself is the reward the reward for
doing good work is the ability to do
more good work this morning I was going
through my highlights of this book I've
made about 70 different highlights from
this book I'll put a link down below if
you want to see them to my notion page
for the Highlight but this book
resonated with me so much because as a
Creator sometimes I struggle with the
process I know that you know when I was
writing my book that the creative work
was in showing up and doing the writing
every day I know that for making YouTube
videos the creative work is in showing
up and filming the videos and preparing
the videos but I often let emotions and
feelings and like oh I don't feel like
doing this therefore I don't want to do
it like there are a lot of times where I
don't treat it like a professional but
weirdly on the times where I do treat it
like a professional where the reason I'm
making the video is not for the sake of
a sponsor deadline or for the sake of
like some sort of external metric but
the reason I'm making the video is so
that I can genuinely share from the
heart share with the with the intention
of love and contribution and service and
then show up and make the video it just
feels freaking amazing it's sort of like
kind of like going to the gym sometimes
you don't feel like going but if you
actually just push yourself and make
yourself do the thing and just focus on
the process and focus on showing up as
your best self at the end of it there's
no world in which you don't feel good
having been to the gym and it's the same
with this sort of creative work and the
reason that I think this book is
life-changing is because I know so many
creators who struggle with having their
selfworth to attach to the outcome of
the process they're not focused on the
process they're focused on the outcome
they feel bad if a video doesn't get
that many views I've been through this
myself they feel bad if the video gets
negative comments it feel bad if for
example someone someone replies being
like oh this wasn't that helpful whereas
the creators who I know who are the
happiest are almost the ones who detach
themselves from the outcome they're just
showing up they're focused on the
process and for them it's a win if they
get the video out if they spend the time
filming the video if they spent the time
writing the thing even if they've
written a th000 words and the next day
they delete all thousand words the fact
is they are still proud of themselves
because because they showed up and they
did the work and you know when it comes
to these sorts of non-fiction books I
would know having having written one
myself often there are just like one to
three key ideas in the book and the rest
of the book some people would say very
cynically is just fluff but actually I
could tell you right now through this
video yeah just focus on enjoying the
process but like you know that
intellectually but through experiencing
it and through reading a book about it
that tells you the same thing again and
again and again in loads of different
ways with loads of different examples
that is when it becomes more than just
intellectual knowledge that's when it
starts to seep into your soul into your
body into your heart whatever
terminology you want to use and this is
why reminders are super helpful this is
why you know Atomic habits is an amazing
book fundamentally the one thing he he
says is small habits lead to Great
results but if you read the book you
know it's freaking amazing it's really
really really helpful even though he's
just saying that one thing so it's not
filled with fluff as cynics kind of
sometimes say it's almost like for
example if you're watching a comedy show
and they just gave you the punch line
that's not a very fun comedy show to
watch you kind of need the build up to
benefit from the punchline similarly if
you're listening to a musical
performance and all you had was climaxes
and the crescendo that's not
particularly fun because the buildup IS
what makes the crescendo and the climax
worth it in the words of alen wats so
I'd encourage you if you take even one
thing away from this video please do not
dismiss the value of non-fiction books
like this if the right book hits you at
the right time and gives you the right
idea oh man that can completely change
your life and the practice by Seth Goden
is one that's completely changed my own
creative process because now I'm less
focused on myself more focused on
service and more more focused on showing
up even if I don't feel like it I will
still show up and maybe I won't film a
video directly because I kind of feel
like I want to film videos when I feel
like it but I'll at least show up get
myself to a coffee shop drink a cup of
coffee and at least do some creative
work do some writing get some highlights
from a book summarize what I think about
it write it for my weekly email
newsletter and the more I stick to this
process and focus on the process the
better everything in my life becomes so
that is the first book The Practice by
Seth Goden and if you are a Creator in
any form I think you will get enormous
value and I think that book might just
change your life now this book is all
about shipping creative work but if you
are like me and you ship creative work
and then you also want to create a
business out of it then you might like
to to check out HubSpot who are very
kindly sponsoring this video HubSpot is
powerful flexible and easy to your
software that's built for growing your
business and we are actively using in
our business as well we've been dreaming
about having the perfect trm for our
parttime H accelerator for years and we
finally switched to HubSpot and it is
such a breath of fresh air and it's so
magical to be able to connect all of our
data all in one place through the
platform you get a ton of insight into
your entire sales process by being able
to track all of your leads all of the
way from when they first sign up to
something to when they're a loyal
customer and that is insanely helpful
and whether or not you're at the stage
yet where you want to build a whole
sales and marketing and customer success
CRM HubSpot actually has a bunch of
quick practical online courses that you
can take as well along with
Comprehensive certifications so that you
can learn everything you need to know
about the most sought-after business
skills they also have a great free
template for being more productive at
work which has loads of information and
tips about how to manage your day and
your energy which is the sort of stuff
that I talk about in my book as well as
well as stuff about remote working and
actually the hubs sport resources on
remote working have been super helpful
for me and my team over the last few
months as I've been traveling the world
and switching to a remote lifestyle you
can check out HubSpot and get all of
these resources completely for free by
by hitting the link in the video
description so thank you so much HubSpot
for sponsoring this video and let's move
on to book number two okay the next book
that we're going to talk about that is a
book that you've almost certainly not
heard of and it's called The Strangest
Secret by Earl Nightingale now Earl
Nightingale is this American
motivational speaker author coach kind
of guy who was around in like the 1950s
in the US on Radio and on TV Earl had
this classic kind of ragar richer story
he was born during the time of the Great
Depression and he grew up in poverty and
the stranger secret is actually a record
that he recorded in 1956 it's like an
audio program which has been converted
into a book and his whole thing
apparently was that he was trying to
figure out why is it that some people
grow rich and prosperous and why does do
people like his family end up growing up
in poverty and so he did a bunch of
reading and ended up becoming like this
motivational speaker and stuff and so
this book The Strangest Secret is like
one of these OG from like the 1950s
self-help books that has a core message
and the core message is going to sound
weird it's going to sound cliche but I
think if you take the idea on board it
can completely change your life and that
idea is the power of knowing what you
want and writing it down
that's basically it his the whole I'm
not a huge fan of the second half of the
book but the first half of the book I
highlighted the absolute Living
Daylights out of and there's a quote
here about the secret to success he says
I'll tell you who the successful people
are a success is the school teacher who
is teaching school because that's what
she wanted to do the success is the
woman who is a wife and mother because
she wanted to become a wife and mother
and is doing a good job of it the
success is the man who runs the Corner
Gas Station because that's what he
wanted to do the success is the
successful salesman who wants to become
a top-notch Salesman and grow and build
with his organization a success is
anyone who is doing deliberately a
predetermined job because that's what he
decided to do deliberately but only one
in 20 people actually does that and I
actually really like this definition of
success he's not saying that success is
trying to be rich he's not saying
success is trying to become famous or
popular or whatever the thing is he
sayings you are successful when you are
working towards doing the thing that you
actually want to do that's it whether
it's being a mom or a housewife or a
teacher or a businessman or entrepreneur
or a YouTuber or author you are
successful if you are actively taking
steps to work towards the the thing that
you actually want and the problem is
very few people actually know what they
want for example if I were to meet you
in a coffee shop right now and we were
having a conversation for whatever
reason and I were to say hey can you
show me where you've written down your
goals for the next year you'd probably
say what goals for the next year if
you've thought about your goals then you
probably haven't written them down there
there are very few people who a know
what they actually want to do and to be
write it down somewhere and ear
Nightingale and a lot of these books
like Think and Grow by Napoleon Hill
anything by Jin Ron anything by Tony
Robin like all of these self-help type
people including me ultimately land on
the conclusion that if you know where
you are trying to go then you'll figure
out the how of how you're going to get
there but so few people actually know
where they're trying to go that like
they end up Meandering around all the
all over the place and ear's definition
of success is you are working towards
the thing that you actually want to do
so this is not actually that hard the
whole thing is just figure out what you
actually want to do and turn it into a
goal and just write it down doesn't need
to be a smart goal doesn't need to be
that specific or measurable or
achievable orisk you just need to have
some idea of where you're actually
trying to go and the way I think of
goals is that that setting a goal is
like understanding where is the
destination and that's not to say that
you are then fixated on the destination
but it is to say that you are then
taking steps so moving in the direction
of that destination and given that you
know roughly what the destination is you
can also then assess am I on the right
path to go towards that particular
destination if you know for example that
you want to write three books in the
next 10 years cool that's really useful
to know that means on average one book
every 3 and a half years and so you can
then assess am I actually taking the
steps to get there this is not to say
you're fixated on it it's not to say
that you know that you're wedded to that
particular timeline maybe it'll be 12
years maybe it'll be 8 years but you're
way more likely to write three books if
you have set the intention of I want to
write three books in the next 10 years
here's another great quote from the book
people with goals succeed because they
know where they're going think of a ship
leaving a harbor and think of it with a
complete Voyage mapped out and planned
the captain and crew know exactly where
it's going and how long it will take it
has a definite goal
99,999 times out of 10,000 it will get
to where it started out to get now let's
take another ship just like the first
only let's not put a crew on it or a
captain of the helm let's give it no
aiming point no goal no Destiny we just
start the engine and let it go I think
you'll agree with me that if it gets out
of the harbor at all it will either sink
or wind up on some deserted Beach a
derelict it can't go any place because
it has no destination no guidance and
this book has had a major impact on me
because it literally in like the half an
hour it took me to read the first half
of this book completely sold me on the
idea of setting goals in the past if
you've been following the channel for a
while you know I've had a bit of like
I'm not really sure whether setting
goals is worthwhile or not and I'm like
of course it is it's useful to have a
destination in mind because there is no
Journey without a destination in mind
again not to say you're going to be
fixated on the destination but if you
know where you're going then you are far
more likely to Marshall resources and to
find a way to get there and to enjoy the
process of getting there which is the
whole thesis of my book feel-good
productivity like how do you find a way
to make the journey itself feel good
because sure maybe you'll get to the
destination but you'll realize when you
get there that the journey is What
mattered in the first place but
crucially even though the journey is
what matters you cannot have a journey
without a destination without feeling
Meandering and without feeling like you
don't know where your life is going and
all this kind of stuff and the more
clarity you can have on where you're
actually trying to go the the more
likely you are to actually get there and
to enjoy the process along the way so if
you currently do not have goals and do
not have them written down somewhere
perhaps you might enjoy reading The
Strangest Secret by L Nightingale it
will take you like half an hour to read
you can skip the second half I don't
really like the second half or you know
I'm sure it's good but it didn't Vibe
with me at this stage of my life right
now but the first half completely Vibes
me and I was like oh my freaking God
this is bloody incredible stuff and
again I'll put my highlights in a link
down below if you're interested in just
reading the highlights and then you can
decide if the book is for you or not all
right book number three that I think
might have the potential to change your
life is a book called No More Mr Nice
Guy by Robert Glover now I agree the
title of this book is a little bit
clickbaity and you might think No More
Mr Nice Guy is this some book that's
going to teach men to become even more
assholish or like all that kind of stuff
it is not that at all I've highlighted
the absolute out of this I actually
read this like 10 years ago and I've
been every few years I find myself
rereading it and taking new things away
from it because it's basically a book if
I were to sum it up in one sentence it's
a book that encourages men to be mindful
of and express their own feelings it's
basically a book that says as a dude
it's okay to have feelings it's okay to
have needs and it's okay to express
those feelings and needs and to love
yourself for who you are rather than
trying to perform kind of gain the
approval of other people now if you are
a guy like me and you struggle like me
to understand and express your own
emotions and feelings and needs then I
think you will get enormous value from
this book here's a fun quote consider
this if you did not care what people
thought of you how would you live your
life differently if you were not
concerned with getting the approval of
women how would your relationships with
the opposite sex be different nice guy
seek external validation in just about
every social situation but their quest
for approval is the most pronounced in
their relationships with women nice guys
interpret a woman's approval as the
ultimate validation of their worth signs
of a woman's approval can take the form
of her desire to have sex flutatious
Behavior a smile a touch or
attentiveness at the other end of the
spectrum if a woman is depressed in a
bad mood or angry nice guys interpret
these things to mean that she is not
accepting or approving of them nice guys
have a difficult time comprehending that
in general people are not drawn to
perfection in others people are drawn to
Shared interest interests shared
problems and an individual's Life Energy
humans connect with humans hiding one's
humanity and trying to project an image
of perfection makes a person vague
slippery lifeless and uninteresting I
often refer to nice guys as Teflon men
they work so hard to be smooth nothing
can stick to them unfortunately this
Teflon coating also makes it difficult
for people to get close it is actually a
person's rough edges and human
imperfections that give others something
to connect with I've got so many
highlights from this book it's really
really good again I'll share a link to
my highlights down below if you want to
check them out but basically the whole
book is about teaching guys that it's
okay to have feelings and it's okay to
have needs and it's it's okay to express
them and you don't need to have shame
around the fact that you have feelings
and needs and your own preferences and
actually you know this narrative that
we're taught as men that like your job
on this Earth is to sacrifice yourself
for the sake of the other people in your
life you know maybe there's some truth
to that we're going to talk talk more
about that in the fourth book but it's
like that thing with the in the
airplanes like you put your own oxygen
mask on first before helping other
people with it and I think this applies
to me this applies to basically most of
my male friends we really struggle to
express our emotions and feelings and
needs and the exercises and journaling
prompts and everything in this book no
more Mr a nice guy are super helpful and
could potentially change the course of
your life if any of this sort of stuff
has resonated with you so far and now
we're on to book number four which is an
amazing book called the second Mountain
by David Brooks now the whole thesis of
this book is that there are two
mountains that we climb in life the
first mountain is the mountain of the
self it's the mountain of achievement
it's the mountain of Freedom it's the
mountain of I want to make money I want
to be successful I want to make
something of myself and then one of very
things happen either we get to the top
of the first mountain in AR number one
or we get knocked off that first
mountain and into the Valley through
someone close to us having a health
problem or dying or ourselves having a
health problem or dying or some kind of
major life event that takes us off of
the first mountain and then we end up in
this Valley and in the valley is when we
realize that oh there is actually a
second mountain and the second mountain
is the mountain of commitment it's the
mountain of service it's the mountain of
where your life is not just about you
it's about serving other people it's
about committing to something it's about
building a family it's about
contributing to something greater than
yourself it's about getting involved in
your local community getting involved in
your local church or Moscow whatever the
thing might be like really going for
your business because of the service
that it provides David Brooks argues
that while the first Mountain might make
you happy and give you Freedom the
second Mountain gives you Joy and
Lasting Joy is actually way better than
momentary happiness now if any of that
resonates with you if you're at a stage
of your life where maybe you've been on
the first Mountain for a long time as I
have and you might find you know In
fairness I've I've got to the top of the
first Mountain uh I've got freedom I've
got success I'm famous people come to me
on the streets and they say how much
they love me how much my Works change of
life all this kind of crap I've got L
money all this kind of stuff this is all
like first Mountain crap this is all
like I'm optimizing for Freedom I'm
focusing on myself I want to be famous I
want to be rich I want to be successful
but you get there and you realize that
it's not all it's cracked up to be and
when you're at the top of the first
Mountain sort of feels a bit Hollow it
sort of feels like uh do I really want
to continue working for more Fame and
more achievements and more accolades and
more freedom and more like optionality
and more like lack of attachment really
is that really what I want and when I
read this book I read it I've been
slowly reading it on and off over the
last year and again so much stuff in
this has resonated with me going to read
out some highlights cuz I like reading
highlights there's a crucial way to tell
whether you are on your first or second
Mountain where is your ultimate appeal
to self or to something outside the self
if the first mountain is about building
up the EGO and defining the self the
second mountain is about shedding the
ego and losing the self if the first
mountain is about acquisition the second
mountain is about contribution if the
first mountain is elitist moving up the
second mountain is egalitarian planting
yourself amid those who need and walking
arm in-arm with them ah beautiful here's
another one people on the first Mountain
have lives that are mobile and lightly
attached people on the second Mountain
are deeply rooted and deeply committed
the second Mountain life is a committed
life when I'm describing how second
mountain people live what I'm really
describing is how these people made
maximal commitments to others and how
they live them out in fervent Allin ways
these people are not keeping their
options open they are planted people on
the second Mountain have made strong
commitments to one or all of these four
things a vocation a spouse and family a
philosophy or faith and a community good
stuff I'm at the moment like I'm
currently in La filming this um cuz I'm
in the in the middle of a digital Nomad
traveling around the world and I know a
lot of people who have done this sort of
thing and they usually say somewhere
between 6 12 18 24 months into the
journey you realize that actually all of
this travel and all this freedom is no
longer that fulfilling I haven't done it
before so I'm doing it but I kind of
know full well based on people I've been
speaking to and based on reading this
book that the thing that's going to
bring me lasting Joy is not the ability
to just travel the world and do whatever
I want thing that's going to bring me
lasting Joy is getting married having a
family committing myself to like a thing
really taking my job seriously in like
sharing ideas and showing up in full
service mode and full contribution with
love and contribution and stuff even and
and not worrying about the money and I
just know that if I just do that it'll
bring me lasting joy and it'll probably
make loads of money as well here's
another highlight my first Mountain was
an insanely lucky one I achieved far
more professional success than I ever
expected to but that climb turned me
into a certain sort of person aloof
invulnerable and uncommunicative at
least when it came to my private life
but when I look back generally on the
errors and failures and Sins Of My Life
they tend to be failures of omission
failures to truly show up for the people
I should have been close to they tend to
be the sins of withdrawal evasion
workaholism conflict and avoidance
failure to empathize and a failure to
express myself openly I have two old and
dear friends who live 250 mi from me for
example and their side of the Friendship
has required immense forbearance and
forgiveness for all the times I've been
too busy too disorganized too distant
when they were in need or just available
I look at those dear friendships with a
gratitude mixed with shame and this
pattern not being present to what I love
because I prioritize time over people
productivity over relationship is a
recurring motive in my life oh
mate there's another really good one I I
felt really called out by this he
describes the sort of person who's in on
the first mountain in centuries past
emerging adults took their parents jobs
faiths towns and identities but in the
age of I'm free to be myself you're
expected to find your own career path
your own social tribe your own beliefs
values life Partners gender roles
political viewpoints and social
identities as a student your focus was
primarily on the short-term but now you
need a different set of navigational
skills to the far Horizon goals you'll
begin to orient your life towards and
then he goes on to kind of describe this
person who lives on the first Mountain
this is an excellent way to begin your
20s but the problem with this kind of
Life only becomes evident a few years
down the road if you haven't settled
down into one thing if you say yes to
everything year after year you end up
leading what kard lamented as an
aesthetic style of life the person
leading the aesthetic life is leading
his life as if it were a piece of art
judging it by aesthetic criteria is it
interesting or dull pretty or ugly
pleasurable or painful and here is where
I felt really called up such a person
schedules a Meditation Retreat here A
Burning Man visit there one Fellowship
one year and another one the next
there's swing dancing one day Soul cycle
twice a week Krav mgar for a few months
bigm yoga for a few months more and
occasionally a cool art gallery on a
Sunday afternoon your Instagram feed
will be amazing and everybody will think
you're the coolest person ever you tell
yourself that relationships really
matter to you scheduling drinks having
lunch but after you've had 20 social
Encounters in a week you forget what all
those encounters are supposed to build
to you have thousands of conversations
and remember none the problem is that
the person in the aesthetic phase sees
life as possibilities to be experienced
and not projects to be fulfilled or
ideals to be lived out he will hover
above everything but never land in in
the aesthetic way of life each
individual day is fun but it doesn't add
up to anything in the aesthetic way of
life each individual day is fun but it
doesn't seem to add up to anything and
if you feel like this concept this
metaphor first Mountain second Mountain
resonates if you feel like maybe you're
like me and that you've been chasing
your own selfish needs for success and
freedom and fame and money and all that
for way too long and now you feel
like actually there's something more to
life there's something there's more joy
to be found in commitment in attachment
in settling down as it were and view
settling down is not a bad thing if
you're at that stage of life I think
you're going to love this book it's
really really good mate David Brooks
what a Legend what a fantastic
book now if you got to the end of this
video and you've been vibing with the
way my philosophy on this sort of stuff
you might like to check out this video
over here which is a life update video
that I did recently that's very long
that shares some of these sentiments
around this sort of second Mountain
stuff and some of the realizations I've
had around kind of serving the self
serving other people doing what I want
like chasing money fulfillment all
happiness all that kind of stuff that's
in a video right over there thank you so
much for watching and I'll see you next
time bye-bye