so if there is one single habit that has
most changed my life that habit is
journaling I've been journaling pretty
consistently since like 2014 and so many
of the good things that have happened in
my life have happened directly as a
result of journaling consistently but
one thing that is really really helpful
when it comes to journaling is having
the right prompts or questions and so in
this video I want to share 10 of my
favorite questions 10 powerful
journaling prompts that I found enormous
value in that I hope you will find Value
in as well all right question number one
is what would you do if money were no
object now this question is so
incredibly powerful and I ask myself it
at like like every every 3 months
because it's one of those things that
like there's so much stuff that we do
for the sake of money there is so much
stuff that we do chasing like oh I need
more money I need more Financial
Security I need more financial safety
all this scarcity all all of this stuff
and it's really useful to ask the
question what would I do what would I
genuinely do if money were No Object now
if you're a noob at this you will your
answer will be oh I would just like sip
cocktails on a beach in Thailand and
just chill uh but if you've tried to do
that I've tried to do that uh and I've
realized it's not particularly enjoyable
and everyone I've ever spoken to who has
made load and load of money who has then
just retired has been absolutely
miserable because actually work is
profoundly meaningful if you're doing
something that you enjoy so there's a
sort of followup to this question which
is sort of question 1B which is if I had
all the time and money in the world how
would I use my talents to serve other
people and this is also a really really
really good good follow-up question
because it takes care of the money thing
it takes care of I don't have time thing
and it specifically asks about talents
and about service and a big part of what
makes life feel meaningful is when we
are doing things that we are good at
when we're using our strengths and when
we are doing something to serve other
people so if you had all the time and
money in the world how would you use
your talents to serve others these days
I I have a lot of like lunches and
dinners and stuff with entrepreneurs and
creators and sometimes students as well
people seem to look at me as some sort
of life coach or something it's like hey
Olie what should I do with my life and
often this is the first question I'd be
like hm what would you do if money were
no object and if they need a little bit
of prompting I will ask
if you had all the time and money in the
world how would you use your talents to
serve others for me personally asking
the question what would I do if money
were no object has led to a lot of
decisions that I've made for my YouTube
channel and for my business if money
were No Object I would still continue to
write books by the way you should check
out my book if you haven't yet link down
below and if you have I would really
love an Amazon review feel good
productivity it's about how to do more
of what matters to you in a way that
actually feels good but if I had all the
money in the world honestly I would
write more books cuz writing books is
cool I would continue making YouTube
videos I wouldn't do it on a schedule I
would I wouldn't have sponsored videos
but I would do it on my own terms I
would still do YouTu videos I would love
to be able to do workshops and seminars
and stuff where I teach other people
about productivity and like aligning
your actions with the life you want and
how to reach Financial Freedom and so
really for me I realized after doing a
lot of the these journaling prompts the
main thing I wanted to do with my life
was to be a teacher and that is what
ultimately led to me deciding to quit
medicine cuz I realized the thing that I
would do to serve others is not practice
medicine it's to teach and so that one
question has single-handedly changed the
trajectory of my life question number
two is what would you like people to say
at your funeral and here you can think
of family you can think of friends you
can think of co-workers and you can
think of people whose life has been
impacted by your work now generally
family and friends and co-workers even
are going to comment on like the
personality traits and like how much of
a nice person you were and all that kind
of stuff uh but someone whose life has
been impacted by your work is going to
comment on the unsurprisingly the impact
that your work had on their life so if I
think about it for myself I'd want my
family friends and co-workers to say I
was Broly a nice guy very you know I was
humble I was always there for them I was
present I didn't let success and stuff
get to my head all that kind of personal
stuff but I would want someone let's say
you're watching this and you might be
one of the people who's followed my
YouTube channel for a while or read my
book or listen to my podcast and if you
were to come to my funeral and my and
your life has genuinely been impacted by
my work what I'd love for you to say is
something like Ali's content really
inspired me and educated me and changed
the way that I feel and that I think
about what to do with my life and my
career because of Ali's content I
realized I was following a path that had
been chosen for me not a path that I
chosen myself and his content gave me
the courage confidence and motivation
and inspiration and stuff that I needed
to change the trajectory of my life to
me that is that would be absolutely
freaking sick if that's what people said
at my funeral people whose work people
whose lives have been impacted by my
work and so doing that journaling prompt
and knowing that that's what I'm going
for gives me a very clear North Star it
gives me a sense of like okay this is
the point this is the point of sitting
down here and setting up the cameras and
the lights and and like talking to
a camera when you can have that level of
clarity about the reason why you're
doing your work it makes everything feel
much more fun it makes everything feel
much more meaningful and purposeful and
it helps sustain you through the moments
of kind of where you don't feel like it
or where you're like tired and you know
you want to do the thing connecting to
that Spirit of service really helps the
personal side is also quite important
I've sort of brushed over that but like
it's it's really like the personal side
is really important what sort of spouse
do you want to be what sort of parent do
you want to be what sort of child do you
want to be what sort of colleague do you
want to be the things that these people
who who love us and who work with us
will comment on is is not like hey he
drove 8% returns for our hedge fund like
no one cares no one cares about your
performance they care about how you made
them feel they care they care about how
you showed up and so often I'll think
like what would I want my family to say
at my funeral what would I want my
friends to say at my funeral and then I
will ask myself the follow-up question
to what extent am I actually living in
alignment with that and usually when I
ask that question I realize ooh actually
I have been overemphasizing work at the
expense of relationships uh-oh let me
arrange a holiday or a hangout or a
dinner or whatever with some friends let
me arrange to see my family a little bit
more like usually for me the inertia is
kind of in work because it's fun and
it's meaningful it's like all that all
that stuff and I know that like okay I
actually haven't been showing up as the
sort of family member or as the friend
that I would like to be showing up as
therefore I can make a change and really
the whole point of journaling prompts is
not that it's like sort of Naval gazing
that you just do for the sake of it the
whole point of like these sort of
questions and these sort of prompts is
that they encourage you to take action
and to tweak your course in some way or
another another maybe you do the what
what would I do if money were an object
and you realize crap I'm in the wrong
career let me make a change that's very
useful maybe you do the what would I
want people to say at my funeral and
you're like crap I haven't been a great
friend recently let me make a change and
nudge myself in that direction okay so
one of the biggest tangible benefits
that all of this journaling has had in
my life is that it has allowed me to
make lots and lots of money running this
business and a lot of the decisions that
I've made to grow my business have
directly come as a result of journaling
but let's say you were to decide to
start or grow a business based on your
journaling practices now you have all
the spare money that has to go somewhere
well that's why the sponsor of this
video comes in and that is trading 212
trading 212 is a fantastic app that I
personally use that lets you invest in
stocks and shares in a commission free
fashion they've got a new feature that
gives you 1% cash back which will be
allocated to your investment account for
each deposit that you make in your Isa
if you are in the UK for example so for
any money you do deposit into your Isa
you will get 1% back on that money
completely for free they also have a new
debit card that helps you save and
invest your money automatically it's
designed to seamlessly integrate with
your trading 212 invest account and lets
you earn interest on your invested cash
in 13 different currencies the card is
also free and there are no sneaky fees
or subscription plans to worry about if
any of that signs up your street then
hit the link in the video description
and that will take you to this page
where you'll be guided on how to set up
an account and if you use that link you
will also get a completely free share up
to the value of £100 it's free money you
might as well so thank you so much
trading 212 for sponsoring this video
okay the next question it comes from my
friend Dicky Bush and the question is
something to the effect of if I were to
repeat the things I've done this week
for the next 10 years where will I end
up and is this where I want to end up
and I think this is incredibly powerful
you can do this at the level of day you
can do that if I were to repeat my
actions today for the next 10 years
where would to end up I personally like
to do it in a week because like today
kind of varies depending on if I happen
to have zoom meetings all day today it's
like that might not be representative of
a week but I think a one week long
period is like a pretty good sense of
like that is like the formula that
you're following for your life so last
week what did I do well I went to the
gym four times yeah that's pretty good
um I probably spent too much time in
meetings last week okay that would
result in me spending loads and loads of
times a meeting 10 years from now that
would compound in a negative way and
that's not what I want with my life
maybe I spent a little bit too long
playing Bower's gate all all of last
Saturday okay I probably don't want to
repeat that every single week for the
next 10 years you know I did two date
nights yep that's a good amount I saw my
friends twice saw my family once yeah
that seems pretty reasonable and it's
like you can really take an audit of
your life if you were to imagine the
last 7 Days repeated every single week
for the next 10 years because everything
in life comes as a result of compounding
you're either compounding positively or
you're compounding negatively I've
decided that it's actually be helpful
for me if I go to the gym at 8:00 every
single morning great that's going to
compound in a positive direction in
terms of my health whereas in the past
when I went to the gym maybe like once a
week or like never and asking this
question of like will these actions
compound me positively or negatively
again help me realize oh crap health is
not on track let's make a change again
this is all about deciding what changes
you want to make to your life and if you
can figure out this sort of Ideal week
for yourself what does the week look
like a 7-Day period where if you were to
just repeat that every day for the next
10 years you would end up in a pretty
good place again it's not to say you
going to be wedded to that it's not to
say that it's completely set in stone
but it's a helpful way of thinking
because it helps us realize that we're
playing long-term games here and it's so
easy to make short-term decisions at the
expense of the long-term game it's so
easy to say h you know what just for
this week work is super busy and
therefore I'm going to skip all these
workouts or work is super busy therefore
I'm going to skip my date nights or or
I'm not going to see my friends or I'm
not going to sleep enough but all of
these decisions compound over the long
term so I really love this idea of copy
and paste this week extend it out for
the next 10 years see what happens is it
good is it bad whatever you decide
whatever you learn from this you can
decide what changes you want to make all
right question number four I also have a
list of like hundreds and hundreds of
Jour prompts which are linked down below
completely for free I've got a
journaling Hub where it's like a oce
page that I keep updated with my
favorite journaling prompts but what
have I done in the last 2 weeks that has
energized me and what have I done in the
last 2 weeks that has drained my energy
this is the energy audit and you don't
even need to write it out what you can
do is you can look on your calendar cuz
hopefully you're living life by your
calendar so you can flick for the last
two weeks and you can see you can kind
of color code your calendar events or
you can even rename your calendar events
with a plus or a plus plus if it gave
you energy or a minus and a minus minus
if it drained you energy and sort of a
plus minus if it was kind of neutral
this is something I got from uh
Professor Grace Len's book uh think big
take small steps really good book and
we've also got an interview with her on
my podcast Deep dive linked up there and
somewhere but this is great this is the
energy audit because again how we spend
our time how we spend our weeks is how
we spend our lives and if we can figure
out what are the things we're doing that
are draining our energy and what are the
things we're doing that energize us a we
can figure out how do I do more of the
things that energize me and less of the
things that drain me but B we all
obviously have to do things that we
don't want to do and sometimes those
things are going to drain our energy and
so we can follow the principles and feel
good productivity for example the 3ps
play power and people and you can try
and find ways to make the things that
you are doing that are currently
draining you can find ways to turn those
into a source of energy rather than a
drain in energy it would be so sick if
everything on your calendar was a net
gain in energy rather than a net loss of
energy and again it just encourages us
to see what are the changes we might
want to make to our lives all right
question number five is the wheel of
life this is something I've talked about
a fair bit so if you're already familiar
with this feel free to skip ahead in the
video but it might be worth doing
basically the idea is that we split up
life into three different components
work health and relationships now within
Health we've got physical mental and
spiritual or body mind and soul whatever
that means for you within relationships
we've got romance family and friends and
within work we've got Mission money and
growth I'd like to have a 10th category
called joy and the idea for this
question is in each of these different
categories how aligned are my current
actions with the future that I want how
aligned is my current actions in
physical health with the future that I
want how aligned are my current actions
in Joy or in romantic relationships with
the future that I want if you do this
exercise enough times you'll you can
draw it as a little circle you can turn
it into a graph you can track the
changes in your Wheel of Life over time
um I've got a bunch of friends and team
members who are super into this stuff
and so if for example I was hanging out
with Tintin earlier today one of my team
members hadn't seen hadn't seen him in a
while and instead of being like how's it
going I was like how's the Wheel of Life
and he gets it because he's been doing
The Wheel of Life every Sunday for the
last like several years and he was like
huh actually the wheel of life is pretty
good I realized you know I'm actually
maybe a little bit negative in this this
and this area but actually broadly
things are good it's a nice holistic
kind of Life assessment and again the
point of asking yourself this question
is that you can identify areas for
improvement like right now if I were to
run the Wheel of Life on myself I would
say my joy category is probably a 6 out
of 10 and so I'd like to make more time
for Joy which is why I'm considering
buying a PS5 for whatever that's worth
um and I would say my spiritual health
my soul category is also probably like a
four out of 10 because I haven't really
done any meditation I haven't really
been particularly mindful recently it's
like by just asking myself the questions
I'm already able to come up with some
action points which again to reiterate
is the whole point of these different
journaling prompts question number six
is the Odyssey plan this is three sets
of questions the first one is your
current path the question is what does
my life look like 5 years from now if I
continue down my current path next
question is the alternative path what
would my life look like 5 years from now
if I took a completely different path
and then option three is the radical
path what would my life look like 5
years from now if I took a completely
different path where I didn't care about
money and I didn't care about what
people thought I talked about this a
bunch of times in the channel before
this is probably the journaling the
journaling prompt that's most
single-handedly changed my life I first
did this in late 2019 and doing this
Odyssey plan made me realize oh crap 5
years from now the medical career that
I'm in is not actually the career I want
to be in that was super interesting
caused me to make immediate changes to
my life and caused me to end up here
making YouTube videos and writing books
for a living rather than being a doctor
so I think it's incredibly incredibly
powerful it does take some time to do it
takes some time to think about but it
gives a lot of clarity on like what are
the options and sometimes you might even
realize that like oh I just I've got a
bit of a failure of imagination like i'
I'm sort of imagining that I have to go
down this particular path but now that
I've written out my alternative path and
my radical path my alternative path
might be to become a music composer and
sing a songwriter and my radical path
might be to I don't know van life around
the world for the next 10 years and be a
photographer or something like that
there is this really cool image um from
Tim Urban's blog it basically shows that
like our life has could have taken a
bunch of different paths but we took one
path to end up here but where we are now
our life can still take an absolute
multitude of other paths but it's so
easy to think and be blinkered by the
fact that like oh well I guess I did a
degree in economics I guess I have to
become a banker or I guess I did a
degree in medicine I have to become a
doctor and so to confine ourselves to a
path that is not actually the path we
necessarily need to be on and so the
point of the Odyssey plan and these
other sorts of sorts of journaling
prompts is that they help us realize
that actually you've got way more
control and you have way more options
available to you than you might think
and so to me every few years I will
actually every year when I do my annual
review I will just redo my Odyssey plan
just to make sure that I'm thinking big
and I'm not allowing the inertia of my
existing path to keep me on the road of
content creator or whatever the thing
might be all right question number seven
is incredibly powerful
what is the goal and what is the
bottleneck I find myself asking myself
this question a lot I also ask it a lot
to people when I do these sort of pseudo
life coaching and business coaching
sessions with other creators and
entrepreneurs and stuff what's the goal
and what's the bottleneck the first half
of that question is incredibly valuable
what's the goal if you are struggling
with absolutely anything if you feel
like you're torn in multiple directions
and and stuff you feel like you might be
in a transition period of your life
right now I suspect if you're watching
this channel ask yourself what's the
goal what am I really optimizing for and
so often we get embroiled in our
problems and we don't remember to ask
ourselves what is the goal cuz the goal
changes everything I was at a a writer's
Retreat the other day we had this little
like hot seat session where the idea is
that you get you're in the hot seat for
45 minutes and you discuss your problems
or your challenges and then everyone
gives you advice and asks you questions
and one thing we realized is that
basically all of us go in the hot seat
and we were describing like a problem
that we were having and someone in the
group would ask what's the
goal and and then the person in the hot
seat was like hm I guess the goal is I
want to get my business to $10 million
okay cool what's the bottleneck I.E what
is the what is the one thing that's most
stopping you from getting there we don't
have enough products to sell cool we can
solve the bottleneck I guess the goal is
to really enjoy my work life okay what's
the bottleneck what's stopping you from
doing that right now well I guess I've
actually been spending a lot of my time
chasing money rather than chasing
passion huh that's interesting what's
the goal and what's the bottleneck is
often like a question that cuts to the
heart of anything that we're struggling
with and so it's a question I ask myself
a lot when I'm doing my own journaling
and it's a question I love to ask other
people because it just encourages us to
think in a way that we might not
otherwise all right question number
eight is actually a journaling prompt
that I got from Brian Tracy Brian Tracy
is like this old dude who's written a
bunch of really good books about goal
setting and productivity and there was a
good YouTube short from a clip of his
that I came across a few months ago take
a clean sheet of paper and write down
goals in today's State and then write
down 10 goals that you would like to
accomplish in in the next 12 months and
write them in the present tense I earn I
achieve I weigh I drive such and such a
car I own and then you take this list of
10 and you say if I had a magic wand and
I could wave this magic wand and I could
have any one goal on my list within 24
hours which one goal would have the
greatest positive impact on my life and
usually this will jump out at you put a
circle around that goal and that's a
goal you transfer to a clean sheet of
paper and then you follow the seven
steps write it down set a deadline make
a list of everything you have to do to
accomplish it organize the list into a
checklist take action and then do
something every day if you'll just do
this nothing can stop you but yourself
so for me at the start of the year when
I I led like an annual planning session
for like 12,000 people in my audience it
if you joined it then welcome back uh
this was the sort of idea that I used to
land on my own goals for the year for me
I've got like three main goals work
health and relationships my work goal is
to get our business from 5 million to
$10 million in Revenue for whatever
that's worth uh my health goal is to get
into the best shape of my life and
actually over the last two months 3
months I have gotten into the best shape
of my life like I'm in better shape than
I've ever been in terms of muscle mass
and in terms of General activity levels
and so I've got another 9 months to bulk
a bit more then do some cutting then
think about flexibility and Mobility but
all of this is for the goal of getting
to the best shape of my life which I
realized was a really important thing
for me on the health front and then on
the relationships front got a couple of
goals one of them is secret but the
other one is to host six mini Adventures
for friends and family and that's
something that I'm working on this here
cuz I think it would be cool all right
question number nine this applies to
entrepreneurs uh and the question is do
you work for your business or does your
business work for you I first came
across this question about a year ago at
a entrepreneurs Retreat that I was in in
California of all places um and that
question just sort of hit me like a
baseball bat to the face do you work for
your business or does your business work
for you I L at the time oh crap my
business doesn't work for me I work for
it like I'm an employee of my business
like my business is the the prison that
I've created for myself and I'm a slave
to that prison okay cool now that I know
that let's change things up I want my
business to work for me rather than for
me to work for my business I want to
make videos on my own terms I want to do
stuff that I want to do I want to sort
of I wanted to feel purposeful and
spirit of service and all that kind of
stuff but that question caused me to
make a lot of changes in my business and
therefore by extension my life and now
I'm in a way less stressful place than I
was this time last year I'm way more
chill I enjoy the business a lot more I
feel much more confident about our
future as a business and finances and
stuff and I feel much much more aligned
with the stuff that I'm creating and the
content I'm making this is a pretty fun
video for me to make I freaking love
these journaling prompts I love these
questions but a year ago I would have
been like no but like the titles are not
clickbaity enough and like uh not sure
anyone cares about journaling and like
we don't have any products about
journaling so why would I make the video
but now I'm just like I just want to
make videos that I think would be just
useful to people watching them because
the North Star is if you visit me at my
funeral uh I want you to I would love
for you to say that something about my
content my books my YouTube videos my
podcast whatever thing might be
something about that content helped
change the trajectory of your life and
so if even one of these journaling
prompts that I've given you out of the
10 in this video helps you make an
action or make a decision that causes
you to take action that causes you to
change your life that's pretty cool
that's what I'm here for and then
finally question number 10 if I knew I
was going to die 2 years from now how
would I spend my time now this is sort
of a variation of like if you knew you
were going to die tomorrow how would you
spend your time but generally if you
knew you were going to die tomorrow
you'd probably do very destructive
things things but if I knew I was going
to die 2 years from now what would I do
I wouldn't just stop working because I
really enjoy my work and find it
meaningful um I'd probably play more
video games which reminds me I should
probably get that PS5 and plug it into
that TV I would probably see my grandma
more she's in Pakistan at the moment so
probably fly to Pakistan and just chill
with my grandma a bit I would probably
host more dinners with friends H what
are the things I would do if I knew I
was going to die 2 years from now and
then why am I not just doing those
things now obviously that's what the
question is implying I do like to change
of the time timeline sometimes sometimes
I think okay if I knew I was going to
die 10 years from now what would I be
doing if I knew I was going to die two
years from now I probably wouldn't write
another book because it take took three
three and a half years to write this
freaking thing but if I knew I was going
to die 10 years from now I might
actually think you know what I think it
would be really nice to work on two
books during that time during for the
next 10 years so really the time Horizon
does sort of dictate what projects you
want to work on but again the point of
this stuff is not that you become wedded
to the thing that you said in the
journaling prompt it just gives you
ideas so yeah if I knew I was going to
die 2 years from now or 5 years from now
10 years whatever the thing might be how
would I spend my time and what of those
things can I just do now so that brings
us to the end of these 10 powerful
questions that have personally had a
massive impact on my life if you're
interested in a more in-depth guide to
exactly how to journal with like
expressive writing and morning pages and
different journaling techniques check
out this video over here that I've done
a few months ago about how to journal to
change your life otherwise thank you so
much for watching I hope you took
something from this video and I would
love it if you could leave a comment
down below which of these is your
favorite question or if you're a
journaler yourself what is your favorite
journaling prompt I would love for you
to leave that down below we can compile
them and put it out as a community post
or something anyway check out this video
over here for the ultimate guided
journaling thank you so much for
watching and I will see you in the next
video bye-bye