hey friends welcome back to the channel
so we often think that the opposite of
distraction is focus but this isn't
actually true the opposite of
distraction is traction and what's
really cool about these two words is
that they both end in the same six
letters which means that distraction is
any action that pulls you away from your
goals and traction is any action that
pulls you towards your goals now this is
something I came across when I first
read The Incredible Book indestructible
by near I've taken a lot of advice from
that book myself personally and I
recently had a wonderful conversation
with near all about how to become
indestructible so we constantly lie to
ourselves and what that means is that we
look back on our lives and we are full
of regret we said we should have done
that thing we should have started the
business we should have written the book
we should have started the podcast we
should have started youtubing whatever
the case might be but we didn't do it we
got distracted so being indistractable
is about doing what you say you're going
to do n is in his 40s now and he's in an
amazing shape with six-pack apps he's
got a great family he thinks very
intentionally about what he wants in his
life but it actually took near 5 years
to write the book because ironically he
kept on getting distracted so partly he
wrote the book to find out for himself
how he could become IND distractible
both when doing day-to-day tasks and
also on big long-term projects and in
this video we're going to be breaking
down the four key elements of the
indistractable model which is all about
doing more traction and less distraction
perhaps unsurprisingly principle number
one the 10minute rule so a lot of us
think that the reason why we're so
distracted is because of our phones and
emails and work and kids and all of
those things around us but according to
ne's research this is actually a myth
because external triggers only account
for around 10% of our distractions
instead 90% of our distraction is caused
by internal triggers what are internal
triggers internal triggers are
uncomfortable emotional states that we
seek to escape boredom loneliness
fatigue uncertainty anxiety these are
these uncomfortable Sensations that we
look to escape many times with
distraction so the research shows that
we are more motivated to avoid pain than
we are to seek pleasure this is
something called prospect theory and it
explains why you care more about not
losing $100 than you do about winning
$100 rationally it's the same thing you
either win 100 or you don't lose 100 but
there's something about losing stuff
experiencing that pain that makes us
feel very motivated to avoid that so
like what n said internal triggers are
uncomfortable emotional states that we
are trying to avoid and so if we want to
become indistractable we need to get way
better at taking control of our internal
triggers and there are loads of
techniques that NE talks about in his
book about this but one of the key ones
is that 10-minute rule the 10-minute
rule says that you can give in to any
distraction whatever that distraction
might be whether you're on a diet and
you're trying to resist that chocolate
cake whether you're trying to quit
smoking whether you're trying to not
check your phone every 5 minutes when
you're trying to be with your family or
do a work project you can give into that
distraction but not right now in 10
minutes and if 10 minutes is too long
make it the 5minute rule it doesn't
really matter so next time you feel
distracted try procrastinating from that
distraction for just 10 minutes now in
those 10 minutes you can do a couple of
things you can firstly choose to get
back to whatever you were doing before
you got distracted or alternatively you
can use that time to surf the urge and
this is where we acknowledge that
emotions come in waves and you sort of
explore why that feeling came about in
the first place and a key action point
here is to create what NE calls a
distraction notebook so most people have
no sense of why they got distracted they
all of a sudden find the cigarettes in
their hand they all of a sudden find the
phone you know they're scrolling on Tik
Tok or whatever without realizing what
was the preceding internal trigger so a
distraction notebook is a way for you to
start bringing awareness to what is that
preceding emotion that you are trying to
escape he recommends actually doing this
on pen and paper or keeping it written
down somewhere rather than just doing in
your head but you can do it in your head
if you want basically it's a good way to
keep track of those internal triggers
that cause you to become distracted and
then obviously you can put steps in
place to avoid that thing distracting
you again in the future hopefully now in
the rest of this video we're going to
talk about three other things but if
you're the sort of person who gets
distracted you're also probably the sort
of person who's not going to watch the
rest of this video so I'm telling you
now if you just take one thing away from
this video it is to recog ize that
practically all of the time 90% of the
time when you're getting distracted it's
because there is some kind of emotional
state that you are trying to avoid and
just having that knowledge that
appreciation that you are a little
and no not that and just having that
knowledge and just having that knowledge
can help you actually figure out okay
what's the source of that emotion why is
that emotion happening what's the
narrative you're telling yourself about
the emotion feelings are not facts as
various people on the internet famously
say which is kind of true feelings are
not facts the feeling is caused by some
kind of internal sensation and then
you're telling yourself some sort of
narrative or some sort of story which is
then precipitating that specific feeling
and that negative emotion is the thing
that you're trying to avoid when you get
distracted so if you just remember that
feel free to click off this video scroll
Tik Tok instead but if that's a thing
that you take away from this video this
video will have been totally worth it
but okay if you're still with me then we
know that internal triggers are not 100%
of the problem there is another 10% and
if we want to solve the other 10% of
distraction then we've got to think
about two other causes of distraction
that is firstly planning problems and
secondly external triggers oh and by the
way if you are enjoying this video then
you might like to check out brilliant
who are very kindly sponsoring this
video brilliant is a fantastic online
education platform where you learn by
doing not just by consuming and they've
got thousands of interactive lessons in
maths and data analysis programming and
even AI I've personally been learning
stuff on brilliant for the last 5 years
and I've gotten a lot of value from it
in helping me understand various things
around Ai and programming and crypto and
I've even had people in my audience in
that time who have said that they
started using brilliant on the various
recommendations that I that I give for
it and they've gotten value out of it as
well they've got a really good first
principles approach to learning which
helps you build understanding from the
ground up and it's all crafted by an
award-winning team of teachers and
researchers and professionals from cool
places like MIT Caltech Microsoft Google
and many more places and really
brilliant helps you build critical
thinking skills through problem solving
rather than through memorizing things
which is traditionally how we're taught
to do stuff in school so while you're
building real knowledge on specific
topics you're also becoming a better
thinker and in just a few minutes each
day which can replace some of the
minutes you spend mindlessly scrolling
brilliant can help you build genuine
Real World Knowledge the growing number
of courses on programming are
particularly good and those can help you
get familiar for example with python
which is the world's most popular
programming language and you can start
building programs on day one with their
built-in drag and drop editor if any of
that sounds interesting and you'd like
to try out everything brilliant has to
offer completely for free for a full 30
days head over to brilliant.org Al adal
or you can scan or screenshot the QR
code on screen or you can click on the
link in the video description and if you
sign up for brilliant using any of these
mechanisms you'll also get 20% off the
annual premium subscription so thank you
so much brilliant for spons answering
this video principle number two The
Willpower myth okay so aside from all of
these internal triggers there are lots
of other external triggers that also
pull us away from traction like phones
and computers and TV shows and work
emails and meetings and the whole Shang
and I've made a bunch of videos
specifically on how to deal with some of
these external triggers like phone
addiction and stuff but one of the
really interesting things that n and I
talked about was willpower and whether
or not willpower is really something
that runs out towards the end of the day
like some people think it does so there
is this popular notion
that willpower is a limited resource and
this came out of some research uh done
several years ago now uh around this
concept called ego depletion ego
depletion says that we run out of
willpower just like we would run out of
battery charge on our phone or gas in
our gas tank that it's a depletable
resource and this got a lot of of of
press because it's kind of a concept
people want to believe this original
study on ego depletion was published in
1998 by a psychologist called Roy
balister and a lot of people subscribe
to this idea of willpower being a
limited resource because it's a
comforting thought it allows us to say
that oh man I I'm just so tired by the
end of the day my willpower has run out
I get so drained at work by my boss or
by life or by circumstances or by the
weather or by whatever my willpower has
run out and so I have to watch Netflix
in the evening it's not my fault that
I'm not actually making progress on my
goals and instead I'm just scrolling Tik
Tok and Instagram and all that kind of
stuff it's not my fault it's that my
willpower has run out but it turns out
actually that the results from this
original 1998 study have been totally
debunked turns out
this idea of ego depletion that we run
out of willpower like gas in a gas tank
turns out not to be true except in one
group of people there is actually one
group of people who really do run out of
willpower they really do spend it up and
those people and only those people and
this work was done by Carol DW I'm sure
you know her work uh her wonderful book
uh called mindset and she found that the
only group of people who run out of
willpower are people who believe that
willpower is a depletable resource so if
you think that you run out of willpower
by the end of the day then your body and
mind will behave in that way if you just
choose to believe that willpower is not
a depletable resource and actually you
can always muster up willp power and
discipline whenever you feel like it
then it's not really going to become a
problem the word Addiction comes from
the Latin addico which means slave So
when you say to yourself I am a slave I
am addicted I have no more willpower I'm
spent you're making it true and so we
have to be very very careful about these
labels and make sure that we only adopt
the labels that serve us rather than the
ones that hurt us by the way if you are
enjoying this video then you might like
to check out my completely free 7-Day
Focus crash course it's completely free
and it's a series of seven emails that
I'll send you each day that each have
some evidence-based principles
strategies and tools that you can use to
improve your focus as well and the
reason we've put that together is
because whenever I pull the audience and
ask like what are you guys struggling
with focus and like consistency seems to
be the the highest thing on that list
basically all the time and so we thought
you know what let's just turn into a bit
of an email course cuz there is so much
to share and so many strategies that are
really helpful when it comes to focus so
if you're interested it's completely
free you can sign up you can unsubscribe
whenever you want head over to focus
crashcourse tocom or hit the link in the
video description all right principle
number three is traction time boxing
everything is a distraction unless you
plan your time so unlike a to-do list
which is just a register of things you
want to have done when you time box and
I didn't make up this technique it's
been around for a long time it's called
setting an implementation intention it's
the most widely studied technique that
far too too few people use it's
basically saying here's what I'm going
to do and when I'm going to do it okay
so the issue with to-do lists is that
when you write a to-do list and then you
tick things off one by one then you
can't plan firstly how much time it will
take you to complete the task and
secondly how much attention you actually
need for the task but the idea of
traction time boxing is that it lets you
track both of these inputs because
traction time boxing is basically a
fancy way of describing putting stuff in
your calendar and like actually doing it
I discovered this when I was at
University and I realized that I sucked
at managing my time and then I started
using a calendar and actually just time
boxing things and actually trying to
plan my week at the start of the week
and figuring out okay when do I need to
allocate time for my essays when I'm
going to work on my side hustle business
that's going to go in the calendar and
that just helped me really become way
more effective with how I use my time
and it wasn't that I was sort of
planning every single moment of the day
because I also had a very social life at
Uni and hung out with friends playing
board games until 4 in the morning way
too often but it let me sort of Juggle
all these different things and it's
still just amazes me how few people
actually use a calendar when people get
into the professional workplace everyone
has to use a calendar cuz it's how me
are organized and stuff but using a
calendar for your personal life as well
and also using a calendar for any side
hustle type goals that you want to work
towards whether that's starting a
YouTube channel or a business or even
just I don't know watching the top 50
movies in IMDb actually just putting
those into your calendar and time boxing
it really helps you make the most out of
your time and so when you budget those
things your time and attention the new
metric isn't did I finish the new metric
is did I do what I said I was going to
do for as long as I said I would without
distraction whether that's being with my
family whether that's playing video
games whether that's working on a big
project did I do what I said I was going
to do for as long as I said I would
without distraction because that is the
only way to have a feedback loop now
over time you get better at estimating
how much time and attention these
different things in your calendar need
and that way you can keep on improving
at it over time but the most important
takeaway is that everything in your
calendar should ideally be traction so
actions that pull you toward words your
goals rather than distraction now
sometimes people don't like this
sometimes people like will say that well
if you time block everything then that's
like toxic productivity and like where's
the spontaneity and where's the fun and
I'm like no that's not how it works you
can absolutely timebox your evenings for
example to be fully present with your
partner you can time boox a whole
Wednesday evening for like a solo
relaxation evening which is what I do on
Wednesday evenings I don't care what
your goals are the thing that I care
about that I would love to happen is
that you use your time which is the
single most valuable non-renewable
resource that we have you use that time
towards things that you actually care
about doing you don't use that time
ideally just scrolling a random app
based on what the like Engineers who get
paid stupid amounts of money at Facebook
and at Tik Tok and at Instagram and
stuff instead of letting them decide
what you're doing with your most
valuable asset on this planet you decide
yourself what you'd like to do with your
most valuable asset on this planet I.E
your time and if that means being on Tik
Tok and chilling out watching Netflix
watching Disney plus whatever you want
great fantastic as long as you have made
that decision then I'm happy cool
principle number four the rule of pcts
okay so there are three types of pcts
that we can use to help become more
indestructible price effort and identity
so firstly price packs involve money now
this part of the conversation near told
me about his burn or burn technique when
it came to working out now near used to
be pretty overweight and now he's become
absolutely ripped and apparently the way
he did this was that he taped a $100
note to his mirror and when he looked at
that mirror every single day he made a
decision I can either burn some calories
by doing some push-ups going for a walk
around the block going for a swim doing
some kind of exercise every day to burn
calories or I have to burn the $100 bill
and to this day near has never broken
this price packed and he actually even
did the same thing when writing the book
IND distractable if he didn't write the
book by a certain date then he owed
someone $20,000 but of course he managed
to write the book and so he never
actually had to pay the money okay
secondly we have effort packs which is
where you put a bit of friction between
you and the distraction so for example
near has set it so that his internet
automatically turns off at 1000 p.m.
every single day yeah he could always go
and turn the router back on and like
unplug the Amazon Alexa switch or
whatever the thing is that's turning it
off but that would take effort to do and
he has to really think about it and then
he has to really think about whether he
actually wants to use the internet after
10 p.m. this is the same reason why I've
installed an app called opal which is
very good and I set it so that it blocks
all social media apps after 10 p.m. and
before 9:00 a.m. so when it gets to
night time and I'm sitting on the toilet
scrolling through my phone and I'm like
huh you know what I'm just habitually
going to go on Instagram reals I can't
because Instagram is blocked and I think
well what if I just watch a YouTube
video and I can't because YouTube is
blocked as well and then sometimes I
think you know I should have Instagram
unblocked because I need obviously need
to post an Instagram story at 11:30 p.m.
and then I go on opal and then you know
you can always unblock the apps but you
have to wait like 30 seconds and in that
30 seconds I'm like do I really need to
post this Instagram story at 11:30 well
why don't I just go to sleep I can wake
up early I can have a nice morning I'll
be a bit more refreshed and energized
and stuff and so I end up not going on
social media anywhere near as much as I
used to because I've now set this app to
automatically block of these offending
apps between 10: p.m. and 9:00 a.m. and
I'd recommend you do it as well there's
literally no reason to ever allow
yourself to even click on a social media
app when it's nighttime and your primary
goal is to sleep hopefully and then
thirdly we have identity packs now if
you give yourself an identity you are
much more likely to actually do
something so using that technique to our
advantage by actually having a moniker
by having an identity this is why the
book is called indistractable
indistractable is meant to sound like
indestructible it's who you are so when
you have that this this identity makes
you much more likely to follow through
this comes from the psychology of
religion in fact that when someone calls
themselves uh a member of a particular
Faith they're much more likely to to act
in accordance and reinforcing this
identity of being indestructible this
can be your superpower now there's
something really cool that I heard from
Tony Robbins a few years ago which is
that the strongest force in human
personality is the need to stay
consistent with how we think of
ourselves so if you define yourself or
if your identity is that of someone who
procrastinates or I'm I'm a
procrastinator then you're going to
continue being a procrastinator if your
identity is oh I'm a gamer and I have to
get through school on the side then
you're going to struggle to ever do your
work if your identity is that of a
writer you are much more likely to write
if your identity is that of a YouTuber
you much more likely to create videos if
your identity is that of a healthy
person you're going to go to the gym but
if your identity is that of someone who
really struggles to go to the gym or to
stay in good shape and work out and
stuff you're going to struggle with that
this is also something James Clear talks
about in atomic habits identity-based
Behavior change is a lot easier than
focusing on the tactics it's much easier
when you can make your habits consistent
with the identity that you want to have
and actually like s up yourself into
actually having that identity okay so
those were the four elements of n's
indistractable model you should totally
check out the book it is really good but
if you're maybe struggling with some of
these external triggers like spending a
lot of time on your phone then you might
like to check out this video here where
I've made a video specifically targeting
phone addiction so thank you so much for
watching hope you enjoyed the video and
hopefully I'll see you in the next one
bye-bye