in this video we're going to be talking
about how I focus for Peak productivity
using my deep work system so we're going
to start off by talking about the
philosophy of deep work and why it is
particularly important and why building
your own deep work system will
completely change your life and then I'm
going to go over my personal fairly
simple four-step system that I've
evolved over time on how to actually
Focus if you are new to the channel
hello my name is Ali I'm a doctor turned
entrepreneur and I'm the author of The
New York Times bestseller Feelgood
productivity which is a book about how
to do more of what matters to you in a
way that actually feels good and since
2017 on this channel pretty much every
week I've been do M menting my journey
from a broke medical student to working
full-time as a doctor to now being an
entrepreneur and author and none of the
success I've ever had would have been
possible without having some sort of
deep work system to actually focus on
something for an extended period of time
so if you are in a stage of your life or
your career where you would benefit from
having more time in the day to actually
Focus then building some sort of deep
work routine or deep work system for
yourself I think will absolutely move
the needle and so I hope you enjoy this
video let's get to part one where we
start by zooming out a little
bit all right so let let's start by
defining shallow work versus deep work
so Cal Newport defines shallow work as
non-cognitively demanding logistical
style tasks often performed while
distracted these efforts tend to not
create much new value in the world and
are easy to replicate and then we have
the definition of deep work which is
professional activities performed in a
state of distraction free concentration
that push your cognitive capabilities to
their limit these efforts create new
value improve your skill and are hard to
replicate and there's a few key phrases
here so for example shallow work he's
arguing is often performed while
distracted and distracted is
unfortunately the state that most of us
find ourselves in most of the time
shallow work tends not to create much
new value and tends to be fairly easy to
replicate whereas deep work is a state
of distraction free concentration this
is often what we call Focus now
crucially deep work pushes our cognitive
capabilities to their limit I.E it is
hard it is effortful deep work does not
feel easy and deep work tends to create
new value and tends to be hard to
replicate now these definitions give us
a little bit of a hint as to why deep
work is so important if you are anything
like most people in my audience you are
somewhere along the freedom path what is
the freedom path well the freedom path
is the path from where you currently are
to a place of Freedom often defined as
Financial Freedom and time freedom and
location Freedom basically where you
have the freedom to do what you want
with who you want and have a good time
and work on your own terms and work from
anywhere and you know all of that sort
of stuff now as it relates to work there
are actually three paths I'm going to
argue that get you to this kind of dream
life Freedom me type situation you've
got path a you've got path B and you've
got path C boom boom and boom path
number one or stream number one as I
like to think of it is the career stream
stream number two is the side hustle
stream and stream number three is the
entrepreneur stream now what's
interesting about this is that all three
of these streams could take you to this
version of Freedom that you're aspiring
to where you have time Freedom Financial
Freedom location Freedom flexibility you
can do what you want that sort of stuff
but each of these three streams have
different characteristics the career
stream can get you there Tim Cook for
example the CEO of Apple has never
started his own business but he's pretty
rich and he got there by working his way
up through the ranks at IBM and then
getting hired into apple as like their
operations guy and then like working his
way up and you can get to the freedom
that you want through being an employee
through being part of a career it tends
to be slower and it tends to be less
risky and Cally there is nothing wrong
with being in the career stream if
that's what you want to do then some
people go from the career stream into
the side hustle stream where you're
trying to keep a career going at the
same time and also building some sort of
side hustle with the hope that that's
side hustle makes an extra 5K a month
10K a month eventually you know makes
enough money that you can go part-time
in your career or maybe quit the career
allog together after a while in the side
hustle stream you often when it's about
making 5 to 10K a month you could jump
to completely to the entrepreneur stream
try and build your own business etc etc
that tends to be a FAS path to the
freedom that you aspire to but it tends
to be a riskier path now in this video
we're not going to go into the
differences between these three three
streams we're going to do more videos on
that later but the crucial thing to
remember is that for all three of these
streams there is a key thing that you
have to do in order to get to this
Freedom that you want and that key thing
is two words create
value within the context of a career if
you are trying to get to Financial
Freedom there is no way you will succeed
at that unless you are creating value in
some way for Society for your employer
for your boss for your customers
whatever that might be when you start
your own side hustle when you become an
entrepreneur there is no way to actually
make money unless you are creating value
in some way because the only way to make
money is to create value and then find
other people who are willing to pay you
for for that value that you've created
oh by the way if you are interested in
sustainable routes to monetizing a side
hustle then you might like to check out
Circle who are very kindly sponsoring
this video now as a Creator one of the
most common questions I get is how to
actually earn a sustainable income
online and sure there are plenty ways of
doing this like ad revenue and
sponsorships and Affiliates and selling
much but in my experience one of the
most fulfilling ways and most
sustainable ways is by building a
community now when you set up your own
Community you basically create a
dedicated space around whatever your
passion is and that's a place where
like-minded people can come together to
learn grow and support each other and
you can and make money doing this which
is where Circle comes in I found circle
in my experience to be the absolute best
platform to create and manage your own
online community we've been using it
since 2020 for our parttime youber
Academy we're also using it for our
productivity lab and we've even migrated
all of our online courses over to Circle
so whether you're running courses or
hosting Live Events or offering premium
memberships absolutely everything is all
in one place they've now even introduced
built-in email marketing so you can grow
your audience you can nurture them over
time and you can invite them to join
your paid offerings all without juggling
a bunch of different tools the cool
thing about building a community like
this is that you can see these
connections forming amongst people
online and then those connections often
translate like for example for our
YouTuber Academy and even for
productivity lab we've hosted and our
members have also hosted in real life
events and it's all because everyone is
together on these communities hosted on
Circle if you're looking to build a
community full of people who share your
interests and you want to invest in your
content then do give Circle a try it is
quick and easy and affordable and you
can test it out completely free for 14
days using the link in the video
description if you like it Circle might
just be the next step in turning your
passion into a thriving and supportive
and potentially even profitable
community so thank you so much cirle for
sponsoring this video and let's get back
to it now coming back to our definition
of shallow work versus deep work
overlaying all of this on here shallow
work tends not to create much new value
whereas deep work tends to create new
value and so if we can create a system a
routine for being able to do more deep
work and create more value than
whichever of these three streams we
happen to find ourselves in we are going
to be working towards our goal of
Financial Freedom time Freedom location
Freedom the freedom to do whatever you
want all right now I'm going to double
click on this create value because this
is this is worth understanding this is a
video about deep work system you can
skip to the Deep workk system in the
time stamps if you really want to but my
personal recommendation would be that if
you understand the why behind this it
makes the motivation to build and
maintain your own deep workk system way
stronger because to be honest if you're
watching this channel you've probably
seen some of my videos in the past
you've probably seen some self-help
videos on YouTube you've probably tried
to solve the problem of focus and like
distraction before but unless you've had
a compelling reason to solve it unless
you understand the why behind why we are
even bothering to do this it's really
hard to sit down and just like Focus for
an extended period of time not get
distracted when amongst like Tik Tok and
Instagram and social media and all of
the other things you could be doing with
your time so that's why we are double
clicking into this stuff anyway let's
double click into the create value thing
what the hell is value okay well there's
various different ways of thinking about
this but the way I think of it is that
you take raw materials which might be
worth I don't know $1 you then do stuff
to the raw materials and then it creat
creates output which might be worth I
don't know $2 so in the process of the
stuff of doing the stuff you have
basically transmuted $1 worth of raw
materials with the stuff that you are
doing and created $2 out of it therefore
you have added $1 worth of value
crucially this output is only worth $2
if someone else is willing to pay the $2
for it and so this is not like a
subjective thing it's not like hey I've
created this piece of poetry and it's
super super valuable it's valuable in so
far as people are willing to pay for the
thing this is not the only definition of
value there are all sorts of other
definitions of value but if you're
trying to get to Financial Freedom then
we have to be creating the sort of
financial value that the market in this
capitalist world that we live in that
the market values now whatever your job
is you are probably not really
converting actual raw materials into
actual output if you're a baker for
example you are converting the raw
materials of flour and sugar and milk
and water and stuff you're doing stuff
to it and then you're transforming it
into bread which you then sell at a
bougie Bakery for like $7 a pop but I
suspect if you're watching this channel
you probably don't have a physical
manufacturing type job whether that's
what you do I suspect if you watch this
channel you are doing some sort of
knowledge work where for the most part
you probably don't have too many raw
materials for the thing that you're
doing and the key stuff that you are
doing is using your brain you are
essentially using your brain this why
it's called knowledge work you're using
your brain to your skills and your
knowledge and stuff to transmute
probably pixels on a screen into more
pixels on a screen and then you're
trying to sell those extra pixels on a
screen for something this is how
management consultants make money they
transform a blank keynote slide or
PowerPoint slide into with a bunch of
research and a bunch of knowledge work
and all this sort of stuff into a
PowerPoint presentation that they
present to a client and they charge
stupid amounts of money for it but they
have created value at least in the eyes
of the client so what does any of this
have to do with deep work well on this
Freedom path in order to get to the
freedom that we desire we need to create
value and the way that we probably you
and me create the value is by using our
brains and in order to use our brains
effectively we need the skill of deep
work or Focus where essentially we need
to sit still for an extended period of
time and we need to do cognitively
demanding things that use our brain to
try and create new value in the world
crucially this deep work and focus thing
is sort of like a muscle in that it can
be trained and you're doing it in a sort
of reflective sort of way where you can
improve the strength of that muscle over
time and improve the strength of that
system over time fundamentally what all
of that contributes to is that you are
able to create more
value in less
time that is ultimately in many ways the
definition of productivity increased
productivity is creating more value in
less time now let's imagine two
different people one person is really
good at doing deep work and really good
at focusing the other person is not very
good at doing deep work and not very
good at focusing and let's imagine that
both of these people have a day job
maybe they're working 9 to5 or whatever
and they both want to start some sort of
side hustle that makes them an extra 5
grand a month 10 grand a month so that
they can get to Financial Freedom
location Freedom time Freedom all of
that sort of stuff they're on the
freedom path both of these two people
have a job job and therefore they let's
say they only have 5 hours a week to
devote to their side hustle which of
these people do you think is going to be
quicker at getting to their goal of side
hustle making 10 grand a month obviously
is going to be the person who's going to
deep work right because the guy who
sucks at Deep work is going to get home
and is going to be super demotivated and
they're going to sit down and they're
going to have to figure out their
business plan and figure out the
business strategy and actually do the
cognitively demanding things that it
takes to get a side hustle or a business
off the ground and they're trying to do
those things and they're all over the
place they're unable to focus they're
like getting distracted they have their
phones on they're browsing Instagram
reals and trying to emails while trying
to do the work and this person is still
spending 5 hours a week on the side
Hustle but the amount of value they are
creating in that 5 hours a week is
pretty low whereas this person spends
the same 5 hours a week they're not
working anym they're not working any
harder they're just fully focused
they're like less distracted in that
time they have discovered the power of a
deep workk routine they have it
scheduled into their calendar they've
got a system that they're following they
block off whatever distractions they can
they don't allow social media and the
phone and Instagram reals and stuff to
affect them while they're in that 5
hours of deep work this person might
well be consuming TV or entertainment or
reading books and like you know having a
life and all that kind of stuff but
they're just not doing that in their 5
hours of week and yeah even though money
is not everything money is like a pretty
important thing if you're trying to get
to the goal of Financial Freedom or even
Financial Security like for some people
the goal of Financial Freedom is I just
want to be free from the stress of
paying the mortgage for some people it's
I want to be a Dubai boy and have a
yacht and all that kind of stuff but
whatever the thing is like this person
is creating way more value in those 5
hours than the person who sucks at doing
deep work and so coming back to our
freedom path figure figuring out some
sort of deep workk system whether you
use mine or whether you use anyone
else's or whether you figure out your
own to be honest what I would recommend
you do is actually figure out your own
the point of this video is to just give
you some ideas the point is that when
you figure out a deep work system you
are creating value in less time which
means whether you're doing the career
stream or the side hustle stream or the
entrepreneur stream you're able to
create the value that gets you to your
goal of Freedom a lot faster and a lot
more likely the final thing I will say
on this front which is I think I think
is also important is that on the freedom
path freedom is the destination that
lots of us are spiring to but there are
two other things as it relates to work
that are more underrated and those are
what I think of as Journey goals and
those two things are fun and
fulfillment yes everyone is striving for
freedom but generally what you realize
when you get to Freedom you know by the
grace of God in a position where I am
financially free I don't need to work
another day in my life if I don't want
to I can do whatever I want I can do it
whenever I want I have time location and
Financial Freedom but what you realize
when you get there is that freedom is is
a currency kind of like money and
freedom itself has no intrinsic value
Freedom only has value when it is
exchanged for other things like if you
for example had 168 hours completely
free you would be depressed pretty
quickly if you had nothing to do with
that time the point of freedom is to be
able to cash it in for fun and
fulfillment and the other things that
make life worth living the freedom to
spend more time with your kids for
example gives you fulfillment and fun
the freedom to read or to play video
games or to go on that walk in the
middle of the day or to play squash in
the evenings that gives you fun and
fulfillment it's not really about the
freedom it's about what the freedom can
get you which is ultimately fun and
fulfillment now what's interesting is
that on the freedom path on your journey
to Freedom you can in fact and I would
recommend you should find a way to
experience fun and fulfillment because
whether or not you get to the
destination you will realize that the
journey was what always mattered in the
first place but even when you do get to
the destination you realize oh like
the destination is worthless on its own
the destination is only worthwhile in
that it gives me fun and fulfillment
what does any of this have to do with
deep work well when you speak to people
who have achieved freedom time Freedom
location Freedom Financial Freedom you
tend to find something fairly common
which is that firstly these people still
want to work work as in do something
that uses their skills that feels like
it is providing a meaningful
contribution to someone or to society or
something which I would argue is the
definition of work they still want to be
useful in some way but if you ask these
people like what sort of work they would
want to do they never ever ever say
shallow work they only ever say deep
work like in your case for example let's
say you had all the money in the bank
and all the time in the world and you
could do whatever you wanted you might
might sit panina colados on the beach in
Thailand for about 2 weeks before
realizing that makes you miserable and
depressed and you and you're going to
want to find some sort of work to do
what sort of work would you like to be
doing you're probably not answering I'd
like to answer emails while getting
distracted on Tik Tok your answer is
probably related to deep work to some
degree I'd love to have 4 hours free
every single morning to just focus on
writing I'd love to have hours each day
where I can just focus on expanding my
creative Pursuits or my art or my music
or my this that or the other the reason
I'm saying all this is because deep work
is not just the means to an end it is
not just the way to create value
monetize that value and then get to
Financial Freedom that's not the only
thing that deep work is good for deep
work is also the way you get fun and
fulfillment from your work and again
this is something that I don't think
enough people talk about like the skill
of focusing the skill of being able to
sit down and just work on something for
an extended period of time that skill
buys your financial freedom but it also
gives you fun and fulfillment you feel
way more fulfilled when you're in the
Flow State when you're working on
something that's hard but that's within
your limits maybe at the edge of your
limit you feeling like you're growing
you feeling like time is absolutely
flying you get to the end of that
session having done deep work having
been in the Flow State and you get that
glow of fulfillment you probably do not
get that glow of fulfillment while
you're distracted watching Instagram
real and answering emails and trying to
do a zillion things at once so that is
why deep work is important I hope if
you're at this point in the video that
you agree with me that deep work is
really important and cultivating the
skill building that muscle of focus
being able to deep work is vitally
useful for fun fulfillment and Financial
Freedom let's now move on to part two
where we talk about my personal deep
work routine which I've built over last
several years of trying to get really
good at
this okay so there are four steps to the
Deep work system and what I would
recommend you do which is a philosophy
that I talk a lot about in my book
Feelgood productivity which is now out I
think on paperback it's also hardback
Kindle audio book paperback I recorded
the audiobook so if you haven't read it
yet you should check it out cuz it's a
guide on how to enjoy your work and we
find that when we enjoy our work it
makes us more fulfilled more creative
less stressed more productive etc etc
anyway a key philosophy that I teach
teach in the book and that I'm keen on
sort of making obvious on this channel
is that building your own productivity
system is a very personal thing yes you
can copy and paste my system you can
copy and paste someone else's templates
but really by experimenting with what
works for you and seeing what happens
and then tweaking your own system by
building your own system that is what
will ultimately get you to the result
that you want and so in this video I
want to tell you what the four steps of
my own personal deep work system are so
that hopefully you can get some ideas
for how to apply them to
yours all right so step number one is to
actually schedule the Deep work into the
calendar I have two methods of doing
this the first one is that I have an
ideal Week calendar more details in that
video up there about the Trident system
of managing your time basically I've got
a separate Google Calendar which is my
ideal week where I block out in a dream
world what does my ideal ordinary week
look like now here I want to talk about
four different types of deep work now
this is from Cal newport's book deep
work and he defines there being
basically four different ways of
scheduling deep work into your calendar
deep work method number one is monastic
this is monk mode before it was called
monk mode before it was cool
method two is
bodal method three is rhythmic and
Method four is journalistic now the
stuff around this stuff is very
interesting if you haven't yet read deep
work by Cal Newport I would recommend
reading it you could also get yourself
the summary of the book deep work on
short form there is an affiliate link
down below if you want to sign to short
form it's the world's best service for
reading summaries of books they even
have a summary of my book and I read the
summary of my own book and I was like
damn this is an annoyingly good summary
of my own book so there's a link down
below if you want to check it out but
let's talk about these four different
ways of scheduling deep work into your
calendar monastic is the monk mode thing
where it's like you you have you carve
out an extended period of time to just
do deep work this is like going on a
writing Retreat for a whole week
probably not suitable for most people
because most of us can't take a whole
week off to just do deep work in a
focused fashion we can maybe do it some
of the time I occasionally do the
monastic thing if I you know when I was
on deadline for my book I went to Bali
to give a talk and I just stayed there
for an extra like week just focusing on
the book that's just not feasible for
most people for most part of life so I
generally ignore the monastic approach
then you have the bimodal approach which
works for some people which is basically
where you have some days that are
entirely deep work days and some days
that are entirely shallow work days then
you have the rhythmic approach which is
trying to build a daily Rhythm for
yourself as it relates to deep work this
is what I do I focus on the first 4
hours of every day being focused on deep
work usually making videos or working
one of my courses or working on one of
my books because that is the key way in
which I add value and then finally you
have journalistic which is kind of named
after I think journalists where they're
just sort of sort of doing so much
random that they're just trying to
squeeze in random small amounts of time
of deep work here and there because they
literally don't have any other choice
back when I had a real job working as a
doctor I was really unable to do a lot
of these things because I had an
unpredictable schedule based on on call
rotos and work and that kind of thing so
while I was at work I had a sort of
journalistic approach to deep work where
I would squeeze in time in the middle of
the day or like an extra 20 minutes on
my lunch break that that sort of thing
to be able to work on videos or for
example if I happened to be on night
shifts for a week and then I had 3 days
off I'll be like all right in those 3
days I'm going to be absolutely laser
focused on deep work in the monastic
sort of Camp cuz I'm like in those 3
days I can bang out so much stuff for my
for my videos or for my course or
whatever the side hustle thing I was
working on when my side hustle of this
YouTube channel and the business around
it was enough to be able to quit my day
job as a doctor suddenly I had free time
to be able to do whatever I wanted
essentially and I experimented with all
the different types of deep work and I
landed on rhythmic so the first 4 hours
of every day are focused on deep work so
that's like 9:00 a.m. till 1:00 p.m.
then 1: till 2 I'll have lunch 2 till 3:
I'll in theory attempt to go to the gym
and then 3: to 6 is sort of like shallow
work meetings all this sort of stuff but
it basically guarantees that roughly the
first four hours of the day are focused
on deep work so that is step one of the
whole thing figure out what sort of
schedule you would like to schedule your
deep work into and generally when I
coach people on this CU people come up
to me on the streets and want to do
talks and stuff sometimes and ask like
you know I'm really struggling to focus
or you know students in my YouTuber
Academy a productivity lab who struggle
to focus usually they haven't done step
one which is to actually schedule the
Deep work into the calendar it must be
scheduled into the calendar otherwise
it's not going to happen so let's say
you have scheduled the Deep work into
your calendar then what do you do when
you get to that slot well at this point
we have points 2 3 and four so the first
one is as part of my deep workor system
is I Take 5 minutes to align and
organize this is part of my life
productivity system which I'm releasing
as a course at some point soon if you
want to sign up to my newsletter you'll
hear more about it if you want but
anyway 5 minutes align and organize
basically it's I spend 5 minutes at the
start of every deep workk session
firstly figuring out what do I actually
want to accomplish in this deep work
session because it's very very very
useful to have a goal research around
Flow State and all this sort of stuff
says that it's very difficult to achieve
flow when you don't have a clear goal
that you're working towards so that is
the point of aligning and then secondly
I have organized which is basically
where I make sure I have a cup of water
or a cup of coffee if it's sufficiently
early in the day which it often is
because in the first 4 hours I make sure
I have all the materials that I need to
actually do the thing because something
that's going to distract me from Deep
work is having to get up off my desk or
off the coffee shop and like go and do
something I make sure I've done a Wii so
that I don't need to do a Wii or a poo
in the middle of my deep workk session
and in those 5 minutes I do a little bit
of a startup routine so I have for
example these headphones which is a nice
nice little blue color or I just whack
in my airpods or if I'm on my actual
desk and there's no one else in the room
I'll play some music I'll put on my
study with me playlist on Spotify
because I know that that always gets me
into the sort of focus zone and I think
this sort of startup routine is actually
really helpful because what it does is
that it eases you into the focus for a
lot of people it's like even if you have
scheduled in the Deep work it comes to
sitting down to do it and then there's
this enormous like activation energy
barrier of like oh but like I don't want
to sit down and do the hard thing
because like uh I don't want to do it
and I used to have that a lot I still
have that to this day but what I can do
is that firstly I can set a goal because
it's easy enough to do that it doesn't
take that much cognitive manpower to be
able to set a goal and what I can also
do is put on my headphones put on my
nice music so of make sure I've got my
little coffee I've got my little water
make sure I've got my desk organized in
a nice way it's all these like tiny
little things that help me ramp up
towards the actual Focus block then step
three we have Focus which I often do for
about 50 minutes but to be honest the
focus time varies I'm not wedded to
doing it for 50 minutes I tend to just
do it for or however long it takes me to
start to lose focus sometimes it's 50
minutes sometimes it's 45 sometimes if
I'm really tired or like I've just got
lots of going on my brain it's only
15 minutes where I'm like I'm focusing
for 15 minutes and then I start to feel
like oh I'm itching to get distracted
and do something else if you want more
details on exactly how to stay focused
I've got a whole evidence-based guide up
there somewhere there's like a three pot
playlist on how to actually Focus which
is about maximizing the use of this time
here and then finally I spend the final
5 minutes of the session on reflect and
recharge and crucially one thing I do in
this section if I'm in a stage of life
where I'm struggling to focus
is something I've talked about in videos
a lot the focus log what is the focus
log the focus log is basically where you
log the amount of time you spent
actually focused on deep work this is
something Cal Newport absolutely swears
by in his book deep work if there is
just one thing you do that will
radically completely change your
relationship to deep work and focus it's
actually just keeping track of how many
minutes or hours each day are you
actually spending focusing this is
something I was really bullish when I
first taught my life productivity system
course to students in productivity lab
about 9 months ago and I was so bullish
on this that like you know we built
templates and systems and processes into
our course and into our community that
helped people do their focus log and we
had so many testimonials from students
who took that course who basically took
that advice and said that damn actually
tracking the number of minutes I spend
each day focusing a made me realize how
little time I actually spend focusing on
deep work and B gave me awareness of
that problem so that I was able to
increase that time there's all sorts of
stuff in the world of business Alex MOSI
talks about this a lot around
measurement as intervention like there's
all those studies of people who want to
lose weight if you just weigh yourself
every day you are by default going to
lose some weight because now you're
aware of what that number is most of us
who struggle with Focus you probably
struggle with Focus if you're at this
point in the video you you like this
idea of the deep work system you
probably have no idea how many minutes
each day you actually spend focusing on
deep work and if there is just one thing
you were to apply to your life from this
entire video if you just start tracking
however you want you could do it on a
posted note you can do it on a notebook
you can do it on an app you can you can
use whatever you don't need a fancy tool
for this you don't need a fancy template
you can just do it on a Google sheet I
do it on a Google sheet these days
because I'm just can't be asked to deal
with the apps if you just track the
number of minutes or hours you spend
each day focusing and the
goal the goal is 4 hours or rather
that's the upper limit there's a great
book called Rest by Alex something or
rather I've got it in the living room
over there but the name eludes me rest
he cides a lot of evidence and well a
lot of anecdotes from people throughout
time that says that about 4 hours a day
is about the upper limit of how long
humans can focus for so the goal is to
actually track your focus hours through
your focus log and get that number to
about 4 hours a day man if you could do
4 hours a day you are absolutely Off to
the Races I don't even do 4 hours a day
and I have full control over my time and
I can do whatever I want I maybe
sometimes manag to do like two in a bit
or like three in a bit like back when I
was working on my book I would get up to
four and then like the whole day would
be gone because actually for 4 hours of
focus it's actually really hard to get
in 4 hours of uninterrupted focus it
obviously doesn't happen all in one go
it happens in and like strips and bits
and spits and drips and drabs but the
goal is 4 hours if you just do that one
thing just track how many hours you are
spending focusing each day and then
trying to get that number up to 4 hours
you will be completely transformed and
your life will never be the same ever
again because now you have figured out
some sort of deep work system but unless
you know what that number is unless you
are tracking how many minutes each day
you are actually focusing it's very
difficult to actually improve on the
thing because as Peter drer famously
said what gets measured gets managed and
what gets measured gets improved so that
is the system that I personally use
pretty much every day to focus for Peak
productivity it's a system that I've
built over the years of being obsessed
with productivity to the point where I
realized that damn this Focus deep work
stuff is super important and without
having some sort of deep workk system I
would not be at anywhere near the level
of Financial Freedom if that's what you
care about as I currently am and so my
sincere hope for you is that the thing
that you take away from this video is
that a it's worth building your own deep
work system and B it's worth tracking
the numbers so that you can actually
improve your deep work system and I
would love to get an email from you a
few weeks months or years from now
saying that like whoa I've been tracking
my focus minutes for the last like X
number of time and it's just completely
changed my life because I know that
doing that did it for me and I hope that
it will do it for you as well if you are
interested in more details on how to
focus I've got my three-part playlist on
how to focus over there somewhere thank
you so much for watching and I'll see
you hopefully in the next video bye-bye