Hey friends, welcome back to the
channel. In this video, I would like to
make one central point. There's
basically just one point I'm going to
make throughout the entire video. And
that point is all about a number. More
specifically, it is about a ratio. And
so the ratio is between these two
numbers. So this is a little exercise
that you can try for yourself. Firstly,
count how much time in the last 7 days
you have spent consuming stuff. Screen
time is a good proxy for this. How much
time have you spent consuming stuff that
has been created by other people? And
then once you've done that, you want to
estimate how much time you have spent
creating something yourself. Now you
calculate your creation to consumption
ratio. And according to the internet,
the average person spends about 28 hours
a week consuming stuff created by other
people and only around 2 hours a week
doing their own acts of creation. That
leads to a consumption to creation ratio
of like 14 to1, which is totally fine if
that's how you want to live your life.
But the people who follow this channel,
people in my audience, uh I suspect you
have goals that are beyond just being a
professional consumer of things, I
suspect your goals maybe involve freedom
to some degree. You'd like the freedom
to live on your own terms. Maybe you'd
like financial freedom. Maybe you'd like
time freedom. Maybe you'd like the
ability to choose what you do for work.
And my hot take in this video is that if
you have any goal that is related to
freedom and that goal is something that
the masses do not accomplish, then you
really want to be shifting your ratio of
creation to consumption more in favor of
creation than consumption. I.e. you
should be spending at least as many
hours of the week creating stuff as you
spend consuming stuff. Ideally, even
more creating stuff than you do
consuming stuff. So, what does creating
stuff mean? I don't mean you have to be
a YouTuber, although creating videos and
sticking them on the internet does count
as creation. You could be making
anything. You could be producing
anything. You could be building stuff.
You could be using your head. You could
be using your hands. You could be using
your brain. You could be using your
skills. You could be using any of this
sort of stuff to make something and put
it into the world, something that didn't
exist before. Oh, by the way, quick
thing. If you happen to be watching this
before the 1st of August 2025, then for
6 weeks from the 1st of August through
to the 12th of September 2025, me and my
team are hosting a live 6 week challenge
called the 1K challenge. And the whole
idea behind the 1K challenge is that
it's a 6 week live online course and
boot camp to help you make your first
$1,000 on the internet. It's a challenge
that we've designed for complete
beginners to entrepreneurship to side
hustles to making money. And you'll be
doing this live with people from all
around the world who are also at that
same stage as you. So, if that sounds
good and you would like to make your
first thousand dollars on the internet
and you'd like to learn the skills and
actually take action through the format
of this live online boot camp, then
there is a link to sign up in the video
description. If you look at the examples
of a lot of successful people, like
actually, you know what, forget about
how you define success. Just like pick
anyone that you look up to, chances are
a big part of the reason you look up to
them is because of the stuff they have
produced or created. It is very unlikely
to be because of the stuff that they
have consumed. If you look at a very
large number of successful
entrepreneurs, a lot of them built
random stuff when they were in school or
university or in their 30s or before
they started their main business. And as
I said, the main point of this video is
that if you are trying to work towards
freedom, you really want to be spending
more hours a week creating than you do
consuming. I'm not trying to tell anyone
what to do. You can live your life
however you want. You can do whatever
you want. But when I speak to people in
my audience at events and workshops and
stuff and they have goals that are
around freedom, like financial freedom
or time freedom or location freedom or
freedom of choice or freedom of creative
expression or like freedom of anything,
like freedom to not have to do you
don't want to do and the ability to do
stuff that you actually want to do, that
is it's worth recognizing that that is a
top 1% goal, right? Only like 1% of the
people in the world actually have the
freedom, probably less than that
actually, actually have the freedom to
just not do stuff they don't want to do
and the freedom to do stuff that they
want to do. I suspect for you, you're
probably not trying to get like mega
rich. You're probably not trying to
become like a Dubai boy billionaire
super yacht kind of lifestyle, but you'd
probably like to have more money in your
life, right? You'd like to have more
money and you'd like to make that money
in a more flexible and freeing way than
you're currently doing. The problem is
if you have the consumption ratio that
most people have, you're just not going
to get there. It's probably not going to
happen because the only way you work
towards that kind of freedom, whether
you're doing it through your own
business or you're doing it through a
career that's sufficiently flexible, is
by creating value for other people. And
then that's how money is made. Like you
create value for other people and then
they give you money for the value that
you are creating. There is almost no one
in the world who makes a good amount of
money from consuming stuff. Also, it's
not just about money, right? Like
freedom is a clear goal of a lot of
people in my audience. But also
fulfillment like we also want to be
fulfilled. And if you look at the stats
and like the data on this and also just
like think about your own experience.
What are the sorts of activities that
are more likely to lead you to feeling
fulfilled? How fulfilled do you really
feel after you binge Tik Tok or
Instagram res for a few hours? How
fulfilled do you really feel when you
have binged a whole season of something
on Netflix? It can be sometimes nice,
right? Especially if you're doing it
with like loved ones, it kind of feels a
little bit connecting some of the time,
but for the most part, if you look at
what people say in the in the surveys
and in studies around this, the things
that disproportionately create
fulfillment for human beings are
creative activities rather than
consumptive activities. Creating stuff
and connecting with others tends to be
the thing that makes us fulfilled. So
even if you're like this guy, I don't
care about money. It's like, okay, but
you probably care about fulfillment, and
that will probably come more naturally
to you and more readily if you shift
your consumption ratio in favor of
creating rather than consuming. And
speaking of creating more than
consuming, one of my absolute favorite
tools that I use pretty much every day
to help me create more than consume, is
Claude from Anthropic, who are very
kindly sponsoring this video. Claude is
the incredibly thoughtful AI
conversational partner designed by
Anthropic. And of all of the different
AI tools, all of the different large
language models out there, all of the
ones that you've heard of and you
haven't heard of, I've tried pretty much
all of them. And Claude is the one that
I keep coming back to because I
personally think it's the best one out
there. The reason why I think Claude is
better than Chad PT and all of the other
sort of competitor LLMs is because its
personality is really, really thoughtful
and it's like having a very intelligent,
honest, sort of genuinely deepinking
conversational buddy to sort of bounce
ideas with back and forth. So for me,
the way that I personally use it is I
start off all of my sort of creation for
YouTube videos and newsletters and
whatever using the app voice pal. So
I'll go for a walk, I'll speak into
voice pal to get an initial transcript
of whatever I'm thinking about. And then
I will put that transcript into Claude
and then Claude will understand the
essence of what I'm trying to say based
on the original transcript. And I can
ask it to give me really thoughtful
opinions distilling the essence of what
I've said. And that really helps me
think in different directions. And
generally, I find that by going back and
forth with Claude, it massively improves
the quality of the ideas that I'm
thinking about, whether it relates to
content that we're creating or strategy
or product design or anything like that.
And yeah, what I really love about
Claude is that the experience feels very
it feels very nice. It feels very
collaborative. So, if you haven't yet
tried out Claude, there is a link in the
video description for you to try it out
completely for free. So, thank you so
much Claude and Anthropic for sponsoring
this video. And let's get back to it.
Now, one of the crucial points is that
it's not just about consuming
entertainment. It's also about consuming
education. So, a lot of people in my
audience will be like will be watching
YouTube videos like this one, right?
They'll have watched all the
productivity content. They'll be
following all the gurus on Instagram and
Tik Tok. They'll be listening to
episodes of Dar CEO. And it it feels
good. It feels good because you're
consuming educational content. Even
books fall under this category. And for
the record, there is nothing wrong with
consuming educational content. There's
nothing wrong with consuming
entertainment content either. You know
what? There's nothing wrong with any of
this. I'm just saying that if your goal
is freedom and fulfillment, shifting the
ratio towards creation rather than
consumption, even if it's consumption of
educational content, is likely to
increase the probability that you get to
your goal. But the reason I'm also
including educational content in the
consumption camp, is because it's very,
very easy for educational content and
learning and research to fuel the
consumption treadmill, the research
rabbit hole where you're like, "Ah, I
know I want to start a business someday,
but I don't have the right idea yet.
Therefore, I'm going to listen to all
the business podcasts and I'm going to
maybe read all the business books and
I'm going to watch all the YouTube
tutorials of people talking about how to
set up a marketing agency and this that
and the other. It's like, yeah, okay,
that's all well and good, but the people
that actually start successful
businesses, they tend to be creating the
business and producing stuff and making
things and then they are learning
alongside that. I personally feel that
consumption and education and learning
should come on top of a foundation of
action and doing stuff rather than learn
first do later. It is also not just me
who says this. There is a guy called
Paul Graham who is the founder of Y
Combinator, which is like this massive
startup accelerator in the US. And he
has a really good essay about how to
find work you love. And I'm going to
read directly from the article here.
Always produce. For example, if you have
a day job that you don't take seriously
because you plan to be a novelist, are
you producing? Are you writing pages of
fiction, however bad? As long as you're
producing, you'll know you're not merely
using the hazy vision of the grand novel
you plan to write one day as an opiate.
The view of it will be obstructed by the
all too palpably flawed one that you're
actually writing. There's one more quote
from this, but I'm going to double click
on this point over here right now
because this is a thing that I see in
loads of people uh at my events and
workshops and stuff, which is that you
have this vision for this thing that
you'd like to do, but you're not taking
any action towards it. And in not taking
the action towards it, you are doing a
very clear thing, which is you are
avoiding confronting the feeling that
you might be crap at the thing. I've got
a good friend who's been wanting to make
YouTube videos for like 5 years of her
life, like right now. And so far she's
made like one or two videos. And she the
last one she made was like years ago.
She admitted the other day she was like,
"Oh man, you know, I kind of realized
something. The reason why I'm just not
making any videos is because in my head
I'm a really good YouTuber and I could
totally make a living from being a
YouTuber. But I know that as soon as I
start making videos, I will have to
confront the fact that maybe that's not
going to happen and that maybe I'm
actually at the job." And that's
like a profoundly good insight. Like
when you start out doing anything,
you're going to suck at the thing,
right? It's like the gap between what
you know good is and what you'd like to
be capable of producing and what you are
actually producing. That gap feels
really scary to confront. So, if you're
at this point in the video, the question
might be to take uh an honest look at
your life and ask yourself, in what
areas am I allowing my vision of
perfection to stop me from actually
doing the messy work because I'm afraid
I will actually suck at the thing. And
you will suck at the thing. You're going
to suck at literally everything you
start out doing. And you have to suck at
the thing for a very long time before it
starts to get even vaguely good. And
that suck period, the period where your
thing is objectively is so it's so
uncomfortable and so scary. I think for
kids it's fine because especially if
they haven't been like had that squashed
out of them. Kids are just chill with
just being crap everything. But when
you're an adult, I I suspect you
probably are if you're watching this,
and especially if you've had any kind of
success, academic success or
professional success, it's easy for us,
people like you and me, you know, people
who are very intelligent and very
good-looking, it's easy for us to get
fixated on this idea that we're good at
doing stuff like you're good at your
job, you were good in school, and now
you try this new thing. In my case, it's
like drawing. In your case, maybe it's
like starting that business that you've
never done before or like being a
creator or whatever the thing might be.
You have to confront the fact that
you're going to be terrible at the thing
to begin with. And that's really really
scary because we have this ego image of
ourselves as being competent and being
good at stuff and we have to let go of
that image and just recognize that hey
we just got to be producing as Paul
Graeme says we got to be creating all
the time. There's another line from
this. Always produce is also a
heruristic for finding the work you
love. If you subject yourself to that
constraint, it will automatically push
you away from things you think you're
supposed to work on and towards things
you actually like. Always produce will
discover your life's work. the way water
with the aid of gravity finds the hole
in your roof. When you are making stuff
and you're just constantly making stuff
and your ratio of creation to
consumption is more in the creation
camp, you will inevitably find stuff
that you actually enjoy doing because
you'll realize you can't sustain this
kind of creation ratio by doing things
you're supposed to do, by doing the
shoods. You can't should yourself into
making YouTube videos for 8 years. You
have to actually at a certain point
start enjoying the process. And the more
of these things you try and the more
like random stuff you create, the more
you'll realize, oh, I actually prefer
creating that sort of thing rather than
that sort of thing. Steven Spielberg,
for example, was randomly making random
camcorder movies when he was a kid with
his like dad's camcorder or whatever.
Then he realizes, oh, I just really like
making these movie type things. It
wasn't part of some kind of grandm where
he was like, you know what, I'm going to
break into Hollywood. I'm going to be a
director. It's like, no, he was just
creating random stuff when he was a kid.
And in that process, he realized what
was the thing he liked doing. I speak to
a lot of people in my audience who who
also ask the question of like, "How do I
know what my passion is?" Like, "How do
I find the work I'm supposed to be
doing? How do I find work that like I
don't hate doing? Work that I find
enjoyable, work that I'm passionate
about, work that I find energizing." If
you ask most young people, "What are you
passionate about?" they'd be like, uh, I
don't know, like scrolling and, um, I
don't know, like reading romanty or like
most people, especially who are in the
consumption end of the spectrum, which
is most people I speak to,
unfortunately, don't have a clear idea
of what they actually like doing because
they haven't created enough stuff. It's
in the process of making things that you
realize, oh, I actually really enjoy
designing websites or I really enjoy
building electronics or I really enjoy
making arts and crafts or I really enjoy
writing short fiction. And it's the
people who are spending a good chunk of
their time making random stuff. Those
are the people Paul Graham says and I
would agree for what it's worth end up
finding the work that they actually
enjoy. You will not find the work that
you enjoy. You will not discover your
passions. You'll not find what you were
meant to do by consuming stuff. You will
only find it by creating stuff. All
right, so at this point, maybe you're
sold. You're like, "All right, cool. I
want to shift my ratio of stuff from
away from consumption and more towards
creation. How do I actually do this?" I
have a theory on this, which is just do
I call it random acts of creation. Just
create random stuff. And there are five
characteristics that I would recommend
for the stuff that you create. It needs
to be small, needs to be fast, needs to
be bad, needs to be stupid, and it needs
to be pointless. small, bad, fast,
stupid, and pointless. That is the
guiding characteristics of the of the
stuff that you should create. Why? Okay.
Well, firstly, it needs to be small.
Small enough that you can probably just
do it in a weekend or a week or in like,
you know, the Christmas holidays or in
the summer holidays or whenever you take
time off work or whatever the thing
might be. It needs to be small and
manageable, fast. It needs to be
something you can make quickly. If
you're trying to, you know, your first
random act of creation is to write an
epic fantasy, it's probably not going to
happen because it's like too big. where
starting with short stories is generally
a way easier way to get into the writing
thing and get in and get into the
creative act. Thirdly, bad. Well, it
should be bad because if you are
actively aiming for the thing to be bad,
you are hopefully going to avoid all of
the resistance traps that the ego tries
to put in place where if you try and
create something good, but you've never
done it before, you will suck at the
thing and then you're going to be
perfectionistic about it and then the
fear and the uncertainty and the doubt
and the imposter syndrome and all the I
suck and I shouldn't even be on this
earth. All all of the things that the
mind likes to say, all of those things
are going to get in the way. Whereas, if
you aim for it to be bad, you're like,
"My goal is to make something bad." It
suddenly sort of removes a lot of that
like random crap that's associated with
trying to make something good. So, it
needs to be small, it needs to be fast,
it needs to be bad. It also needs to be
stupid. The thing should be stupid
because if you tell yourself that the
thing is not stupid, it's going to allow
the fear of what other people think to
get in the way of you and your active
creation. Whereas if you if you actively
just say to yourself, "Hey, I'm just
making this dumb stupid thing." It gives
you way more permission to do something
weird, to do something that your friends
may not necessarily approve of, to do
something that might be a little bit off
the beaten track. If you tell yourself,
"This is a dumb stupid thing." And
finally, the thing should be pointless
because if there is an instrumental
purpose to the thing beyond just the
intrinsic value in creating the thing,
that also adds loads and loads of
pressure to the thing. So for example,
my brother my brother is one year
younger than me and when he was in
school and a little bit at university,
he decided to make random uh small,
fast, bad, stupid, pointless, like three
random projects. One of them was a
website where you would just click a
button and the number would go up and it
was there would be leaderboards of like
who's clicked the button the most times.
And this was I think the first website
that he made. He'd watched The Social
Network, the film about Facebook, and he
was inspired to learn to code and he
realized he just needs to make this
fast, small, dumb, stupid, pointless
project. I'm sure he won't mind me
saying that, but yeah, it was dumb,
stupid, and pointless. It's a random
website called Clickfilia where you just
click a button um and then there's a
leaderboard. But that random tiny ass
project taught him some of the basics of
learning how to code. The next thing he
made was another small small, fast, bad,
stupid, dumb, pointless project, which
was called speed sums. I think it might
still be online, which was basically a
website where it would just give you
like 30 different sums like 5 plus 3 and
7 plus 4, kind of like the brain
training Nintendo DS game from back in
the day. And it would be a little test
to see how quickly you could solve these
sums. And again, there was a leaderboard
or something like that. Now, I remember
when he was making these random
projects, our mom would ask him, "Hey,
what's the point?" And he'd be like,
"Yeah, there's no point. I'm just doing
it for fun." And she'd be like, "All
right, then." And that's very good. It's
good that he felt the he felt able to
make pointless stuff. The problem that a
lot of smart people have, especially
when you become adults, because again,
adults are very adults are very used to
optimizing for CV points and like what
good what looks good on the resume.
Adults are like, "Oh man, I don't want
to waste time doing this pointless thing
because I could be spending my time
investing it more wisely to do this
thing that might lead to something
further down the line." The more you try
and get your random smallass tiny
creative projects to lead to something
further down the line, the more pressure
you're going to put on yourself to make
those things actually good and to make
them purposeful and to make them like
meaningful and have a point to them and
the less likely you are to do it. If
you're at this point in the video and
you are concerned about your creation to
consumption ratio, we just want to lower
the bar for what counts as creation as
much as is humanly possible because
chances are if you haven't started
creating a lot of stuff already, which I
suspect is true if you're at this point
in the video, but if you haven't done
that, it's probably because you're being
held back by the bar for a creative
thing just being way too high. When my
brother was making randomass websites,
he did not think there was a point. He
just did it for the fun of it. And
making those, this is where I was going
to go with the story, making these
random small tiny ass projects, what
that meant was he learned how to code.
I'm very bullish on learning how to code
as you guys might know if you've seen
some of the content. So he did all these
like pointless shitty projects when he
was at school in university and then he
graduated. He did a degree in maths and
then did a masters in like statistics
and then got a job as a data scientist
at some company. And a year into his
job, he was like, "Wait a minute. Um,
there's this clear like Monte Carlo
simulation thing that we're having to
use like Excel, Microsoft Excel for, but
what if we could just build some
software that does Monte Carlo
simulation statistical modeling for
finance teams? And what if we could just
like turn that into a startup?" And that
was the business called Cosal that he
started like in 2019. And he sold the
company recently and is living a great
life and stuff. Um, but he wouldn't have
learned how to code if he hadn't done
these small, shitty, pointless projects.
Doing those small, shitty, pointless
projects ended up giving him the skills
to then see and capitalize upon a
startup opportunity like 6 years later.
The other benefit of random act of
creation, which is I'm kind of alluding
to, is that they teach you stuff. They
teach you skills. You never know when a
certain combination of skills is going
to come in handy. For example, if you
were someone who did played a lot of
chess and you had chess lessons and you
were also someone who was making like
random home videos with like your phone
or your camcorder back in the day, you
probably wouldn't have predicted 10
years ago that during the pandemic there
would be a TV show called The Queen's
Gambit, which would suddenly make
streaming chess a massively popular
thing on the internet and loads of
people are suddenly going to start
getting into chess. you probably
wouldn't have predicted any of those
things. But if you had been someone who
was like super into chess and also super
into like making videos and stuff, you
might have been able to combine those
two interesting like random unrelated
skills to create something very very
interesting and now make a living as
like a chess content creator if that's
what you're into. For me, the stuff I
was creating back when I was in school
was like random websites. I was trying
to build random websites. Um, a because
I thought they were fun, b cuz I wanted
to learn to code and and c because I
thought, "Ooh, maybe one day I can make
a website that makes money." So, they
didn't quite fit the pointless thing.
Actually, a lot of them are pointless,
like a personal website for myself and
like forum signatures and random stuff.
Learning how to use Photoshop, learning
how to use Dreamweaver, learning the
basics of how to code. I could not have
known that six years later when I would
get into medical school, those website
design skills would come in handy
because that's what allowed me to build
my first business. I couldn't have known
that 10 years after I got into med
school when I was working towards a
residency in plastic surgery, I would
end up meeting these people who needed a
guide to design their website. And so
that's what allowed me to get in with
these like hot shot plastic surgeons who
were doing like really cool
reconstructive surgery all over the
world because I was their web master. I
was just some random medical student,
but I knew how to make websites. And so
it's like this randomass skill which I
randomly learned when I was like 15
years old ended up coming in handy 10
years later and getting me into this
like network that would have been really
hard to penetrate otherwise. And if you
read biographies of successful founders
and if you listen to podcast interviews
with like anyone that you look up to and
the host asks them about like what what
sort of stuff they were doing when they
were younger, a lot of it is based
around random acts of creation rather
than just loads and loads and loads of
consumption. Now, one of the issues that
you're probably going to find when you
start creating more stuff, especially if
you do it publicly, and I would
recommend you to do it publicly, because
putting stuff out there publicly, even
if no one reads it, even if no one
watches it, even if it's a newsletter
that you only subscribe to, even if it's
an Instagram that has zero followers,
even if it's a website that no one ever
visits, there's something about putting
stuff out there publicly that confronts
a lot of the emotional hurdles that hold
people back from stuff in general, like
fear and imposter syndrome and doubt and
all the stuff. But what you're probably
going to find when you start creating
stuff and you put it out publicly is you
might be familiar with this idea of tall
poppy syndrome, which is the people
around you, your peers,
probably they won't care. But if you
have a particularly judgmental set of
peers and friends and people in your
family and whatever people people that
you work with, there's this idea of tall
puppy syndrome where everyone is sort of
here and then you're sort of sticking
your head up as the tall puppy and the
tall poppy gets cut down. People don't
like it when you are doing something
that is outside of the norm. Unless you
have a particularly supportive
friendship group, in which case,
fantastic. You should you should
definitely keep them around. But people
generally don't like it. And so there is
a chance that you might experience some
social backlash to doing creative stuff
and putting it out there. And I think
this is a good thing. This is actually a
sign that you're on the right track. If
you don't want to be like all of the
people around you, then exp then feeling
their social backlash is probably a good
thing. it's probably a sign that you're
roughly on the right tracks. Obviously,
don't experience social backlash by like
doing something illegal or something
like actively harmful. But if you're
experiencing social backlash, if people
are laughing at you or people that think
it's cringe that you've started an
Instagram account or whatever the thing
is, that's a sign that you are stepping
outside of your comfort zone and and
stepping outside of the comfort zone of
the crabs that you surround yourself
with. My wife Izzy, she like a few years
ago before she became a YouTuber, she
started an Instagram account because she
got super into gardening during the
pandemic and so she started a gardening
themed Instagram account that's like an
act of creation. It's like planting
seeds and trying to get into gardening
and you know snapping photos of it to
sort of document the journey on a sort
of on an Instagram account. But somehow
some girls in med school, it was it was
mostly girls, uh, found out about this
Instagram account and um, she heard that
people were laughing at her behind her
back, like handful of people being like,
"Oh my god, I can't believe he's
starting an Instagram account. Like,
lol, that's so cringe." You know, all of
all of that sort of stuff. And it made
her feel really bad. But, you know, she
continued with the gardening Instagram
account. Starting the Instagram account
gave her the sort of uh, confidence to
then start a YouTube channel. Starting a
YouTube channel has completely changed
her life because now she has like
700,000 subscribers and is like able to
live life that she wants and is able to
make more money from YouTube than she
does through medicine. And the point is
when you start doing stuff,
especially creative things, especially
things that push the boat out a little
bit, you might find that the people
around you, some people around you will
judge you for that. Mostly they won't.
Most of us worry way more than we should
about what the people around us think.
But if you have a very
judgmental friendship group or group of
peers, they might laugh at you. And you
got to be okay with that. Because if you
want to work towards freedom, the people
who laugh at you are probably not the
ones working towards freedom. Social
disapproval in a creative context is
generally a sign that you are on the
right track because you are stepping
outside of your comfort zone and you are
learning skills. And in the process of
learning those skills, you will sort of
skill stack to a point where if your
goal is freedom, if your goal is
fulfillment, doing the creative stuff is
going to be is going to make it way more
likely that you'll hit both of those
goals. Thank you for coming to my TED
talk. I hope you found this video
useful. And if you did and you haven't
yet seen my video on how to get rich,
maybe I suspect you might want to watch
that because it sort of is somewhat
related to the stuff in this video. So,
thank you so much for watching. Have a
lovely day and I'll see you in the next
video.