hey friends welcome back to tech
tuesdays it is that time of the year
again we are doing the most requested
video of which ipad should you buy in
2022 there are five to choose from you
have the basic ass budget ipad there is
the ipad
the ipad air there's the ipad mini there
is the 11 inch ipad pro and there is the
12.9 inch ipad pro so as usual we're
going to start with an upfront
conclusion where i tell you what i think
about these then we're going to talk
about the idea of diminishing returns
and the consumer to create a spectrum
which kind of dictates which of these
five ipads you should go for and then
one at a time we're gonna go over the
pros and cons of each of the ipads and
i'm gonna tell you why i personally use
an ipad mini rather than any of the
other fancier ones so let's start things
off with the upfront conclusion and that
is that if you are broadly a consumer of
stuff ie you watch things you maybe do
the occasional google doc here and there
but broadly your ipad is a consumption
device for you i would recommend the
basic ipad which is a fantastic option
if you're a student as well or the ipad
mini moving along spectrum if you are a
light creator or a student then broadly
the ipad air is a good option for you
and the ipad pro's the 11 inch and the
12.9 inch models so this one and this
one those are only really ideal if you
are a kind of professional and you know
that you need the power of something
like the m1 chip which is i suspect not
what 99.9 of people out there actually
need so that was the upfront conclusion
to hopefully save you time if that's all
you wanted then feel free to drop a like
on the video on the way out and maybe
consider subscribing to the channel but
now let's talk about this stuff in more
detail and let's start by talking about
this idea of the consumer to create a
spectrum so there is this thing in all
of tech it's like are you a consumer or
are you creator it's it's sort of like a
spectrum a consumer is someone who tends
to watch things or read things like you
know netflix spend spends most most of
the time in a web browser maybe watching
some youtube videos maybe listens to
some spotify maybe listens to some
podcasts maybe reads a book on kindle or
reads articles on instapaper or in
safari or on chrome or whatever it's
broadly a consumptiony type person then
as we go further along the spectrum
towards the creator professional
category we have people who most people
are kind of in that middle camp where
you're kind of using your ipad for some
consumption stuff but also for some like
creation stuff maybe you're typing word
documents here and there maybe you're
making presentations maybe you're an
artist and you're sketching some stuff
maybe you're a student and you're taking
typed out or handwritten notes that puts
you square in the middle of the consumer
to create a spectrum and then all the
way on the creator or pro side of the
spectrum we have people who need things
like 3d modeling people who do advanced
like i don't know video gaming people
who do stuff like rendering massive
files in photoshop or music producers
who have like zillions of tracks running
for those sorts of people they are on
the creator slash professional end of
the spectrum so it's generally useful to
know where you land on the spectrum
because it helps you figure out how much
money you should actually pay for stuff
if you're on the consumer end you don't
need to buy tools that are designed for
the professionals and the creators but
if you're a professional creator you
kind of know it and you know you have to
spend more money on the things that you
want so that was one of the principles
the other principle that really comes in
when valuing ipads is the idea of
diminishing returns which is that as you
spend more money on an ipad you actually
get less and less return for your money
spent so for example if you just buy the
basic ipad for 319 pounds that gives you
i would suggest roughly 88 of the value
of the ipad experience spend an extra
160 pounds on the ipad mini and you go
up to 92 percent i think these are just
my numbers off kind of my own personal
experience spend an extra 100 pounds and
go for the ipad air and you go up to 95
paying an extra 170 pounds then takes
you from 95 to 98 with the 11 inch pro
and then paying an extra 250 pounds
takes you from 98 to 100 with the 12.9
inch m1 ipad pro with the i don't know
fancy xdr display that they've got on it
so you can see we've got this sort of
curve where the more money you spend the
less value per unit money spent you're
getting from the ipad and a graph like
this is particularly important because
when we're asking is the ipad air worth
it or is the ipad pro worth it it kind
of depends it's just like well
objectively no because you're paying a
lot more for a very very small
percentage increase in utility or
usefulness or whatever but the question
of whether something is worth it
actually does depend on how much money
you have how much money you have to burn
because that dictates whether you know
is it worth it to spend one pound 50 on
a can of coke when you could just get
water at home like i don't know like it
just depends on how you personally value
money and there is no one answer to the
question of is something worth it so so
far what we've arrived at is basically
that the budget ipad 319 pounds gives
you the vast majority of the value of
having an ipad so if you are on a budget
honestly this is the one i'd recommend
it's still really good it looks a bit
old-fashioned compared to the newer
models but to be honest the budget ipad
is pretty sick and especially if you're
a student on a budget this is the one
that i would recommend broadly without
reservation with the new model that was
released in september 2021 they now have
support for the apple smart keyboard so
you could add an apple smart keyboard if
you want although logitech and other
brands have a bunch of third-party
accessories which are pretty good as
well and if you're on a budget you
probably don't want to spend i think
like 100 150 quid for the apple version
of the keyboard and this one has the a13
processor which is a few years old at
this point but again if you're a student
if you're on the lighter creator or
consumer end of the spectrum you're not
really going to notice the difference
between a 300 pound processor a13 and a
1300 pound like m1 processor you just
will not notice any kind of difference
between the two having said that there
are a few drawbacks of the budget ipad
firstly is the design like it still has
the old design that has the home button
and so it's less bezel-less than for
example the new ipad air is it's also
got a 10.2 inch non-laminated display
what that basically means is that
there's a bit more of an air gap between
the screen and the stuff underneath it's
not massively relevant you don't really
notice it but if you're writing with an
apple pencil a lot you might notice and
if you have like an ipad air on ipad pro
side by side then you may well notice
some slight difference again i don't
think it's a big enough difference to
justify spending an extra 200 quid on
the ipad air just for the sake of that
laminated air gap but it is something
that is noticeable about the ipad budget
if you hold it side by side with other
ipads the other annoying thing is that
this is compatible with the apple pencil
generation one which means if you want
to charge the apple pencil you can stick
it out of your ipad like this this is
not a very aesthetic way to charge a
pencil and apple pencil whereas with the
other models it's the apple pencil
generation too and so
you can charge it magnetically alongside
the ipad which is just a much nicer way
of dealing with pencil charging having
said that recently they have included
this adapter with the apple pencil
series one so what you can do is you can
put this lightning to lightning adapter
on the back of it and then you can just
charge this via a lightning cable which
is what you can charge your iphone with
or in fact your budget ipad with because
this still uses lightning rather than
usb-c that's not a huge concern like
lightning cable for the pencil lightning
cable for the ipad but it's just a
slight difference between the usb-c
compatible version of the ipad air and
the ipad mini and the ipad pro so
conclusion if you're on any kind of
budget at all i would fully recommend
the budget ipad it's genuinely really
good it gets you 88 of the value of an
ipad without having to pay too much for
it and it starts at 319 pounds and we'll
put the dollar price here as well all
right so let's put that aside next up we
have the next one which is the ipad air
now the ipad air is a 260 pound upgrade
over the ipad budget this starts at 579
pounds again dollar price here and
overall this is a really good middle
ground ipad yes you're paying quite a
lot more you're paying almost double the
price of the budget ipad but there are
things about the ipad air that make it a
pretty compelling alternative to the
budget ipad and what you get because of
these slightly reduced bezels is that in
basically the same form factor of the
bit of the budget ipad you get a very
slightly larger screen so this is 10.9
inch rather than the 10.2 inch on the
budget ipad the great thing about the
ipad air is that it has support for the
apple pencil generation 2 which means
you can charge an apple pencil by
sticking it on the side which is just
very convenient and the apple pencil
generation 2 is just a nicer a nicer
feeling apple pencil it feels a little
bit more
kind of like matte plastic rather than
glossy plastic compared to generation
one it also is more has this like ridge
on it which means it's not gonna fall
off the table and when i was a student
and i used the ipol apple pencil
generation one it would always just end
up like rolling off the table which was
just like super annoying whereas this
one it rolls a bit and then it stops
rolling because it's got this like ridge
on it so apple pencil two is a bit of an
upgrade over the apple pencil one the
display quality is apparently better
than the budget ipad and it does feel
less plasticky it feels more like a
premium product because this is a
laminated rather than non-laminated
display but again unless you hold them
up side by side this isn't really a
thing that you're gonna notice on like
on the daily the ipad air also has usbc
support so for example if you have a
macbook and you charge it by usbc and
you have an ipad you can charge it by
usbc although generally people with
ipads also have iphones and so lightning
versus usbc is not a huge difference
there but if you do want to use third
party accessories it's generally easier
to find usbc accessories for the ipad
air and then it is to find lightning
compatible accessories for the budget
ipad although again i've been using
ipads for like five plus years at this
point and i basically never needed to
plug in an extra accessory because the
ipad just does the job completely fine
on its own so the question here is is
the ipad air worth it compared to the
budget ipad is it worth spending an
extra 260 pounds on upgrading to the
ipad air for the sake of a new a new
design a a slightly upgraded apple
pencil and a slightly different
connectivity in usbc
again it just depends on how much money
you have to burn like i said if you're
in any kind of budget you get 88 of the
value of an ipad from the budget ipad
and yes you could pay an extra like 80
more for the ipad air but you're only
getting an extra 7 value in my kind of
subjective estimation of values of an
ipad and so it's really hard to answer
this question of is it worth it you just
have to decide for yourself is it worth
spending an extra eighty percent cash to
get an extra seven percent improvement i
don't know i would personally but i have
more money to burn and i can buy these
as a business expense and so it really
just depends on what your personal
circumstances are all right newsflash as
of yesterday the ipad air now has the m1
processor which makes it a significant
speed jump from the budget ipad but that
doesn't really change the question of
whether it's worth it because m1 versus
a13 versus a14 i mean for most people
who are in that middle band of the
spectrum so like semi-consumer
semi-creator you're not going to bump
into the limits of an a13 or a14
processor anyway and so the upgrade to
the m1 processor shouldn't be a major
factor it's like oh my god it's such a
speed jump from the ipad budget to the
ipad air having said that the fact that
the ipad air now has m1 means that you
are likely to get a longevity upgrade so
going from a13 to m1 it your ipad is
likely to last longer so if you're
looking to buy something which is then
going to last you for the long term you
might want to consider the ipad air
rather than the budget ipad even though
it's an extra 260 pounds difference
between the two so that was the budget
ipad and the ipad air let's now talk
about the ipad mini which is the one
that i actually have now as my daily
driver now the ipad mini is a bit of a
weird addition to this lineup um it was
always one that's sort of a bit on the
side but the ipad mini is actually 100
pounds cheaper than the ipad air and
it's kind of similar in that it's got
the same kind of design but the form
factor of the ipad mini is obviously
like this and it's very much holdable in
one hand and basically the way i think
of the ipad mini is that it's basically
a glorified kindle so i like using the
ipad mini for reading books or reading
scientific papers while i'm on the go
i'm in the process of writing a book
right now so i have to read a bunch of
papers and it's much easier reading
those on the ipad mini because i can
read it with one hand i can read it on
the train i can read it on ubers i can
read it in public transport i can read
it in cafes and if there's just
something about it holding an ipad air
holding an ipad mini that makes it just
feel more manageable than holding an
ipad air like you have to hold this in
two hands and you kind of need to rest
on something it feels a bit
uncomfortable whereas the ipad mini it's
like it's so nice it's just very much
and holdable in one hand and therefore
makes it better for me at least as a
consumption device now i wouldn't really
use this as a creation device i wouldn't
recommend the ipad mini if you're like a
light creator i would recommend more of
the bigger sized ipads especially if
you're going to do things like
illustration or taking notes but i think
if you are going to use the ipad as
basically a glorified kindle or a
glorified i don't know netflix machine
then actually the ipad mini is a really
solid option annoyingly there isn't
really a first party kind of smart
keyboard attachment for this i thought i
think that would have been nice i would
have used this as like a portable book
writing e typing note taking device on
the go but actually you can get a bunch
of these small bluetooth keyboards and
i've got one which sadly i forgot to
bring to the studio with me today it's
in my bedroom at home i've got one of
those that i occasionally use to type
stuff on on the ipad mini but again
that's a bit of a niche use case if i
need to actually do some typing i'll
just get out my 14-inch macbook pro and
just use that because it's so much
easier than trying to fiddle with typing
on an ipad unless of course you have a
magic keyboard or things like that but
then you're getting into the extra ping
and then paying an extra 300 pounds for
that kind of thing so should you go for
the ipad mini or should you go for the
ipad air i think really the decision
just comes down to the form factor do
you need a smaller ipad would you like a
smaller ipad or do you want something
bigger and the reason i personally go
for the ipad mini is because the ipad
does not replace my laptop i have a
macbook which i literally carry
everywhere i go this is the 14 inch m1
pro macbook pro it's literally in my bag
all the time and i just know i have to
carry it everywhere i go i don't i
really don't go anywhere anywhere
without this and i've actually had the
11 inch ipad pro in my bag for the last
few months at the same time as the as
the macbook pro but i just never use the
ipad pro or the ipad air like when you
have the option of getting a macbook out
and you have to do some quote proper
work
i would just never use an ipad when i
could use the macbook and so for me
there's really no point in having this
kind of middle ground 10.9 or 11 inch
ipad
when i have my macbook for real stuff
but there is actually a point and having
like a glorified kindle in my bag i can
just chuck it in it's very lightweight i
kind of forget that it's there but if i
do want to take it out and i'm in i'm in
a circumstance like in a cramped cafe or
in a library or in public transport
where taking out my macbook is a bit
overkill i can just take out the ipad
mini and i can read some stuff which is
awesome next we come to the 11-inch ipad
pro now this is what i've had in my bag
for the last few months but as i said i
almost never even take it out because
i've got the macbook and it is really
nice it's it's just it's just very
expensive it's 750 pounds and it's such
a it's such a beautiful glorious device
that i you know have gotten a reasonable
amount of use out of but again it's hard
to justify when you have a macbook and
you have an iphone like why would you
need an 11 inch ipad as well at least
for me that's just how i feel about it
maybe your use cases would differ but i
think most things that you can do on an
ipad pro you can also do on the ipad air
you can also do on the budget ipad it
just depends on how much money you want
to spend and yes the ipad pro does have
the new m1 processor as does the ipad
pro 12.9 inch but again realistically
for the vast majority of people you're
never going to notice a difference in
performance between the a13 chip the a14
chip or the m1 chip i certainly have
never noticed i've been dabbling with
these ipads for a while switching ipads
here and there i just never noticed a
speed improvement the only difference i
noticed with the ipad pros is the fact
that they have an incredible display
with the 120 hertz pro motion thing
which makes the display like super super
smooth and the annoying thing about all
the other ipads the non-pro ones is that
they only have 60 hertz displays now
this difference between 60hz and 120hz
it's annoyingly noticeable but it's only
noticeable again if you if you've used a
pro then you are very used to what it
the beautiful buttery smoothness of the
ipad pro display just looks freaking
incredible whereas if you then switch to
an ipad mini or an ipad air like i've
done and you scroll around the screen
you notice that oh oh something about
this just feels bad it just it just it
just doesn't feel as nice it doesn't
look as nice now if the ipad mini had
the option of 120hz promotion display i
would be buying this in a heartbeat
because that's my only beef with the
ipad mini that it doesn't have that
promotion display in fact if they had an
ipad pro and they just shrunk it to the
form factor of an ipad mini i would be
like take my money this is the absolute
perfect ipad for my personal use cases
but yeah i just i just cannot get enough
of the 120hz promotion display is this a
good enough reason to buy the ipad pro i
don't think so i think it's mostly an
aesthetic preference and it's good for
example if you're an artist and you
actually notice the difference between
drawing with an apple pencil in 60hz
versus drawing with an apple pencil 120
hertz these ones also now have face id
it's kind of nice but face id versus
touch id on the side doesn't really make
much difference to my life and the good
news is this has 128 gigabytes of
storage by standard as standard whereas
the other ones have 64 gigabytes as
standard and you know in the past i used
to hate on 64 gigabytes but actually i
now have a 64 gigabyte ipad and i've
realized that i i very rarely store
anything locally because cloud storage
options have become so cheap and so good
these days and i have fast internet
basically everywhere i go and so 64
gigabytes is actually reasonable but
it's kind of nice that for the extra 200
and 300 quid you're paying for the ipad
pro you are getting a little bit extra
storage as well so is the ipad pro worth
it i would say for most people probably
not if you're the sort of person that
needs the performance of the m1 chip you
already know that you need the
performance of the m1 chip and so this
review of me as someone who is not
someone who needs a performance of the
m1 chip shouldn't really sway your
decision one way or another but hey it's
kind of nice to have if you have the
money to burn and let's let's say you're
a student and you've just got rich
parents or you've got a side hustle or
you just have loads of money then 11
inch ipad pro is actually sick if it's
non-trivial for you to spend an extra i
don't know 300 quid to upgrade from the
ipad air for 579 to the ipad pro for 749
then go for the ipad pro you won't
regret it the promotion display is
really really nice but again it just
depends on what sort of budget you're at
it is an extra three percent gain for an
extra
80 cost or like 70 cost it's objectively
not worth it but it just again it just
depends on how much money you have to
burn on the purchase of an ipad oh and
now that the ipad air also has the m1
chip the reason you're upgrading to the
ipad pro i mean it's mostly for the
screen and for the build quality it's
not really for the chip itself and so
the fact that the ipad air now has the
m1 shape makes it even less of a need to
upgrade to the ipad pro but if you know
you need an ipad pro and you need to
have and you know that you need to have
one this generation you already need
that anyway and you probably don't need
this video to explain it and then we
come to the big daddy the 12.9 ipad ipad
pro now this actually used to be my
daily driver i used to use this a lot i
used to use this a lot when i was at the
hospital when i was at work um for
planning videos and things but that was
before the m1 macbooks came out now that
the m1 macbooks are here it's like you
know 13 or 14-inch macbook pro versus
12.9 inch ipad pro even though i've got
this and i've got it with a magic
keyboard and all the accessories and
stuff i just never find myself reaching
for the 12.9 inch ipad pro when i could
just be using my macbook people always
ask the question can an ipad replace
your laptop and i still think five years
later the answer to that question is no
not really it's very hard to fully
replace your laptop with an ipad because
the ipad at the end of the day it's just
an ipad it does still have the
limitations of ipad os it's not a proper
desktop operating system the ipad pro
12.9 is very nice it's got the same
processes and stuff as the 11 inch ipad
pro but it does have a slightly nicer
screen which has slightly more contrasty
blacks again you never notice this
unless you're watching looking at them
side by side i watch things on the ipad
pro sometimes i watch things on the ipad
mini i never think to myself oh god the
blacks on this don't look as black as
they did on the ipad pro unless i'm
doing a review and looking at them side
by side and that's a very artificial
unfair way to test ipads and there's a
bunch of creators i know on the internet
who use the 12.9 inch ipad pro there's
like music producers that plug devices
in and they're like having 4.9 inches
and this is like their go-to device for
making music i'm not one of those people
if you're watching this video i would
hazard a guess that you're probably not
one of those people either and so i
would again unless you just have loads
of money to burn and you really really
want a 12.9 inch huge ass screen maybe
with the magic keyboard it's just very
hard to justify spending all this money
on an ipad pro 12.9 inch so where are we
at the end of all this like i said my
daily driver is now the ipad mini i
don't need an ipad because i have a
macbook to do quite real work but it's
nice having the ipad mini as a glorified
kindle as a consumption device that i
can use one-handed i can just chuck it
into my bag and i can use it whenever
i'm on the go if i were a student and i
had absolutely no money at all i
wouldn't even get an ipad because an
ipad is not a game changer for your
university life save your money use it
for something else but if i were a
student and and was on some kind of
budget and i wanted to spend some money
on tech maybe i wanted to go paperless
with my notes and do handwritten note
taking on the ipad i would go for the
budget ipad if i was on a budget if i
had an extra 300 quid to spare i would
go for the ipad air just because the
conveniences of the apple pencil usbc
and the new design is kind of nice and
if i was a real bowler of a student and
i had like a side hustle and stuff and i
had a business that i could funnel
business expenses through or i just had
really rich parents and stuff i would
probably go for the 11 inch ipad pro
just because why not at that point but
yeah it just sort of depends diminishing
returns you know where you're on the
spectrum and you can decide from that
hopefully what's the best ipad for you
this ipad mini is the one for me by the
way if you're getting an ipad you should
totally put a paper-like screen
protector on it they're not sponsoring
this video but i'll put an affiliate
link in the video description if you
want to check it out i have been using
these guys for that since like 2017 was
when i first got a paper like screen
protector and it's been on my ipad ever
since it's just really good and if you
like this video you might like to check
out this video over here which talks
about my top favorite apps for the ipad
because obviously the device is one
thing but it's really all about the apps
and that video goes over all my favorite
apps for the ipad so thank you so much
for watching hopefully you found this
video useful do hit the subscribe button
if you aren't already and i'll see you
hopefully in the next video bye